<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The litle memorial, concerning the good and fruitfull vse of the sacraments Wherein be handled such defects as some persons commit in the vse of them, and the remedies therein to be practised. Composed in Spanish, by the R. Father Francis Arias of the Society of Iesus, and newlie translated in to our English tongue.</title>
            <title>Del buon uso de los sacramentos. English</title>
            <author>Arias, Francisco.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1602</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 227 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 141 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A21051</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 742</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113868</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849097</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849097</idno>
            <idno type="VID">14230</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A21051)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14230)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1265:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The litle memorial, concerning the good and fruitfull vse of the sacraments Wherein be handled such defects as some persons commit in the vse of them, and the remedies therein to be practised. Composed in Spanish, by the R. Father Francis Arias of the Society of Iesus, and newlie translated in to our English tongue.</title>
                  <title>Del buon uso de los sacramentos. English</title>
                  <author>Arias, Francisco.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24], 253, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By the English secret press],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at Roan [i.e. England :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1602.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of: Del buon uso de los sacramentos.</note>
                  <note>The imprint is false; in fact printed in England by the secret press (STC).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in St. Edmund's College, Ware, Herts.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sacraments --  Catholic Church --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:14230:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE LITLE ME<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MORIAL, <hi>CONCER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NING THE GOOD AND</hi> FRVITFVLL VSE OF THE SACRAMENTS.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wherein</hi> Be handled ſuch defects as ſome perſons commit in the vſe <hi>of them, and the remedies</hi> therein to be practiſed.</p>
            <p>Compoſed in Spaniſh, by the R. Father FRANCIS ARIAS of the Society of Ieſus, and newlie tranſlated in to our Engliſh tongue.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Printed at</hi> Roan. 1602</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:14230:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14230:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE TO the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>EVVIS</hi> of <hi>GRANADA,</hi> that excellent and diuine <hi>Beſeleel</hi> of our time for the building and poliſhing<note place="margin">Exod. 31.</note> of the ſpirituall tabernacle of Chriſtes church, amonge many other his notable monuments, intiteled one: <hi>The Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morial of a chriſtian life.</hi> The firſt parte whereof intreating principallye of the Sacraments of Penance, and the ſacred Communion, was to the ſingular benefitte of our countrey, tranſlated into the Engliſh tongue. God whoſe <hi>hand is not abbreuiated,</hi> hath in<note place="margin">Eſai. c. 59.</note> the ſame nation, rayſed him vp a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion, like an other <hi>Ooliab,</hi> for the<note place="margin">Exod. c. 31.</note> proſecuting of the ſame worke: one of whoſe ſmall treatiſes I haue likewiſe tranſlated, as deſirous to inriche our countrey with ſo ſingular a treaſure: and becauſe it is an <hi>Addition</hi> to a
<pb facs="tcp:14230:3"/> former worke, and ſo by the Author cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led: a name nothing fitting it now, when it commeth forthe alone, therefore haue I thoughte good after the imitation of that learned man, especiallye becauſe as his, ſo this alſo contayneth a briefe note, of that which euery good chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an oughte often to practiſe, concerning the Sacramentes of Pennance, and the holy Communion, to put it forth with the title of a <hi>Memorial:</hi> and the name <hi>(litle)</hi> I haue added, both for diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from the former, and alſo for that it is compriſed in a farre leſſe quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. And althoughe denied it can not be, that not onelie <hi>GRANNADA,</hi> but many others, haue learnedly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated of the ſame ſubiecte, yet who knoweth not, that as mens vaines bee diuers in writing, ſo likewiſe their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections in readinge not all one, and therefore both with profitte and pleaſure, many good workes may bee publiſhed
<pb facs="tcp:14230:3"/> of the ſame matter, the latter either for methode, perspicuitie, or ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther notable thinge, adding ſomewhat which in the former was wanting, and as it were with <hi>Ruth</hi> gathering vp<note place="margin">Ruth. c. 2.</note> ſuch eares of corne, as ſlipped from the reapers handes: and that ſuch labours may fruitfullie bee enterpriſed: beſide reaſon, and common practiſe, wee haue alſo the example of the fower E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangeliſtes, who by direction of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt, as with ſingular vnitie, ſo with profitable varietie, wrote the ſame life and death of our Sauiour Chriſte. This booke therefore, though it intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth of Confeſsion and Communion, the ſubiect of diuers excellent diſcourſes, yet is it worthy to be imbraced, ſeeing the manner and ſcope thereof, is of that qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, as I thinke few can reade it, that will repent their ſmall paines employed, and ſome haply be of opinion, that albeit others with <hi>S. Iohn</hi> came firſt to the<note place="margin">Iohn 20. v. 4.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:14230:4"/> monument, yet that this author with <hi>Saint Peter</hi> entred firſt in: and all ſuch, whoſe harts God ſhal ſo effectually touch, as that they will not onely reade, but alſo carefully practiſe, may with much more reaſon bleſſe the time, that they met with ſo heauenly a maiſter, for the ſauing of their owne ſoules, then e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer did <hi>Dauid</hi> bleſſe <hi>Abigail &amp;</hi> her wiſe ſpeech, hindring him from the kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling<note place="margin">1 Reg. 15. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 32.</note> of an other ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s body. The principal intent of this <hi>Memorial</hi> is, to inflame all with the loue of the Sacraments, and to ſtir vp our dull ſpirits, often to repaire vnto thoſe diuine fountaines of grace, from which ſo many and rare benefittes doe flowe: to diſcouer alſo the vſuall diſorders, into which not only thoſe that be careleſſe, but euen the deuoute ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of God doe ſometimes fall, when they goe to confeſsion, and to receaue the bleſſed Sacrament, togither with ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar remedies, how we may auiod al ſuch
<pb facs="tcp:14230:4"/> inconueniences, and ſo free our ſelues, more &amp; more from ſin, purchaſe greater abundance of grace in this world, and eternall felicitie in the worlde to come: all which pointes he doth ſo excellently performe, and like a diuine phiſition ſearch out the ſecret and lurking diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of our ſoule, and preſcribe ſuch ſweet and heauenly receits, that there is almoſt none ſo voide of ſpirituall ſence, but by reading, ſhal finde theire conſcience tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched: nor any proceeded ſo far in pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but that they may make great bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of this ſmall treatiſe, and generallye all that ſincerely deſire the amendment of their life, and increaſe of vertue, ſhall feele their hartes burning in them, as the two Diſciples did when our Sauior wal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ked<note place="margin">Luc. 24. v. 32.</note> in their company, and opened them the Scriptures.</p>
            <p>One thing there is which the author in diſcourſing of ſuch ſins, as many con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe not through culpable ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, hath
<pb facs="tcp:14230:5"/> omitted, to witte the dangerous error of many yonge perſons, that without the knoweledge or conſent of theire pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, beſtowe themſelues in marriage: and an other no leſſe dangerous then the former, if not more, and that is to make priuie contractes, whereof not only ſuch as liue vnder the charge of theire pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, but others alſo of all eſtates &amp; callinges bee ſome time founde guiltye. Of theſe pointes though paſsing neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, he maketh no mention, becauſe the councell of Trent making all priuie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractes<note place="margin">Seſ. 24. c. 1.</note> of no force, hath freed them fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuch inconueniences, which is not ſo here in our countrey for lacke of publication, a thing required by the councell before that decree can take anye place: and therefore I haue thought good to ſay ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what, both concerning the one &amp; the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, (becauſe they be ſins very rife, and be accompanied with many and greate miſchifes, eſpecially the ſecond, as diſcord
<pb facs="tcp:14230:5"/> betwixt houſes, ruines of families, the perpetuall ſtate of adultery, and not ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome a continuall torment of conſcience, as daily experience teacheth) to the end that ſuch as feare God, &amp; be deſirous to ſaue their ſoules, may know what herein they haue to followe and practiſe.</p>
            <p>As it is certaine, that the marriage of children (beeing of yeares requiſite, and no other impediment hindring it) contracted freche without their parents conſent, is perfect matrimony, and can<note place="margin">Concil. Trid. ſes. 24. cap. 1.</note> not either by them, or the temporal ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate bee broken: certaine alſo that children may ſomtime vpon iuſt &amp; good cauſes, marrie without the knowledge or conſent of their parents, as for example, when they would marrie the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to an heri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke, &amp; in ſome few other caſes: ſo moſt certaine it is, that vſually &amp; for the grea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter part, children doe very much offende God, in contractinge marriage either without their knowledge or againſt the
<pb facs="tcp:14230:6"/> mindes of their parents, ſeing it belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth to their charge to prouide for their children: and their experience and loue towardes them is ſuch, that neither can they be ſo eaſilie deceaued, nor yet pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer them to any matches, then ſuch as be good, and moſt conuenient for their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate: and in holy ſcripture we read, that the marriage of the children, was rather commanded vnto the parents then vnto them: for God ſpeaking of the <hi>Cana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites</hi> ſaith thus. <hi>Thou ſhalt not</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 34. Deutr. 7.</note> 
               <hi>giue thy daughter to his ſon, nor thou ſhalt not take his daughter for thy ſonne:</hi> And bleſsed <hi>Iacob,</hi> vpon the commaundement of his father <hi>Iſaac,</hi> verye obedientlye married the<note place="margin">Geneſ 28.</note> daughter of <hi>Laban,</hi> and not of ſuch as he had forbidden.</p>
            <p>Seeing then marriage is oftentimes with ſin contracted by the children, for lacke of their parents knowledge, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and ſometime without any ſinne at
<pb facs="tcp:14230:6"/> all: ſuch as liue in feare of God, &amp; wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly woulde not offend him, ought not herein to relie vpon themſelues, &amp; their own partiall affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; ſo to determine that in this and this caſe, they may with out any reſpect to their parents conſent, make their owne choiſe: but let them craue the aduiſe of ſome wiſe and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creete ghoſtly father, and with humility ſubmit themſelues to his iudgement: and in any wiſe let them take heed that they doe not herein, refuſe the reſolutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haply of many, &amp; reſt vpon the opinion of ſome one whome they haue found out, becauſe he doth moſte fitte their fancie, and beſt pleaſe their paſſion: for that were a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine argument, that they ſought not ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely the truth, nor the honor of God, but rather a cloake for their ſinne, and a fewe colde figge leaues with <hi>Adam</hi> to<note place="margin">Geneſ. 3. v. 7.</note> couer their naked ſoules. Parentes alſo that be the true ſeruants of God, oughte herein to proceede with great moderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb facs="tcp:14230:7"/> &amp; not to preſſe their children ſo much with their authority, as by feare &amp; vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent meanes to draw them cleane contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to their owne minde and liking, for that were to take away that chriſtian li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie which ought to be in marriage, &amp; without which as ſhall ſtraight waies bee handled, it is no marriage at all, &amp; what pitifull effectes followe ſuch vnfortunate matches, where the terror of the parents more preuaileth, then the reaſonable loue and liking of the children, daily experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence doth teach vs.</p>
            <p>Concerning ſecret marriages and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractes, as the danger is far greater, ſo it deſerueth a deeper conſideration: for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny haply thinke, that herein either no ſin is committed, or a very litle one, ſeeing matrimony is a thing moſt free, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore al at their libertie to contract as they pleaſe. But herein are they much decea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued: for albeit moſt free it is in this ſence that none ought to be enforced thereunto,
<pb facs="tcp:14230:7"/> but muſt willingly and freely giue their owne conſent: and therefore if one ſhould by any kinde of violent meanes bee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled to marry an other, to whome in their hart they gaue no conſent, moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine it is, that it were no matrimony at all: yea the violence &amp; feare may be ſuch that albeit inward conſent be wrung out &amp; gotten, yet is it not marriage for lacke of free conſent. I touch this matter brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as being not that whereof I mean now to intreat: if any haue herein any diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultie, and deſire farther reſolution, let them craue the counſell of thoſe that bee vertuous and learned, with that purity of intention before mentioned. Yet for all this, in other thinges marriage is not ſo free, that men or wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may either mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie with whom they liſt, or in what ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner they pleaſe. For by the lawe of God, and the church, they are forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den to marry with ſuch as hee allied to them in certayne degrees of conſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guinitie
<pb facs="tcp:14230:8"/> and affinitie: and if any ſhould preſume ſo to doe, beſides a greate mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal ſin committed, the marriage alſo is of no force, and their ſtate damnable. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can they marrie in ſuch manner as they pleaſe: for to omit other caſes, and to ſpeake of that which we haue nowe in hande. If any heere in our country, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracte marriage priuilie, althoughe the marriage be of force, yet cannot the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of doing be excuſed from ſin, &amp; that ſuch a one, as doth oftentimes plunge the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into a perpetuall miſery, a point worthy to be deepely conſidered of al ſorts of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons: for what caſe can be more lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, then when two haue contracted ſecretly, and made themſelues man and wife before God: and yet afterwarde, either vpon the diſlike of their friends, or diſcontentment growing betweene them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, they goe backe, marrie openly o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and ſo all their life time continue in the ſtate of adulterie, and that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb facs="tcp:14230:8"/> all helpe, in reſpecte of any outward courte or conſiſtorie: for ſeeing the firſt marriage was ſecret, the church can take thereof no knowledge and ſo prouide no remedie. For the auoiding of this ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite an inconuenience, the churche of God, tendering like a carefull mother the good of her children, hath vtterly forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den ſuch kindes of contracts, as the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel of Trent teſtifieth in theſe words. <hi>The</hi>
               <note place="margin">Seſ. 21. c. 1.</note> 
               <hi>holy church of God vpon iuſte cauſes hath alwaies deteſted and forbidden ſecret marriages.</hi> Hee therefore that is the ſeruant of God, and woulde not willingly wounde his ſoule with ſin, nor offende againſt the precepte of the church, nor yet caſt himſelfe into a ſea of miſeries, ought to refraine from all ſuch priuie contracts, and as much as can be, to obſerue the decree of the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid<note place="margin">Vbi ſupra</note> councell, which is to contract matri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony in the preſence of a prieſt, &amp; two or three witneſſes, at the leaſt. Good cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell
<pb facs="tcp:14230:9"/> alſo it is, eſpecially for yong perſons, whoſe iudgments are weaker, experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce leſſe, &amp; their paſsio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly more ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, not to make ſo much as any ſecret promi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes of marriage, no thoughe conditionall: as if ſuch a portio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or ioynter may be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured, or if my friendes ſhall be content, &amp; ſuch like, for proceſſe of time, much talking of ſuch matters, &amp; other like ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents, make them afterward to doubt, if anye future breach happen, whether they bee cleere in conſcience, and may ſecurely marry elſe where or no, &amp; ſo al ſuch kinde of promiſes in concluſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſerue for nothing elſe but to afflict the ſoule, &amp; to weary the conſcience with many ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples: fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al which miſeries they be cleare, that keepe themſelues free from all priuie contractes, and ſecret promiſes of what manner ſo euer, and doe neuer bind them ſelues, but in ſuch ſort as before was me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned: or elſe expect vntill their matri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony be publiquely ſolemnized.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:14230:9"/>
            <p>Although I ſaid before that the ſtate of him that was priuilie contracted, and did after marry ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly with an other, was without helpe: yet God forbid that any ſhould in that caſe diſpaire, for God who is rich in mercie and will not the death of a ſinner like the good <hi>Samaritane,</hi> hath in ſtore oyle and wine to powre in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to<note place="margin">Luc. 10. v. 30.</note> the woundes of him that hath thus pittifully fallen into the hands of theues, and is lefte halfe dead: and therefore though true it be, that ſuch a one, as I ſaide before, hath no remedye in anye worldlye courte or conſiſtorie, yet in the court of conſcience, meanes are left for the ſauing of his ſinfull ſoule. The medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine I confes falleth out ordinarilie to be verie ſower and ſharpe, yet if men wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linglye venture the loſſe of a limme for the preſeruing of the corruptible bodie, though haply they fell into that extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie without any fault of their owne: no reaſon haue they to refuſe any remedy,
<pb facs="tcp:14230:10"/> though neuer ſo penitentiall, for the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of their immortall ſoule: ſeing eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially by their owne folly they haue gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven themſelues ſo deepe a wound. Where<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore ſuch as finde their conſcience herein troubled, let them make choiſe of ſome excellent, wiſe, diſcrecte, and learned ghoſtly father, for the well managing of this buſines, being ſo important and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous. Thus much gentle reader haue I thought good to inſert here in the preface, being a thing paſsing neceſſary (and yet omitted by the Author vpon the reaſon before mentioned) and as I verily hope, that which will bee the occaſion for the preſeruing of ſuch as feare God, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny great ſins, which otherwiſe through ignorance they might fall into. Now no more remaineth, but that thou wouldeſt for thy further direction, to the end thou mayeſt auoide many impediments which hinder others that be careleſſe from re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceauing that abundant co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>moditie which
<pb facs="tcp:14230:10"/> is gained by deuout frequenting of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion and the holy communion vouch<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſafe attentiuely to peruſe this ſmall trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, and I doubt not but that thou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> in comparing the Author with others of our time, that intreat of the ſame mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, ſay of him as they did in the goſpell of our Sauiour. <hi>Neuer did there</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioan 7. v. 46.</note> 
               <hi>man ſo ſpeake as this man.</hi> If thou doubteſt (as <hi>Nathaniel</hi> did of Chriſt) and demande how in ſo ſmall a booke ſo great learning or deuotion can bee contained: I willinglye ſurceaſe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> other anſwers, &amp; ſay with <hi>S. Philip Come and</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioan. 1. v. 46.</note> 
               <hi>ſee:</hi> Reade and iudge.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:14230:11"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A TABLE OF THE</hi> CHAPTERS.</head>
            <p n="1">I OF the great neceſſitie, which all chriſtians haue, often to fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent the Sacraments of Confeſſion and the holy Communion.</p>
            <p n="2">II Of a certaine diſorder, into which ſome doe fall, by excuſing and defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding their ſinnes, in the ſacrament of confeſſion, and how they are therein to be mortified.</p>
            <p n="3">III Of the diſorder in confeſſing ſuch ſinnes as be certaine, with doutfull wordes, and which doe not ſignifie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſinne at all.</p>
            <p n="4">IIII Of the diſorder in confeſſing venial ſinnes, without hauing for them anye griefe, or purpoſe of amendment.</p>
            <p n="5">V Of a certaine careleſneſſe which vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally is founde amonge ſuch as be deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to ſerue God, concerning the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination of their conſcience before confeſſion, &amp; the great harmes which doe followe thereof.</p>
            <p n="6">VI Of ſome ſinnes of ignorance, which a man knoweth not, nor confeſſeth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to wit, to be careleſſe to knowe whereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to in particular he is bounde, and to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit
<pb facs="tcp:14230:11"/> the workes of iuſtice and charity.</p>
            <p n="7">VII Of diuers kindes of wicked ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitions, not knowne to many, &amp; ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times not confeſſed through culpable ignorance.</p>
            <p n="8">VIII Of ſinnes committed by playing, and gaming: and beholding of vaine &amp; hurtful ſightes, into which many do fall through culpable ignorance.</p>
            <p n="9">IX Of other ſinnes more ſecret, as pride of our owne proper iudgement, and ſelfe will, which many doe not know nor confeſſe through culpable igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.</p>
            <p n="10">X Of a very profitable remedy againſte the harme which commeth by ſecret ſinnes &amp; that is euery day to examine our conſcience: and the manner howe this is to be done.</p>
            <p n="11">XI Of an other ſingular meanes for a man to deliuer him ſelfe from ſecret ſinnes, and that his confeſſions may be more fruitfull, and that is to haue one certaine ghoſtly father, vnto whom he ought ordinarily to confes his ſins.</p>
            <p n="12">XII Of an other excellent remedy, to deliuer our ſelues from the harme of ſecret ſinnes, and to ſupplie the defects
<pb facs="tcp:14230:12"/> of our former confeſſions, and that is with care and diligence, to make a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall confeſſion.</p>
            <p n="13">XIII Of ſuch defectes as be an impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to many which doe often com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate, that they receaue not the plentifull fruite of the B. Sacrament.</p>
            <p n="14">XIIII How for the receauing of more abundant fruite of the holy communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, conuenient it is to purifie the ſoule from veniall ſinnes.</p>
            <p n="15">XV How to receaue much fruite of the bleſſed communion, neceſſary it is for a man to prepare himſelfe with recol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection, and meditation: &amp; what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of meditations are good to be vſed for that purpoſe.</p>
            <p n="16">XVI Of that outwarde reuerence, hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie, and modeſtie, with which we ought to come vnto the B. Sacrament.</p>
            <p n="17">XVII Of that quiet and repoſe, with which we ought to come vnto the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly communion: and what thankes are to be giuen vnto God after the recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing thereof.</p>
            <p n="18">XVIII How to abſtaine from the B. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament without iuſt cauſe, is an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediment to ſpirituall profit: and how
<pb facs="tcp:14230:12"/> that neither for negligence, or lacke of ſenſible deuotion, a man ſhould giue ouer the holy communion.</p>
            <p n="19">XIX How for ſcruples and vaine feares, we ought not to abſtaine from the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of the Altar.</p>
            <p n="20">XX With what moderation we ought to frequent the holy communion, that we doe not therein exceede, nor doe any thing contrary to due reuerence: and how we ought to leaue this to the iudgement of a diſcreet ghoſtly father.</p>
            <p n="21">XXI Of ſuch rules as holy men preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be, concerning the often receauing of the B. Sacrament.</p>
            <p n="22">XXII Of that diſcretion which ghoſtly fathers ought herein to obſerue, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the doctrine of holy men.</p>
            <p n="23">XXIII Whether the holy communion ought daily to be giuen to ſome per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of our time.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:14230:13"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14230:13"/>
            <head>THE LITLE MEMO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RIALL OF A CHRI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STIAN LIFE.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>Chap. I.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Wherein is briefely declared, the great neceſsitie, which all Chriſtians haue, often to frequent the Sacrament of Confeſsion, and the holy Communion.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>OR as much as this booke, is publiſhed for the commodity of ſuch perſons, as be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to ſerue God, by ſetting downe before their eyes, ſuch meanes as they haue to vſe, both for the preſerving them ſelues, and alſo proceeding for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in his divine ſervice: and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:14230:14"/> further to exhort them, to put thoſe meanes in practiſe: and ſeing one of them, and that of great force &amp; efficacy, is to fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent the Sacraments, that is, often to be confeſſed, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue the holy communion: two things are here for this purpoſe, eſpecially to be handled.</p>
               <p>The firſt is, to exhort al faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Chriſtians, often to repaire to theſe holy ſacraments, by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring the great &amp; wonderfull commodities, which by meanes of them be obtayned. The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond is, to teach and inſtruct them, concerning the true and laudable vſe of the ſacrament of Confeſſion, and the holy ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Aultar: and becauſe to entreate copiouſly of theſe poynts, were too much for this ſmall booke, therefore touching
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:14230:14"/> this matter, I intend onelie to ſpeake of that, which to me ſhall ſeeme moſt neceſſary, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be noted, of ſuch as be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to ſerue God. The firſt poynt therefore which I meane to handle, ſhall be briefly to ſet downe before our eyes, how ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary it is, for al Chriſtians, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to frequent the divine ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Confeſſion, and the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Communion: the ſecond ſhall be to proſecute in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, ſuch abuſes and diſorders, as be more ſecret, and into which, even thoſe that be determined to ſerue God, doe not ſeldome fall.</p>
               <p>Concerning the firſt. Many &amp; very effectuall be the reaſons, which ought to moue and invite all faithful chriſtians to frequent the Sacraments, that is, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:14230:15"/> themſelues, and communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate once in eight, or fifteene daies, or at leaſt once a moneth. For if they be ſuch perſons, as God hath voutchſafed ſo to fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, that ſince their laſt confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, they haue not fallen into a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny mortall ſinne, very neceſſary it is for them ſo to doe, both to preſerue themſelues in Gods grace, &amp; to increaſe in the ſame, and alſo in all other vertuous &amp; heavenly gifts: to make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues daiely more acceptable in the ſight of God: to be more fit inſtruments to ſet forth his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, &amp; to advance the good of his Church: to make their ſalvation more certaine: to lay vp the trea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſure of greater merits in eternall felicity: to procure more light, and ſtrength, both to know, and overcome all the temptations &amp;
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:14230:15"/> deceipts of the enemies of our ſoule: to doe the workes of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, with greater facilitie and ſweetnes: to paſſe over this life, with more peace, and ſpirituall comfort: to be at our death more aſſiſted and holpen, of God with plenty of heavenly ſuccor: and ſo finally to depart this life, with more hope of ſalvation, greater quiet, and comfort of ſoule. For theſe, and ſuch other like effects, and ſingular commodities, very neceſſary it is, I ſay, that the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant of God ſhould often re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire to the ſacraments. For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit ſince his laſt confeſſion hee hath not fallen into any mortall ſinne, yet certaine it is, that hee hath committed many veniall, wherof ſome he doth know, and others, he doth not, and yet for all that not to be excuſed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:14230:16"/> he might well haue known them: and theſe veniall or ſmall ſinnes, although they doe not ſpoile the ſoul of gods grace, yet doe they great harme, and put a man in ſuch a caſe, that he doth thereby fal the ſooner into thoſe that be mortall, as elſe where hath beene handled: Certaine<note place="margin">In tract. 4. cap. 24.</note> likewiſe it is, that a man is conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually aſſaulted with daiely and divers tentations by the devill, the world, the fleſh, &amp; our cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt nature, which doe put him in great danger, to fall into mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall ſinne: and many of them be ſecret, and very perilous, and therefore paſſing neceſſary it is, that he ſhould alwaies haue a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy to deliver his ſoule from veniall ſinnes, and great neede he hath of daiely ſtrength, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt all tentations: great neede
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:14230:16"/> of the continuall dew of Gods grace from heaven, to mitigate his wicked inclinations: and all this doth he find in the holy Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments of confeſſion, &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, if he do often frequent them. And although it cannot be denied, but that there bee o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther remedies, for the purging of veniall ſinnes, ſo moſt certain it is, that this of frequenting the Sacraments, if it bee done as it ought, is the beſt, and moſt effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall of all other. Of the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull effects, which the bleſſed ſacrament of the Altar worketh in them that doe frequent it. <hi>S. Bernard</hi> giveth an excellent teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony: theſe be his words. <hi>The</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ber. in ſer. de ce. dom.</note> 
                  <hi>moſt pretious ſacrament of the body of our Lord, doth worke in vs two effects: The one is, that it doth diminiſh the ſence of veniall ſinnes: and the other is,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:14230:17"/> that it doth wholy take away all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, to mortall ſinnes.</hi> And the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly man, doth proue this to bee true, by that experience, which the ſervants of God doe find &amp; feele in their owne heartes, to whome he doth there ſpeake in this manner. <hi>If any of you, doe not now ſo often feele, neither yet ſo greate motions as before time you did, of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, of envie, of carnality, and other vices, let him giue thankes to the body and bloud of Chriſt, which hee recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth in the holy ſacrament, becauſe this is the effect thereof, and let him take comfort therein, for as much as God by this meanes doth cure and make ſound the corruption of our nature.</hi> Thus writeth <hi>S. Bernard.</hi> And the ſelfe ſame thing is confeſt by all holy men: and the generall councell of Trent, doth confirm the ſame<note place="margin">Seſ. 13. c. 8.</note> declaring, that the bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:14230:17"/> doth worke this in all ſuch, as receaue it with due pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration, to wit that it doth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver them from conſenting to tentations, pacifie their paſſions, giue them victory over their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, preſerue and encreaſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in good life, by giving force and ſtrength for al theſe foreſaid ends. And from hence it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth that in al cities &amp; townes, where there be many, that often repaire to the ſacraments, many there be alſo, which all their life long continue in Gods grace, without ever falling into any mortall finne: And all ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ghoſtly fathers, be witneſſes of this trueth, who find by expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, that chriſtian people doe receaue this great commoditye by frequenting the Bleſſed ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of the Aultar with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:14230:18"/> and a vertuous diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>Theſe reaſons aleadged, are ſufficient to perſwade all good Catholicks though not guilty in their conſcience, of any mortall ſin, often to confes themſelues, and to communicat: but if ſince their laſt being at co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſion they haue committed any deadly ſin, then beſides the former reaſons, greater neceſſitye haue they ſtreight waies, and without de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay, to goe vnto the ſacrament of Confeſſion: to witt, that by meanes thereof, they may come out of that damnable ſtate, and deliver themſelus, from all thoſe miſchiefes and harmes, which from that kind of ſin do growe: as to be hated of God, &amp; to liue in diſgrace of the Bleſſed Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: to bee abhorred of heavenly
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:14230:18"/> Maieſty, and to be captiues and ſlaues to Sathan the prince of darkeneſſe: to be ſubiect, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient to his will, and to loſe the great value and merits of all the good works of their life paſt: to be in apparant danger of fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling into greater ſins, into grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter blindnes, and hardeneſſe of hart, and finally into everlaſting damnation. From al theſe evils, and miſchiefs, and many more, annexed to theſe, that man is delivered, who after due prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, purgeth his ſoul ſtreight waies by confeſſion. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though true it be, that onely by contritio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, with a purpoſe to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe in time convenient, a man may deliver himſelfe, from the ſtate of mortall ſin: yet to haue contrition without helpe of the ſacrament, is an hard thing, vnto
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:14230:19"/> which few doe attaine: for as much, as true contrition, contei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth in it ſelfe, a great hatred of ſinne, by reaſon wherof, the ſoul doth in will abhorre and deteſt, all mortall ſinne, more then all other evils in the world, &amp; with all a firme purpoſe of amendme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of life: and ſo reſolutely deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mineth, never more to conſent to any deadly ſinne whatſoever, neither for intereſt or commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity, nor to avoide any paine or miſery of this life: and togither with this, neceſſary it is, that the principall thing, which moveth a man to this hatred of ſin, and amendment of his life, bee the loue of God aboue all thinges. And becauſe men commonlye vpon their forſaking of mortall ſinne, doe it not at the firſt, for this ſupernaturall loue of God,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:14230:19"/> but principally for feare of Hell and damnation: for this cauſe a very hard and rare thing it is, to haue contrition without the helpe of the ſacraments: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of it commeth to paſſe, that ſuch as haue ſinned mortally, and go not to the ſacrament of cenfeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, commonly they continue ſtil in the ſame bad eſtate, and ſo be ſubiect to al thoſe miſchiefes and dangers, which accompany mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall ſinne, as before hath beene ſaid: And the reaſon heereof is, becauſe ordinarily without help of the ſacraments, men ariue not to haue contrition, which yet is neceſſary to come out of mortal ſin: but when they go to confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion with that preparatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which is requiſite, if their ſoul be infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, ſtreight waies are they deli<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vered from mortall ſin, &amp; from
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:14230:20"/> all thoſe miſchiefes before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned: for when a man confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth him ſelf having a perfect ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred of ſinne, &amp; a firme purpoſe of amendment, although the principall reaſon which moveth him, to forſake ſin, be the feare of his owne damnation, yet with the helpe of the ſacrament, ſhall he obtaine Gods grace: and this is that which Divines teach, and the holy councell of Trent doth<note place="margin">Seſ. 14. c. 4.</note> declare, to witt that of attrite he becommeth contrite. For ſuch was the infinite mercy of God, now in the lawe of grace, as to beſtowe ſuch efficacy vpon his ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, that to him that wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth grace, and doth not of his part, put any ſtoppe, or impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, grace by meanes of them is given him, and to him that is already in grace, the ſame is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:14230:20"/> and augmented.</p>
               <p>Theſe be in ſumme, the moſt excellent commodities which faithfull people doe gaine by of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten repayring to the Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of Confeſſion, and communion: and theſe bee the pittifull and moſt grievous evils, from which they be delivered. He therfore that is deſirous of ſalvation, and reſolved to ſerue God, and pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dereth well this point, how can he let ſo great commodities ſlip out of his handes? how dareth he adve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture the loſſe of ſo great gaine? how can he excuſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe from frequenting confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the ſpring of life, and ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, by meanes whereof hee is delivered from ſuch notable e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils of death, ſinne, and everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting damnation? and ſuch pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of ſoul obtained, ſuch divine
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:14230:21"/> and ſpirituall beawty, and ſuch treaſures of grace and glorie? And how can he containe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe and not go often to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Sacrament of the Aultar? the bread of life, the death of ſinne, the wel-ſpring of vertues, the medecine of our paſſions, the ſtaffe and ſtay of our weakenes, the treaſure of graces, the moſt pleaſant repaſt of all heavenlye comfort, the roote of immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litye, and the fountaine of all goodnes. And thus much may ſuffice, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the firſt point. Now will I come to the ſecond, which is the principal thing that I inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded to intreat of, &amp; wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of in very deede, we ſtand moſt in neede and ought carefully to be inſtructed in the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:14230:21"/>
               <head>Chap. II.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of a certaine diſorder, into which ſome doe fall, by excuſing and defending their ſinnes, in the Sacrament of Confeſsion, and how they are therin to be mortified.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>MY purpoſe is not heere to note great and mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt defects, into which ſuch as be careleſſe of ſalvation vſuallye doe fall: as to come to confeſſion without having before hande thoughte vppon their ſinnes: to conceale in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion ſome great ſinne, either for feare or worldely ſhame: to confeſſe their ſinnes without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny purpoſe of amendinge their former life, &amp; to avoide al dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous occaſions of mortall ſin:
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:14230:22"/> which bee ſuch notable defects, and hainous ſinnes, that they do wholy hinder al that fruit which ſhould come by confeſſion, and make it nothing worth at al, and ſo bound they are to confeſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine the ſelfe ſame ſinnes, and alſo that fault of ſacrilege, which they then committed in making ſo wicked a confeſſion.</p>
               <p>But my intent is, to note cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine negligences and defectes, which proceede from the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed inclinations of our corrupt nature, &amp; be found in ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons as are deſirous of ſalvation, and reſolved to leade a vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous life, which convenient it is, that they ſhould avoid, by mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifying the rootes fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce they doe ſpring. One of theſe diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders is, for a man in confeſſion to excuſe and defend his ſinnes,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:14230:22"/> putting vpon them divers ſorts of colours, to the end they may ſeeme not ſo grievous &amp; filthy, as in deede they be: As for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe of themſelues, ſome ſay, that they ſinned becauſe they could not chooſe: which is moſt falſe, for God doth not bind any to that which is impoſſible. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſay, that althoughe they gaue conſent vnto the ſinne, as in deſiring of revenge, or ſome vncleane act, yet did that cogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation quickely paſſe away, and ſtayed not long in their heart: &amp; by this meanes, though the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent were deliberat, yet woulde they bee thought, not to haue committed any ſinne, or if they did, that it was but a ſmall one: whereas moſt certaine it is, that if they did not reſiſt the paſsion, but gaue deliberat conſent there
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:14230:23"/> vnto, that they ſinned, thoughe the conſent continued never ſo ſmall a time. And if the thinge to which they gaue conſent, was any notable iniury to their neigh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bour, or fornication, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuch weighty matter, then was that conſent a mortall ſin, &amp; it importeth not, that it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued but a litle while, for that did not proceede from his owne vertue, but for that the fury of the paſsion was now ended. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers excuſe themſelues, laying the fault vpon the Devil, ſaying: The Devill tempted me, and it was he that beguiled mee, and made me to ſin: Others excuſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues aſcribing al the blame to their neighbours, that gaue them occaſion of ſinning, ſaying thus: If I offended god, the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon was, becauſe they asked me,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:14230:23"/> and were ſo importunat that I could not excuſe my ſelfe, or it was becauſe they firſt gaue mee diſgratious and bad wordes, or offered me this iniury, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced me againſt my will, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne them the like ſpeech again and to offer them the like mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. Others defend and excuſe their ſinne, farre worſe then the former, &amp; that is by attributing the fault to God himſelfe, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: God hath given me ſuch a nature, ſo wicked a complexion, and ſo prone to naughtines that although I doe what I can, and enforce my ſelfe never ſo much, yet can I not avoide theſe ſins, nor reſiſt theſe tentations. All which is falſe &amp; a great vntruth, for neither the Devill, nor any man, can compell one to ſinne, if freely and voluntarily of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:14230:24"/> he will not ſinne, neither doth God ever giue over to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowe vpon man in this life, all that helpe which is neceſſary, &amp; requiſite, not to conſent to ſin, if man himſelfe would take the benefit thereof.</p>
               <p>This ſo great a diſorder in man, groweth of pride, &amp; a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine preſumption, by reaſon whereof, he eſtemeth of himſelf, and would alſo be eſteemed of others, more then is lawful, and is afraide of that confuſion, and diſgrace, which for his ſinnes he deſerveth. So ſaith <hi>S. Gregory</hi> in theſe wordes: <hi>Our harts filled with</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In moral. lib. 22. c. 8. in edit. nou.</note> 
                  <hi>pride, if it doth ought worthy of blame, that doth it conceale and hide, and would not openly confeſſe it, to haue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny remedy thereof.</hi> And this diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, deſcendeth vnto vs by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritaunce from Adam, for as
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:14230:24"/> from him, we inherit originall ſinne, ſo likewiſe by way of incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation do we inherit the increaſe of ſin, and that is to excuſe the ſame. Adam ſinned, and God very mercifully came vnto him, and demanded certaine queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to the end that by acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging and confeſsing his fault<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and accuſing himſelfe from his hart, hee might haue obtained pardon. But Adam defended his ſinne and excuſed himſelfe, laying al the fault vpon the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man: and the woman being aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, ſhe likewiſe excuſed herſelf laying the blame vpon the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, which was the Devil: and and as <hi>S. Gregory</hi> ſaith, both of them were in a certaine manner<note place="margin">Greg ibid. ſupra c. 9.</note> willing, to lay all the ſinne vpon God himſelfe: for what was it elſe for Adam to ſay, the woman
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:14230:25"/> which thou gaveſt me, made me to ſinne, but to inſinuat that god was the cauſe of his ſinne, in that he created the woman? And for the woman to ſay: The Serpent deceaved me, what was it elſe, but to aſcribe the ſinne vnto God, as the cauſe thereof, for that he placed the ſerpent in Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe? And thus by excuſing themſelues in this maner, they procured againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, two great evils and paſsing notable harmes. The one was, that they did ſtop and hinder the mercy of God, and obtained not pardon of their ſinne, at that time: for this was the very cauſe why god demaunded of the Devill no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all, becauſe neither would he pardon him, neither was he capable of penance: and of Adam and Eue did hee aske
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:14230:25"/> certaine queſtions for that hee was deſirous that they ſhoulde with ſorrowe, haue confeſſed their ſinnes, and by their hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and ſimple confeſsion, not excuſing it, haue obtained full pardon at his handes. The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conde harme which they did, was, that by excuſing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues they encreaſed their ſinne, and made it more grieuous then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe it was: whereof enſued, that albeit afterwarde through penance which they did, they were pardoned: yet had the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don ſo great a puniſhment an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed, as was the deſtruction of the whole worlde, and their ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment for the ſpace of nine hundred and odde yeares vpon earth, and afterwarde impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for the ſpace of three or foure thouſand yeares in that
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:14230:26"/> place of hell called Abrahams boſome, or <hi>Limbus patrum.</hi> In the very ſame manner doth it fare with all the children of Adam, that defende and excuſe their ſinnes: for by laying the fault v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon his creatures, vpon aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities and tentations, they doe in a certaine ſecret manner, attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute them to God himſelfe, who is the maker of all creatures, and the author of all the euils of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment and affliction: and by theſe meanes, doe they encreaſe and multiply their ſinne, and greatly ſtop and hinder the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of God, who woulde pardon their offences. For ſo noteth <hi>S. Gregory</hi> in theſe words. <hi>It is a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In Moral. vbi ſupra.</note> 
                  <hi>vice amongst men, to hide them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues for the committing of ſinne, and after the committing being asked, to denie it, and being conuinced thereof,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:14230:26"/> to defend and excuſe it, by which the ſinne is encreaſed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This ſo wicked a paſsion, and diſorder, we ought to ouercome and mortifie, by confeſsing all our ſinnes plainely and clearely, with all the greatnes they haue, and to lay all the fault vpon our ſelues, confeſsing our ſelues to be the true and entire cauſe of them, and to attribute all that we doe vnto our ſelues: for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though true it be, that the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels doe tempt vs, and men per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade and provoke vs to wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſſe, yet is man for all that alwaies free, and at liberty, and hath ſufficient helpe from God to withſtand tentations, and not to conſent vnto any ſinne at all, and therefore ought hee to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe and blame himſelfe and not any creature elſe whatſoeuer.
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:14230:27"/> Let him not therefore ſay in his defence, the Diuell did tempte me, nor my neighbour gaue me occaſion, and made me to ſinne: but let him ſay from the bottom of his heart, I am he that did the ſinne, and all the fault is wholly mine, becauſe voluntarily and of mine owne free will I gaue conſent thereunto: and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as it was in my power to haue ſhunned ſuch dangers and oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions, which I ought to haue done, yet did I not auoide them: and being able againſt the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of the enemy, to haue holpen &amp; ſtrengthened my ſelfe with prayer, penance, workes of mercy, ſpirituall talke, and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of good bookes: yet did I not for that purpoſe, vſe either theſe or any other ſuch like mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, which God did inſpire into
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:14230:27"/> my ſoule, and therefore all the fault is mine owne, and all the cauſe of my harme remayneth in my ſelfe: for that ſaying of <hi>Saint Chryſoſtom</hi> is moſt true, that none<note place="margin">Tomo 5. hom. quod nemo ledi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. &amp;c.</note> receaueth any hurt but of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, becauſe there is not any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther true harme or damage in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede, but that which ſinne cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, and that neuer can be, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept a man doth willingly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent thereunto. And when a man confeſſeth his ſinnes with this kinde of purity, let him haue great care that he doe not either pretend or deſire to be accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted humble for ſo doing, or to be eſteemed for a good penitent man, for this were to flie from one kinde of pride, and to fal in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an other: but let his principal intent be, to be taken for a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and to be for his ſinnes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:14230:28"/> reprehended, and to haue ſpirituall phiſicke giuen him, as to a ſinner: Of which minde of his, it will be a good ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument and teſtimonie, if when his ghoſtly father doth blame &amp; rebuke him for his ſinnes, and intreate him as a ſinner, he take it patiently and well: for if hee accuſe him ſelfe plainely as a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and yet wil not be delt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all nor reprehended as a ſinner, it is a ſigne that he doth not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe or accuſe himſelfe ſincerely from his hart. This is the opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Saint Gregory</hi> whoſe wordes be theſe. <hi>True confeſsion which wee</hi>
                  <note place="margin">22. Moral. cap. 20. in edit. noua. Caſſian. col lat. 18. c. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>make of our ſinnes, is tried by the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion which is giuen vs, for thoſe ſinnes which wee confeſſe: for if being rebuked for them we defend them with pride: certaine it is, that we confeſſed them not ſincerely, for it is the ſinne of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:14230:28"/> pride, not willingly to heare that at the mouth of an other which a man doth willingly confeſſe of himſelfe. And if when we confeſſe our ſelues to be ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, we did likwiſe with true humility acknowledge our ſelues for ſuch when we are blamed or rebuked for our ſins, neuer would we denie or defend them.</hi> Thus writeth <hi>S. Gregory:</hi> out of whoſe words we learne what the intent of a true penitent ought to be in confeſsing his ſins ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie and plainely, and without excuſing them, and that is, not to be accounted iuſt, or to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerenced for ſuch a one, but to be confounded, humbled, and reprehended, as a ſinfull man.</p>
               <p>So great is the vertue of this ſincere and humble confeſsion, that by meanes thereof a ſinner doth penetrate the heauens, is preſented in the ſight of God,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:14230:29"/> and doth prouoke his infinite mercy to pardon and diſcharge him, from all paine due to his ſinnes, and to beſtowe vpon him great rewards: for as poore beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers the more they doe lay open their pouertye and ſhewe their ſoares, to men of mercy &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſsion, ſo much the more they moue their pitty, and receaue from them great almes: even ſo when ſinfull men doe diſcouer the miſery of their ſinnes, and more amplifie and ſtand vpon them, the more they doe blame and accuſe themſelues for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting them: ſo much the more do they incline the clemency of Almighty God, to take compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and pitty vpon them, and to beſtowe vpon them in greater a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance, the moſt pretious giftes of his diuine grace. Very
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:14230:29"/> well was Dauid acquainted with this quality of God, when hee ſpake thus vnto him. <hi>Pardon my</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 24.</note> 
                  <hi>ſinne O Lord, for it is great.</hi> He ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed not his ſinne, nor made it leſſe, but did plainely confeſſe it and that with all the grieuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe thereof, the more to moue the pitty of God to pardon and forgiue him. An excellent wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes alſo is that good theefe, who hanging vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Croſſe confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed his ſinnes, and not with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſes laide the fault vpon others but accuſed &amp; blamed himſelfe, acknowledging himſelfe worthy of all ſhame and puniſhment for them, as himſelfe plainely decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, ſpeaking thus to the other theefe. <hi>We doe iuſtly ſuffer this pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke 23. ver. 41.</note> 
                  <hi>for our owne wicked life doth deſerue it.</hi> And for this humble and contrite confeſsion of his,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:14230:30"/> he receaued ſtraight waies par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don for his ſinnes, and was in a moment abſolued from all pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment both eternal and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall, and had alſo that day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed vpon him the poſſeſsion and ioyes of the kingdome of heauen. Theſe be the wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full effects, which a pure confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion voide of all excuſes, and which proceedeth from a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trite and humble heart worketh in the ſight of God: for it doth forthwith pacifie God, take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way his anger and wrath, which he had conceaued againſt the ſinner, reuoketh all his threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninges of euerlaſting tormentes pronounced againſt him, &amp; tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth them into mercy, into the giftes of grace, and eternall glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. Wherefore great reaſon we haue to craue of God, praying
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:14230:30"/> thus with Dauid. <hi>Suffer not my</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 140.</note> 
                  <hi>hart O Lord, to conſent vnto ſuch mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious and proude wordes, that I doe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe and defend my ſinnes.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>Chap. III.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of the diſorder in confeſsing ſuch ſins as be certaine, with doubtfull wordes, and which doe not ſignifie any ſinne at all.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>AN other diſorder which v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually ſpringeth alſo from the ſame roote, and into which thoſe alſo doe fall, that come of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to the Sacrament of Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, is, for a man to confeſſe his ſins with ſuch kind of words, as ſignifie not any fault, nor im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port any ſinne at all, as for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, to ſay: I confeſſe my ſelfe of theſe my faultes and imperfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions.
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:14230:31"/> I accuſe my ſelfe, that I haue had litle patience, litle hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, and ſmall charity. I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe my ſelfe, that I haue not had more attention at my prayers, nor more care in keeping of my tongue and mine eies, and that I haue not more ſpeedely dipatch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out of my hart, vaine and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honeſt thoughtes. I accuſe my ſelfe, that I did not ſuch a work, with all that humility, and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, which I might haue done. I accuſe my ſelfe, if I haue ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken any idle worde or backbited any. Theſe and other ſuch like wordes, doe not certainely ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie any fault or ſinne at al, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe a fault and ſinne is then committed, when a man doth not that to which hee is bound, and faileth in that, which hee ought to doe, and which is of
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:14230:31"/> neceſsity and precept: but as for all theſe former wordes, &amp; ſuch like, one may truly ſay the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who hath done all that which in rigor he was bounde vnto, albeit hee hath not done all that which he might haue done, nor yet al that which was better and of more perfection; becauſe God doth not binde a man in all caſes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der paine of mortall ſinne, no nor veniall neither, to do al that which he might doe, nor yet all that which he may, and is able to doe, neither all that which is the better, and of moſt perfection: and therefore if any ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe himſelfe, not vſing any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther maner of wordes then the former, he could not be abſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, becauſe hee confeſſed not plainely any ſinne at all.</p>
               <p>When one that goeth often
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:14230:32"/> to confeſsion, &amp; amongſt other ſins ſome he hath that be doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full: concerning which he is not certaine, whether hee gaue any conſent or no, or was careleſſe in making reſiſtance: in this caſe to confeſſe them with ſuch kind of words as before are ſet down, is not inconuenient, nor any cauſe why for ſo doing one ſhould be blamed, ſeing other ſinnes, whereof he is certaine he confeſſeth them plainly and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinctly. And if it fall ſo out, that ſince his laſt confeſsion, he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not call to minde any newe ſins, then may he confeſſe ſome of his life paſt, to the ende that he may haue abſolution, which without ſpecifying of ſome ſinne cannot be giuen.</p>
               <p>But concerning ſins that bee certaine, and which the penitent
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:14230:32"/> knoweth full well that hee hath committed, he muſt not vſe any ſuch manner of words, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe them in plaine and expreſſe tearmes, and ſuch as doe clearly ſet downe the ſinne, ſaying thus: I accuſe my ſelfe, that I haue bin negligent in keeping of my hart: that I haue not repelled vaine thoughtes, with ſuch care as I ought to haue done: that in the time of prayer, I haue not had that attention, and deuotion, which I was bound to haue had: that I haue not reſiſted the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of anger, of pride, of enuy, with ſuch patience, humility, &amp; charity, as I ought to haue done, that I haue beene colde in doing good workes, and ſome which I ought to haue done, I haue vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſloath omitted: &amp; in other ſome which I haue done, I haue not
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:14230:33"/> had that vertuous ende, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent which I ought to haue had, in ſeeking for the glory of God in them, but rather my ſelfe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing moued to do them for mine owne pleaſure and inclination, or ſeeking in them mine owne honour &amp; content: I haue with ſuperfluous appetite ſought for commodities and pleaſure of my body, in meate, drinke, apparel, reſt, and other recreations, not obſeruing in all theſe thinges, that moderation to which I was bounde: Of aduerſitie, puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or any diſgrace, I haue bin too much grieued and ſad, and not conformed my ſelfe ſo much to the will of God as I ought. Of ſuch thinges as haue fallen out according to mine owne will &amp; deſire, as for that they brought me honour, and procured com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:14230:33"/> or were thinges of delight and pleaſure, I haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyced in ſome of them vainely, &amp; not referred them as I ought, to the glory of God, &amp; the good of mine owne ſoule: My tongue I haue not kept ſo carefully as I ought, and without any neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie or profit of ſoules haue I ſpoken wordes in mine owne praiſe: curious queſtions haue I demanded, and idle words haue I vttered.</p>
               <p>Theſe and ſuch like, bee the ordinary veniall ſins, into which Gods ſeruantes that liue with care, and in the feare of God, do often times in a weeke, yea and in one day fall into (for thoſe which leade their life without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuch care, doe commit others more grieuous) and with ſuch wordes as theſe that ſignifie and
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:14230:34"/> import ſinne, ought they to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe them: and a true deſire to make their confeſsion as is requiſite, humility of heart, griefe and ſorrowe for ſinne, and that light which daily they gaine in the ſpirituall profit of their ſoule will clearely lay open be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their eies theſe and other ſuch like ſinnes of their heartes, and will teach them fit words to expreſſe them, and make them appeare with all their deformity as is conuenient: becauſe in ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentall confeſsion the peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent is witneſſe againſt himſelfe, and the witneſſe being lawfully demaunded, is bounde to tell all the trueth, and that in cleare and plaine wordes: He is likewiſe an aduocate for God againſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe: and the office of an aduo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat is, to alleadge all the reaſon
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:14230:34"/> and iuſtice that can be ſaide for his owne ſide, and plainely and truely to open al the iniuſtice &amp; litle reaſon that is on the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry part. And when a man doth ſo in confeſsion, then doth hee giue true euidence againſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, diſcouering and laying o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen all the grieuouſneſſe of his ſinnes: and he that doth behaue himſelfe like a wiſe aduocate in Gods cauſe againſt himſelfe, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadging all ſuch reaſons as hee hath to loue and obey God, and confeſſe with true ſorrowe of hart, al his great ingratitude, &amp; malice, with all ſuch conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and circumſtances as doe encreaſe them, which is but rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, then doth God of his infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite goodnes and pietie take vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him mans cauſe, maketh him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe his aduocate and patron,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:14230:35"/> and giueth ſentence in his fauor, pronouncing him abſolued and free from all his ſinnes, from e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting paine and confuſion, yea and ſomtimes from the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall paine alſo which for them he deſerued. And thus in this courte and iudgment, there paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth a wonderfull ſtrange ſecret, to wit, that if a ſinner hideth his ſinnes, and doth not declare &amp; open them as he ought, then do they remaine and be reſerued to be laide open and puniſhed at the day of iudgement, and him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to bee confounded before that terrible tribunall, and to be puniſhed for them in the ſight of heauen and earth: and if on the contrary a man doth nowe confeſſe and declare them with ſorrowe of hart, then doth God hide and couer them in ſuch ſort
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:14230:35"/> that they ſhall neuer bee ſeene more either of God or men for any puniſhment or confuſion to ſuch a penitent ſinner. For hee that confeſſeth his ſinnes in this manner, God doth ſo deale with him as though he had neuer ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and doth giue him ſo good a countenance, loue him ſo en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely, ſo bountifully and ſo libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, beſtow vpon him the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of his grace and glorie, as though hee had neuer offended him in his whole life. O with what great reaſon did Dauid ſay, <hi>Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 31.</note> 
                  <hi>are they, whoſe iniquities are pardo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned, and whoſe ſins are couered.</hi> They are tearmed couered, becauſe now they are not, &amp; albeit ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time they were, yet nowe ſhall they neuer more be ſeene to the hurt, or dammage of the peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent ſinner.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:14230:36"/>
               <head>Chap. IIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of the diſorder in confeſsing of veniall ſinnes, without hauing for them any griefe or purpoſe of amendment.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>SOme ſeruants of God there be, which doe often confeſſe themſelues, and vtterly forſake all mortall ſinne, and yet ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time commit this fault, that is, to confeſſe their venial ſinnes, and yet to leaue their paſsions quick, and liuely, bearing ſtill a loue &amp; affection vnto them: neither doe they ouercome them, or by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary actes mortifie them with true contrition of hart, and ſo they confeſſe, and accuſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues of ſuch veniall ſinnes, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vpon a cuſtome, without any penance at all, that is not hauing
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:14230:36"/> any true ſorrowe or griefe for them, or elſe without a firm pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe any more to commit them: In this manner do they confeſſe, idle wordes, voluntary diſtracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, curioſitie in looking, &amp; the reſt of the ſences, their exceſſe in eating, drinking, ſleeping, and laughing, their idlenes and loſſe of time, and ſuperfluous cheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing of themſelues, their merry lies, light detractions, and their negligence &amp; remiſneſſe in the time of prayer, and Maſſe. Of theſe and other ſuch like ſinnes doe they make their confeſsion, without euer feeling before ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d any griefe for them in their hart, and without hauing any deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination verily neuer to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit them againe. And this care<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leſneſſe is very hurtfull for two reaſons: the one is, becauſe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:14230:37"/> a man doe confeſſe theſe ſinnes, yet if he doe not truely reſolue neuer to do them againe, obtaineth not any forgiueneſſe for them at Gods handes, &amp; ſo they remaine ſtill a liue in the ſoule, and doe weaken and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it to fall into other ſinnes which be farre greater. An o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reaſon is, becauſe confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing his ſinnes in this manner, he addeth a newe fault to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer: becauſe ſuch a confeſsion as touching thoſe ſinnes, is fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and falſe: for though in wordes he doth accuſe himſelfe of them, yet doth he not deteſt and abhorre them, nor reſolue in his hart to auoide them. And therefore if he ſhould confeſſe al his veniall ſinnes in that maner, that is, without a true purpoſe to forſake any of them, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:14230:37"/> the confeſsion all togither coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit and of no valewe: and for this cauſe neceſſary it is, as holy men doe teach, that when Gods<note place="margin">D Grego<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> ſeruants do confeſſe venial ſins, they ſhoulde thinke well vpon<note place="margin">D Bernard ſerm. de ce. Domini. D Thom. 3. p. q. 87. ar 2. &amp; 3. &amp; in 4. diſt. 16. q. 2. ar. 2.</note> them, and before hand be ſory for them in their heart, as being offences againſt God, and veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly determine with a full purpoſe neuer to commit the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any more: and if many times they fall into them againe, many times like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe let them riſe againe, renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their former purpoſe: and if ſo often as they come to confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion they commit afterward the ſame ſinnes, ſo often likewiſe let them haue the ſame reſolution, &amp; not to be diſmaied or diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged: but let them humble the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues, and giue God thankes who alwaies is ready, when ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:14230:38"/> they turne vnto him, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; to pardon their of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences. Neither let them thinke, that ſuch confeſsions be altogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vnprofitable, becauſe they fal againe into their former ſins, but that they be very good &amp; of much profit, becauſe ſo often as they come vnto confeſsion with the ſame purpoſe of amendment of their life, Gods grace, (as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hath bin ſaid) &amp; the vertues &amp; giftes of the holy Ghoſt, be en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>creaſed in them, and they do ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine force &amp; ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth to preſerue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, &amp; not to fal into other ſins which be greater: &amp; a great part alſo of that harme is hindred which they had done, had they not before co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſed ſuch veniall ſins &amp; obtained pardon for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And if the ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of God whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he goeth to confeſsion, through his
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:14230:38"/> frailty feeleth not in himſelfe any determinat purpoſe, to fly al ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial ſins, which he confeſſeth: at leaſt let him haue a full reſolutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to auoid ſome of the greateſt &amp; which do moſt harme to his ſoul: &amp; if his frailty be ſo great, that of ſuch venial ſins as he hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted ſince his laſt confeſsio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cauſe they be ordinary, hee fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth difficulty &amp; paine to auoid the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, let him at leaſt accuſe hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelfe of ſome ſin, which in former time he hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſed, and that which doth moſt grieue him and which he hath a true purpoſe by Gods grace verily to auoide: becauſe if he do ſo, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhall his confeſsio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be lawfull, &amp; accompanied with the fruit of Gods grace: for the obtayning wherof, requiſit is is, that our confeſsio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould be, of ſuch ſins as a man doth abhorre.
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:14230:39"/> The reaſon why one ſhould with<note place="margin">D Thom. 3. p. q. 87. ar 1. &amp; in 4. diſtinct. 16. q. 2. ar. 1. &amp; q. 2. ar. 2.</note> ſuch a diſpoſition confeſſe veni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ſinnes is, becauſe when a man committeth any veniall ſin, the ſoule is diſordinately turned to the loue of the creature, louing more his owne delight, then to pleaſe and content God, &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring more to ſatiſfie his owne will, then the will of God: and therefore for the taking away of the ſame diſorder from the ſoul, &amp; that it may returne againe to his former rightneſſe, neceſſary it is, that a man ſhould do ſome inward act contrary to that for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ſinne, which before he did, as for example, to haue true griefe and ſorrowe for ſinne, or a reſolute purpoſe to commit it no more, or elſe, ſome other ſuch act equiualent to theſe: as ſome act of the loue of God, or deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:14230:39"/> or reſignation, ſo contrary to venial ſinnes committed, that if hee did then remember them, he would abhor &amp; auoid them quicklie: and when he confeſſeth all his veniall ſinnes with ſuch a due diſpoſition, certaine it is, that he obtayneth pardon &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion of them all.</p>
               <p>A great benefit of God cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine it is, that he hath of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite goodneſſe beſtowed vpon man ſo effectuall and ſweet a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy. And for aſmuch as moſt true it is, that the ſoule cannot enter into heauen with one only veniall ſinne, but that of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie it muſt before hand be puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied and purged from all, either in this life, or elſe in the next: great reaſon there is, that wee ſhould make our commodity of this diuine remedie, and that
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:14230:40"/> when we meane to confeſſe ſuch veniall ſinnes as we haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in thoſe eight or fifteene daies, ſince we were laſt at that ſacrament, we ſhould firſt ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly thinke of them in our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and conſider how they be offenſiue to God, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to his diuine will, doe very much hurt our ſoules, and hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der vs from receauing of moſte heauenly giftes at the handes of his diuine maieſtie, and that wee were bounde rather to haue ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered any temporal puniſhment, or loſſe, then euer to haue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to commit them: and let vs be grieued and aſhamed that euer we did them, &amp; determine in our heartes, neuer to commit them againe: and hauing thus diſpoſed &amp; prepared our ſelues, let vs confeſſe them, and albeit
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:14230:40"/> in confeſsion we tell not all, but the greateſt, and thoſe which cauſe moſt ſhame, yet let the griefe and ſorrowe for hauing committed them, and the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of not committing them againe comprehend and include all. And by theſe meanes ſhall we deliuer our ſelues from the terrible fire of Purgatory, and ſhall obtaine more plentye of Gods grace, and greater puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of conſcience, and when wee leaue this mortall life, wee ſhall the ſooner paſſe to the ioyes of heauen: for as <hi>Saint Iohn</hi> ſaith, <hi>Nothing that is defiled ſhall enter into</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Apoc. 21</note> 
                  <hi>that holy city.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:14230:41"/>
               <head>Chap. V.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of a certaine careleſneſſe, which vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally is founde amongeſt ſuch as bee deſirous to ſerue God, concerning the examination of their conſcience, before Confeſsion: and the greate harmes which doe followe thereof.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>ALthough commonly ſuch as feare God, and often go to confeſsion, do in ſuch ſort ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine their conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, that their confeſsion is ſound, and good, and bound they be not, to make their confeſsion againe: yet in ſome ſuch, not ſeldome, a great carleſneſſe is found, which doth much hinder the notable fruite of confeſsion. This negligence is, concerning the examination of their conſcience before they
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:14230:41"/> goe to confeſsion, doing it very lightly, and ſuperficially, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out entering well into the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward parte of their ſoul, &amp; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any great care to ſearch out many ſecret ſinnes, which they haue committed: amongſt which although ſome be great, yea and ſome of them mortall, yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the malice of them is more hidden, or elſe haue ſome ſhew of vertue, they knowe them not, nor make them anye part of their confeſsion. Wherefore for the better vnderſtanding of this point, which is very important, we haue to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider, that as ſome ſinnes proceede of malice, which be thoſe that a man knoweth to be ſinnes, and doth them of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, not hauing any great paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to prouoke him thereunto: ſo there be other ſinnes, which
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:14230:42"/> come of infirmity, ſuch as thoſe be which a man knoweth to bee ſins, yet he doth them, becauſe ſome paſsion or great tentation prouoketh him thereunto: ſo likewiſe there bee other ſinnes, which proceede of ignorance, as thoſe be, which a man through his owne negligence knoweth not to be any ſinnes. True it is, when a man doth what lieth in him, to vnderſtande the trueth of that which hee is bounde to knowe, and yet cannot come to the knowledge thereof, becauſe he cannot finde any that is able to teach him, then is he very wel excuſed from all danger of ſin: but when a man doth not what for his part he ought to doe, to know the truth, as becauſe hee doth not inquire of ſuch as hee ſhould, nor aske cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel of whom
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:14230:42"/> hee ought, neither vſeth other ſuch meanes as bee neceſſarye, that God may giue him light, and that good and learned men may enforme him vvhat hee is bounde to doe, ſuch a man as this, doing that thing which he knoweth not to bee a ſinne, is not through his ignorance ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed: and therefore if that which he doth bee againſt anie precept that bindeth to mortall ſinne, then ſhall that ſin of his bee mortall: and if it be againſt a precept which bindeth onely to a veniall ſinne, then ſhal the ſinne likewiſe bee but veniall, although not ſo grievous as if it were donne of malice, or were knowne before hand. The trueth of this doctrine is ſet dovvne by the church, in a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine decree which is taken out
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:14230:43"/> of <hi>S. Auguſtin</hi> theſe be his words. <hi>Not all they which be ignorant of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill</hi>
                  <note place="margin">De queſt. noui &amp; vet. Teſta. lib. 2 Cap. Non omnis diſt. 37.</note> 
                  <hi>they doe, be free from ſinne, and paine due to the ſame, but ſuch as haue none to inſtruct and tell them, may well he excuſed: but thoſe that may bee taught the trueth, and yet will not take any paines to learne it, are not excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: neither be they free from ſinne, nor the pu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>niſhment which for that they deſerue.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Out of this ground, to wit that ſome ignorance is culpable, as that which proceedeth of care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſneſſe and negligence, which excuſeth not from ſinne, it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth, that there be many chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, which fall into diuers great ſinnes, which through their own negligence, they neither knowe, nor vnderſtand to bee any ſins, and therefore doe they not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe them: and ſome remaine ſo
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:14230:43"/> ſecure, that they thinke them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues moſt aſſuredly to walke in the path of vertue, and the very right way to heauen, when as in very trueth they wander from true vertue, and trauaile in the path of euerlaſting damnation: for which cauſe the wiſe man ſaith: <hi>There is a way which ſeemeth</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pro. 14. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>iuſt and ſtraight, and in the end it lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to death.</hi> As though he ſaide: There be certaine kindes of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing amongſt men which ſeeme iuſt, and there be actions and cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes, affaires and dealinges, which ſeeme good, &amp; yet be not ſo in the ſight of God, but haue ſins in them, which carry men to eternal damnation: what kind of ſins theſe be, and how this e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill is to be holpen, ſhal ſtraight waies be declared.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:14230:44"/>
               <head>Chap. VI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of ſome ſinnes of ignorance, which a man knoweth not, nor confeſſeth: to witte, to be careleſſe, to knowe whereunto in particular hee is bounde: and to omit the workes of iuſtice and charity.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>TO the end that this ſo great an euill may the better bee knowne, and a remedy thereof founde out, it ſhall be very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable to ſet down in this place, ſome of theſe ſecret ſins, which in many caſes by reaſon of the weight of the matter, be mortal, and bee commonlye committed through ignorance: and I will ſpeake onely of thoſe which bee moſt vſuall, for by them the reſt may bee eaſilie gathered and
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:14230:44"/> founde out. Of theſe ſinnes, ſome bee more ſenſible and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall and more eaſilie to bee knowne, if a man woulde bee diligent to note them: others be more ſubtile, internall, and harder to be founde out. Of the firſt kind, be theſe: Negligence for a man to knowe, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme ſuch particular bandes as his eſtate or office requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth. Diuers men haue di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers ſtates, and particular of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices. Some be Lordes ouer ſubiectes, others bee Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, others Iudges, others Bayliffes, others Counſellers, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Scriueners, others Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, ſome haue the ſtate of Prelates, others be Prieſtes, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers religious men, others ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried. Theſe ſtates and offices beſides ſuch bandes &amp; precepts
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:14230:45"/> as they haue common to all chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, other particular they haue alſo of great waight, comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded either by the lawe of God, or by the lawe and ordinance of man, and theſe are they bounde both to knowe, and alſo to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme, and yet many do notably faile herein, not hauing any care to enter into the conſideration of this point. To this kinde of careleſneſſe an other is reduced which many likwiſe do not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider: and it is for Parentes and Maiſters, not to inſtruct their children, and ſervants, in the catholicke faith, and other ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary thinges to ſaluation, not to be careful alſo that they heare Maſſe, keepe the faſting daies, and ſay theire prayers: not to keepe them from wicked plaies, and paſtimes, from gadding a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:14230:45"/> in the night time, from the wicked cuſtom of vaine ſwea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ring, from eating of white meate vpon daies prohibited, not to keepe them from occaſions of ſinning, not to beſtow their chil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dren in due time in ſome good and vertuous ſtate of life: or to beſtow them againſt their owne willes or mindes: not to pay in due time ſeruants and iourney men their wages: nor to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme ſuch promiſes as they made them. By theſe kindes of omiſsions, often times mortall ſinnes are committed, which be not marked or thought vpon. In the number of theſe ſinnes, is alſo the careles cuſtome of ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, By my life, by my health, ſo God ſaue me, or as God ſhall healpe me, with other ſuch like oathes, men ſwearing ſomtimes
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:14230:46"/> thus, &amp; threatning that they wil doe this or that, yet without any intent to performe them: and at ſome other times affirming dout<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full thinges for certaine, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine at other times, to ſweare without thinking whether it bee true or falſe, which ſin although it be periury and of his owne na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture mortal, yet many that make profeſsion of vertue do litle co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider it. To ſweare alſo to doe ſome thing which may notablie redounde to the profit of their neighbour: or to ſweare to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecute ſuch an office faithfully, or to obſerue the rules thereof: likewiſe to ſweare not to receiue anye giftes in ſuch an office, nor anie ſtipende more then is taxed and ſet downe, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwarde to doe contrarye to theire oathes, and yet doing
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:14230:46"/> ſo, many doe not thinke that they haue committed any mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall ſinne in for ſwearing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues: and therefore doe not accuſe themſelues of any ſuch ſinne in confeſsion.</p>
               <p>One of theſe ſinnes like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe which haue their malice hidden, is, to flatter Princes, Prelates, and great men, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending or allowing of ſuch thinges as they haue done wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedlie, and to excuſe their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentions which ſerue to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine pride and gluttonie. To fauour alſo their friendes, and to ſpeake and labour for them that they may obtaine ſuch offices or dignities whether ſecular or ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall, whereof they be not worthy, becauſe they haue not thoſe partes which the lawe of God and man doe require: and
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:14230:47"/> to take mony or other thinges equiualent for offices, which ſhould be giuen freely: or to do other thinges of fauour, which of iuſtice and by reaſon of there office they are bounde to doe. To omitte the doing of workes of charity and mercy, whether ſpirituall or corporall, in ſuch caſes, as the lawe of God doth binde vs thereunto, &amp; to ſpend in playe, vaine apparell, iewelles banquets not neceſſary, and in other ſuperfluous thinges, that wealth which God gaue vs to beſtow in workes of charity. Not to hinder other mens ſinnes whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> conueniently wee may, by cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting them, or denouncing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to their ſuperiours or elſe by our doctrine, counſell or almes: eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially when they that omitte theſe thinges be great perſons,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:14230:47"/> as Lordes, Iuſtices of peace, Iudges, or Prelates, who not onely of charity, but alſo of iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, are bound to correct, pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh, and let what they may, the ſinnes of ſuch as liue vnder their iuriſdiction. Of theſe ſins like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe they be, which although ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry groſſe, yet to many their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice and greatneſſe is ſecret and hidden: as much iniuſtice which is committed in not paying our debtes in due time, and detay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning them vniuſtly againſt the will of thoſe that ſhoulde haue them, whether the debts be old or new. To make colluſions, and monopolies, that is for one man or place to ingroſſe thinges, that none may ſell or gaine but hee: likwiſe for many ſellers to agree togither to the iniurie of the bui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and many buyers, to the da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:14230:48"/> of the ſellers. To ſhewe parciality in diuiſion of common benefites, or taxing of tributes or ſubſidies, or in ſtopping and areſting of goodes, charging ſome, and exempting of others, and that for fauour and friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. To gaine by play, or to buy thinges of other mens children, or ſuch perſons as cannot ſell or do them away. Not to performe faithfully &amp; ſo ſoone as may be, the willes and teſtaments of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. Not to adminiſter honeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and according to conſcience, the goods of Wardes and other childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> during their no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>age, they being their Gardians, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the charge of their educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. To maintaine vniuſt ſutes: and in doubtfull caſes, not to vſe firſt diligence to know whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be iuſt or no, by ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:14230:48"/> out that ſincerely &amp; with a deſire to bee aſſured there of, and that of ſuch as can en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme them truely, and all this, not to doe iniurye or hurte to any.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>Chap. VII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of diuers kindes of wicked ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, not knowne to many, and ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times not confeſſed through culpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ignorance.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>AMongſt other great ſinnes whoſe malice are not of ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny ſo well perceiued, diuers kindes of ſuperſtitions are num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred: as to be deſirous to know by ſuperſtitions meanes, things paſt: as thefts, robberies, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſecret ſinnes or thoughtes
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:14230:49"/> of the hearte: or to bee willing to knowe future thinges, and thoſe not naturall, but ſuch as depend vpon our owne free wil, or thinges caſuall, for the effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting<note place="margin">Deut. 18. Leuit. 29.</note> of which, the actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of mans will muſt concurre: as mariages, getting or looſing of goodes, whether ſuch a man will come, or ſuch a bleſsing or curſe ſhall light vpon ſuch a one or no: whe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther he that goeth on ſuch a ſide of the ſtreete, ſhall be ſlaine, or hurt with a ſtone: whether hee that goeth ouer ſuch a riuer, ſhal be drowned: and ſuch other like thinges, which God onely doth knowe: for a man to be deſirous to knowe ſuch thinges as theſe, either by the ſtarres of heauen, or by the lines or ſignes of a mans hand, or by dreames, lots, or the chattering or ſinging of
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:14230:49"/> birdes, or by the motions of a<note place="margin">Cap. Illud. cap. ſed eſt. cap. ſors 26. q. 2. c. Non obſeruetis 26. q. 7. Con. Trid. ſeſ. 22. D Aug. de doct. Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian. lib. 2. ca. 21. &amp; 22. &amp; de ciuit. lib. 5. vſque ad cap. 6. Ambroſ. in Hexam. li. 4 cap. 4. D Tho. 1. p. q. 115. art. 3. &amp; 22. q. 95. art. 5. &amp; 96.</note> mans body, or by other ſuch like meanes, cannot be excuſed from ſuperſtition. To be willing likwiſe for the recouery of ſome infirmity or to get a remedy for ſome malady, to ſay ſuch kinde of words, or to make ſuch ſignes, or to carry ſuch a wrighting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout them, and by ſuch other like thinges, which haue not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuch naturall force to worke any ſuch thing, nor be ordayned of God for the producing of any ſuch effectes. Likewiſe to vſe holy thinges, and to put all the vertue and efficacie of them in circumſtances, or in ceremonies which be indifferent or vaine: as to obtaine ſome temporall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity at Gods handes, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine that ſo many praiers &amp; wordes are to be ſaid and none
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:14230:50"/> other: &amp; that they muſt be ſaid iuſt ſo many times, and not one more or leſſe, &amp; vpon ſuch daies and no other, or with ſo many candles, and of ſuch a faſhion and colour, and other like thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges: which being ſuch as it li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ſkilleth whether they bee donne in that manner or no, yet therein doe they put the efficacie and effecte of theire prayer, and not in the deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and feruour of ſpirit, with which the prayers bee ſaid, nor in Gods prouidence who diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth of all humane thinges, as beſt ſerueth for his glorye, and the good of our ſoules. Into theſe and other ſuch like ſuperſtitions, many perſons doe fal through culpable ignorance, thinking that in them, there is no ſinne at all, or elſe but
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:14230:50"/> ſmall and veniall, whereas in very trueth the ſinne is verye great, and very much and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerely reprehended in the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and alſo by holy men and eccleſiaſticall Canons vtterlye condemned, as thoſe thinges, in which a ſecret couenant is made with the Diuell, and in which he intermedleth to beguile chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians.</p>
               <p>And not longe ſince <hi>Sixtus Quintus</hi> by his publique letters, hath condemned all ſuch vaine artes, and vpon greate paine forbidden them: Theſe be his wordes. <hi>Beſides that arte which</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In motu proprio.</note> 
                  <hi>entreateth of future effectes, procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of naturall cauſes, all other arts which profeſſe to tell future and caſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all thinges, be guilefull and vaine, and ſubiecte to the pernitiouſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceites of the Diuell, who by them
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:14230:51"/> doe greatly thruſt themſelues in. And therefore Aſtrologers, &amp; Mathemati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians, who profeſſe the vaine knowledge of the ſtarres, and the generation and birth of men, and doe preſume to knowe iudge, and affirme, of that eſtate and condition of life, which men ſhall haue, as what honoures ſhal befal them, what riches, what children, what health, what death, what iorneyes, what quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relles, what impriſonment, and other ſuch proſperous and aduerſe chaunces, doe offend God grieuouſlie, and are the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues deceaued, and ſo deceaue others. And in like manner all others which by other like artes, are deſirous to know thinges that ſhall happen, &amp; be ſecret, as by ſignes in the hand, in the water, in the aire, in the fire, or in beaſtes, or by lottes, or ſuch other tokens, be vaine men, curious, wicked, and without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion: and thoſe men &amp; women which ſeeke to know ſuch like thinges of them,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:14230:51"/> or beleeue them, do offend againſt their baptiſme, &amp; againſt the chriſtian faith.</hi> And he addeth beſides, <hi>that hee doth not onely forbid theſe artes, and commande that ſuch as vſe them ſhould be punniſhed, when they affirme or aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure men, that theſe or theſe things ſhall fal out, but alſo when they ſay the ſame, though certainely they doe not affirme it.</hi> All theſe bee the wordes of Pope <hi>Sixtus,</hi> in his ſaid conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: wherein alſo he comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth all Prelats, &amp; Inquiſitors, to proceede againſt ſuch perſons very ſeuerely, and forbiddeth al bookes that intreate of any ſuch artes: And whereas he ſaith that thoſe which enquire, and would knowe ſuch thinges, or doe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue them, that they do offend againſt their baptiſme, and the catholicke faith: his meaning is, that they offende againſt that
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:14230:52"/> which they profeſſed in theire baptiſme, and againſt that which the catholicke faith doth teach, which is to flie and deteſt al ſuch pactes and couenants, whether open or ſecret, as the Diuell by any meanes hath any thinge to doe in.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>Chap. VIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of ſinnes committed by playing &amp; ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, and beholding of vaine and hurtfull ſightes, into which many do fall through culpable ignorance.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>AMong the former ſinnes, may bee placed playing at Cardes, Tables, Dice, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther like games, which conſiſt in fortune: For whereas play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his owne nature, that is conſidered alone without anie other circumſtance, is not any
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:14230:52"/> ſinne, and accompanied with<note place="margin">D Thom. 22. q 168. ar. 2.</note> good and honeſt circumſtances, in ſome perſons is lawfull: as when one wearied about honeſt buſineſſe, doth now and then play a little at ſome lavvefull game, onely to refreſhe his ſpirittes, and to returne more liuely to his vertuous labours, no ill example or ſcandall fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing thereof, nor any other inconuenience or diſordinate end: hereof it commeth, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though playing and gaming in ſuch manner as they are vſed, be very great ſinnes yet ſeeme they to be little, ſo that ſuch as be reſolued not to commit any mortall ſin, doe play very freely, &amp; falling by meanes therof into many great ſins, &amp; ſome of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mortall, yet they knovve them not, nor take them for any ſuch.
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:14230:53"/> For firſt of all, time, which is the gifte of God and that very pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, graunted freely to man, to the ende he ſhould beſtowe him ſelf in vertuous works, by which he may gaine &amp; merit the ioyes of heauen, the ende for which he was created: that doth he ſpend and waſte againſt the wil of God in play and wicked gaming, and in them doth hee caſt awaye not a little idle time, but many houres, many nightes, &amp; daies. And that time which is ſpent in this vaine and godleſſe exerciſe, is alſo taken away, as by and by ſhall be handled from prayer, whereof hee hath great neede, thereby to preſerue himſelfe in the ſeruice of God: for hee that is giuen to playing, is neither at that time, nor yet before, or af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, in any good diſpoſition to
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:14230:53"/> pray, becauſe that hath robbed and poſſeſſeth his harte. This time likwiſe is taken from much other honeſt buſines to which he is bound of charity or elſe of iuſtice, aſwell for the profit of his owne ſoule, as to performe thoſe thinges which belonge to his charge, conformable to his eſtate or office: and therefore by playing hee doth iniurye to many.</p>
               <p>Seeing alſo God hath orday<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, that ſuch mony as is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for the maintena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of man, &amp; his familie, or for other good vſes, ſhould be gained with the labour of his handes, or by his learning, or elſe by lawfull bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaines and couenantes profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the common wealth, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that which God ſaid to the firſt man, <hi>In the ſweate of</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 3.</note>
                  <pb n="82" facs="tcp:14230:54"/> 
                  <hi>thy face, ſhalt thou eate thy bread.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 3.</note> Which in a certaine maner doth belong to all thoſe which main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine them ſelues by any honeſt<note place="margin">D Thom. 2:. q. 164. ar. 2. ad 3.</note> trauaile: hee that followeth ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, doth contrary to this or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of God, ſeing he would get mony by a vaine and wicked meanes, by a thinge of hazzard<note place="margin">D Thom. 22. q. 118. ar. 8. ad 4.</note> and chance, and as they ſay, not otherwiſe but becauſe it fell out that he had ſuch cardes, or ſuch a chaunce at the dice: For which cauſe the gaine of play is called of learned men a filthy gaine, becauſe it is gotten by a wicked meanes. And as for them which get that whereof they liue, by honeſt trauaile, the diuine ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſaith. <hi>Becauſe thou ſhalt eate</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 127.</note> 
                  <hi>of the labour of thy handes, bleſſed ſhalt thou bee, and well ſhall it goe with thee.</hi> So on the contrary,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:14230:54"/> of them which purchaſe theire wealth and gather mony togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by naughty and vvicked meanes it ſaith, <hi>The treaſures of</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prou. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>wickedneſſe ſhall not profit him that hath them.</hi> Thoſe goodes are called <hi>treaſures of wickednes,</hi> which are gotten vniuſtlye, or by meanes of anye other vice or ſinne, as is that which is got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by play, when a man doth vſe it to the ende to get mony. This mony is to him that hath it, not onely without profit, but alſo to his great loſſe: for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the harme which it doth to his ſoule, it will alſo conſume and vaniſh away as ſalt doth in water. And for the ſin of him that doth ſo get it, it will bee the cauſe that the reſt of his goodes will bee loſt or conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, &amp; that either in his owne,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:14230:55"/> or elſe in the hands of his heires: for this is that puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t which God doth oftentimes inflict vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thoſe that by ſuch vnlawfull meanes come vnto wealth: and no doubt can be made but that this kinde of play is vnlawful &amp; naught, as both heathen Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers,<note place="margin">Ariſt. 3. Eth. D Thom. 22. q. 32. ar. 7. ad 1.</note> and holy Doctors af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme, ſeeing God did neuer or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine playing for a meanes to gather wealth, but this was the inuention of the Diuell, and the deuiſe of the malice of man: and therfore very great reaſon there is, to feare that in ſuch perſons the ſaying wil be fulfilled which is vttered by the Prophet <hi>Miche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as. The treaſures of iniquity</hi> (quoth<note place="margin">Mich. 6.</note> he) <hi>are fire in the houſe of a wicked man:</hi> becauſe they will like vnto fire with ill ſucceſſe conſume both the man and his wealth.</p>
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:14230:55"/>
               <p>Beſide theſe former reaſons which doe ſufficiently ſhewe the malice of play, others alſo there be, more cleare and apparant to the eyes of all: becauſe certaine it is, that he which vſually is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to play, is often times either to himſelf, or to thoſe with who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e he plaieth the cauſe of theſe ſins: to wit, that ſome doe play away thoſe goodes and money, which they haue no authority to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of, becauſe either they bee their fathers, or their maiſters, or becauſe it is due to their cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditours, or becauſe is is neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for the maintenance of their houſe &amp; familie, or elſe becauſe they haue borrowed it by frau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulent meanes, and of them, to whome in very trueth they are neuer able to pay it againe.</p>
               <p>They be the cauſe likewiſe of
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:14230:56"/> much vaine and falſe ſwearing, of much brawling, quarrelling and contention, and that when themſelues or others be angred and fretted by play, that they doe then fall out and badly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat their wiues, their children, their ſeruants, yea and their own fathers: they alſo bee the cauſe of ſcandall and ill example to others: and finally they bee the cauſe that ſuch mony as ſhoulde be giuen to the poore for the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of Chriſt, is taken from them, loſt in play, and beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the ſeruice of the Diuel. And whereas it is a comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement of God, as holy Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors doe affirme: for a man to giue in almes, in common and great neceſsities, that which is ſuperfluous for the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of his owne eſtate, which
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:14230:56"/> is, ſo much as remaineth after hee hath performed all that which of chriſtian decency is requiſite for one of his calling:<note place="margin">D Ambros Luc. 12 &amp; habetur ca. ſicut hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d. 47.</note> and in the extreame neceſsitie of others to giue that alſo which is neceſſary for his eſtate, that is, ſo much as remaineth af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter hee hath prouided for his owne life, and the life of his friendes. In theſe caſes, in which the precepte of giuinge almes, doth binde vnder paine of mortall ſinne, accordinge<note place="margin">D Auguſt. ep. ad Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced. &amp; cap. quid dicam 14. q. 4. D Thom. 22. q. 32. ar. 5. &amp; q. 66. ar. 7.</note> to the doctrine of holye and learned men: theſe gameſters for all that doe it not, but take it from the poore, to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy it vpon play. And as ſuch perſons doe tranſgreſſe the law of God and nature, ſo in like manner doe they breake the canonicall and civile lovve,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:14230:57"/> which vnder great penalties for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid playing at Cardes and Dice and ſuch other games, as a thing pernitious to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon wealth. For theſe reaſons and cauſes ſo ſure and certaine who ſeeth not, that the vſe of play, which to ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny ſeemeth but a ſmall euill, is in very deede a great one, and the roote and fountaine of paſsing great ſinnes.</p>
               <p>One of theſe ſinnes alſo it is to ſee comedies and playes, in which is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>courſe both of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; women, and where many wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton thinges are brought vpon the ſtage. To haunt likwiſe the daunſing ſchooles, and to goe a masking and daunſing: which thinges becauſe of their owne nature they be not mortall ſins, many make ſmall account of, &amp; doe not flie them, no not ſuch as
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:14230:57"/> haue a care to follow vertue: and yet certaine it is, that in them be found the true occaſions of mor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tall ſinnes, which often times do cauſe the weake to fall, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore neceſſary it is, that ſuch as deſire to ſaue their ſouls, ſhould craue of God, that he would o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen their eyes, that they may ſee the deadly poyso<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which lurketh vnder the braue gold of worldly delightes, and the diuers ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrackes which many ſoules doe ſuffer in this ſea, which ſeemeth ſo calme to the eies of the world: And if they perſeuere with hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, crauing this diuine light, God will giue it them, and they ſhall become maiſters of this trueth: and in the meane time, let them be content to learne, &amp; giue credit to others, that haue had experience therein, and let
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:14230:58"/> them carefully flie ſuch occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and dangers, and morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie them ſelues in this point, as elſe where hath beene admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed: &amp; let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> craue pardon of<note place="margin">Tract. 6. par. 2. c 15.</note> God, for that they haue herein throughe ignorance offended, ſaying with <hi>Dauid: Remember not O</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>Lorde, the ſinnes of my youth, nor my culpable ignorance,</hi> giuing mee full pardon for them all.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>Chap. IX.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of other ſinnes more ſecret, as pride of our owne proper iudgement and ſelfe will, which many doe not knowe nor confeſſe through culpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ignorance.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>THeſe examples before no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, which are committed through culpable ignorance, be
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:14230:58"/> of the moſt ſenſible, externall, and eaſie to be knowne: Other ſinnes there bee, more ſubtile, inwarde, and ſecret, into which many that deſire to ſerue God doe fall, and through their neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence doe not knowe them: &amp; although alwaies they be not mortal ſins, yet often times they bee, and euer dangerous, and for ſuch ought to bee auoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. Of theſe, one is a ſpirituall pride, by reaſon whereof a man inwardelye in his hearte doth eſteeme of himſelfe very diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinatlie: a preſumption of his owne iudgement, and proper vnderſtanding, by meanes wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of, what hee doth iudge and thinke to be ſo, that doth he like, and followe, and that more ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinatlie then is either lavvefull or conuenient: A pride of his
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:14230:59"/> owne will, wherewith he loueth his will very diſordinately, is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amoured thereof, and deſirous that it ſhould be effected in all thinges: A preſumptuous and diſordinat confide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of his own forces and ability: A raſh curio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity concerning the workes and iudgements of God: A diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate deſire to be preferred be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore others: A wicked ſadneſſe of an other mans good: A ſecret ambition, of honour and digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: An indiſcretion in penance, faſting, watching, &amp; other mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifications, which he doth, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing his owne iudgment, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the minde of his ghoſtly father: A wicked deſire of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularity, whereby he greatly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſireth in outward apparance, to haue rare and ſingular thinges, that men may caſt their eyes
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:14230:59"/> more vpon him, then vpon o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and haue in him what to admire and commend. Theſe be the moſt ſecret &amp; ſpiritual ſins, by reaſon of which it falleth out ſometime, that a man is full and wholly poſſeſſed of them &amp; yet doth neither knowe them, nor confeſſeth them: for as theeues that break into a houſe, to rob &amp; ſpoile it, do firſt of al put out the light, becauſe they woulde not bee ſeene: euen ſo theſe ſins en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring into the ſoul, &amp; poſſeſsing a great part thereof, do quench out the light of grace and ſound reaſon, and make it ſo blinde, that it can neither ſee nor know them. This is the opinion of all holy men, which venerable <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard</hi> doth excellently well note in theſe words <hi>Who is able to know</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Richard de S. victore</note> 
                  <hi>the pride of his owne heart, which hath
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:14230:60"/> ſo longe continued and encreaſed there, if God doth not open it: who can vnderſtande the ſecret rootes, and craftie cogitations thereof, by which often times priuiely and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out beeing perceaued, it entreth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the hearte, and robbeth that ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue which there it findeth?</hi> And giuinge a reaſon why other kinde of ſins the greater they bee the more eaſilie they bee known, and pride the greater it is, the more ſecret it is, and hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth it ſelfe, thus hee writeth. <hi>Whileſt this vice of pride doth more encreaſe and enlarge it ſelfe in the ſoule, and more poſſeſſe and rule it, ſo much the more doth it make it blinde, and for that cauſe ſo much the leſſe doth it perceiue it, but although the ſoule which harboureth ſecreat pride doth not knowe it, yet God doth, who is
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:14230:60"/> vigilant enough, and doth pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhe it, spoyling the ſoule of all his giftes, and leauing it desti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of his diuine grace.</hi> All this is out of venerable <hi>Richard:</hi> in which wordes hee doth with all other holy men affirme that there bee ſecret ſinnes in the ſoule which a man him ſelfe doth not knowe, and that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge all other that vvhich doth moſte lurke and hide it ſelfe is pride.</p>
               <p>And it is not a thinge much to be maruailed at, that God doth vſe this ſo feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full a iudgemente vvith ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, as to ſuffer them to fall into thoſe ſinnes, which them ſelues knovve not, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God dealeth thus with ſuch perſons, as firſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted thoſe ſinnes which they
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:14230:61"/> knowe well enough what they were, and yet did not true pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance for them: &amp; for punniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſo bolde and ſhameleſſe a behauiour, as wittingly &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litiouſlie to haue committed ſo grieuous ſinnes, God doth per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitte that the darte of his anger come vpon them, which is the greateſt punniſhment that he v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth in this life, ſo that volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily they fall into ſuch ſinnes as through their owne negligence, they knowe not to be ſinnes, and being fallen into them, ſo to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue without doing for them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny penance, and ſometime to die in the ſame. So ſaith <hi>Saint Gregory. It is a punniſhment for ſin committed,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In Moral. lib. 14. c. 15</note> 
                  <hi>for a man to ſee, and knowe that good thing which he ought to doe, and yet through his weakeneſſe, not to put it in execution: and a greater punniſhment
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:14230:61"/> it is, and inflicted for ſome greater ſin, for a man not to ſee, nor knowe that which he is bounde to doe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Of theſe ſecret ſinnes, which are committed through igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and yet for all that bee imputed by God, and ſeuerelie by him punniſhed, we haue ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny examples in holy ſcripture. I will here onely make mention of two, but thoſe of the moſt nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, to giue more light to that which hath beene ſaide. God commaunded King <hi>Saul</hi> to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uade the countrey of the <hi>Amala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chites,</hi> and vtterly to deſtroye<note place="margin">1 Reg. 15.</note> them, not leauing either man or beaſt aliue, becauſe they did not ſhewe mercy, but crueltie to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> when they came out of Aegipt: <hi>Saul</hi> went, and conquered the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>try, ſlew men, and beaſtes as he was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded:
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:14230:62"/> but yet he did ſpare the life of the king, called <hi>Agag,</hi> and ſome of the beſt cattell: and in this facte, hee neuer thought that hee had committed any ſin at all: for to ſaue the kinges life, he did it vnder the title of piety: and ſome of the beaſtes hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued, for outwarde ſhewe of religion, to offer them in ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to God: and therfore when the Prophet <hi>Samuell</hi> did repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hende him, for not hauing kept the commaundement of God, he anſwered confidentlie, that he had done all that, which God had willed and appointed him. Albeit Saul ſinned, becauſe hee ſhould not haue interpreted the commandement of God, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his owne fancy, nor to haue donne, expreſlie contrary to that which God gaue him in
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:14230:62"/> charge, either vpon any pretext of piety, or colour of religion: yet he thought that he had not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted any ſinne therein, nay ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hee ſuppoſed, that he had donne verye well: and ſo that which hee reputed for no faulte, God very iuſtlie did impute vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him for a grieuous ſinne, and did punniſh him moſt ſeverelie for the ſame, depriuing him of his kingdome, and caſting him out of his favour, and ſuffering him by a naughtie death to<note place="margin">2 Reg. 24.</note> ende his daies. <hi>Dauid</hi> had a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to number his people and to muſter all the men of war in his kingdome, &amp; he put this his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire in executio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. This was in him a great ſinne both becauſe it was very chargeable to the king, very troubleſome to the people, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any neceſsity or iuſt cauſe:
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:14230:63"/> and alſo becauſe it was a kinde of pride, and vaine oſtentation, as <hi>Saint Gregory</hi> ſaith: and to this may be alſo added, howe it was againſt the law, which comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that when vpon neceſsitie the people were numbred, that euery one ſhoulde offer a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine quantity in almes, to bee imployed about the vſes of the tabernacle. This being ſo grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous<note place="margin">Exod. 30.</note> a ſinne, and for ſo many reaſons contrary to the lawe of God, yet when <hi>Dauid</hi> did it, he thought it not any ſuch, vntill afterwarde he ſawe the punniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereof, to conſume his people, by ſo pitifull a peſtile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, that there were alreadye dead thereof ſeauenty thouſand per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons: Then he perceaued what a great ſinne he had committed, and did confeſſe it ſaying, <hi>I haue
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:14230:63"/> ſinned much in this fact, and haue done</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Charthuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anus. 2 Reg. 24.</note> 
                  <hi>fooliſhlie:</hi> And <hi>Dauid</hi> fell into this ſinne, becauſe beholding him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſo potent in battaile, and to ouercome al his enemies, he ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered ſome preſumption to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into his hart: and for this ſin, and for the ſinnes of the people, God did ſuffer him, to fall into ſuch an ignorance, and blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that hee knewe not howe greate a ſinne that was which he then committed. So that both <hi>Saul,</hi> and <hi>Dauid,</hi> offended God, in doing theſe ſinnes, not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing howe greate the faulte was which then they did: and in like manner, many fall into verie grieuous ſinnes, through culpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ignorance, as hath bin ſaide, and ſome of them as <hi>Saul,</hi> neuer come to know or confeſſe them, and ſo die in their ſinnes, and
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:14230:64"/> periſhe for euer. Others, as <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> come to the knowledge ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and doe purge them by true penance and contrition. To the end therefore that wee may pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue ourſelues from falling in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſo great blindneſſe as this is, and if we be already fallen, that wee may come out of it, let vs nowe ſee, what remedies are for this purpoſe to be vſed, and put in practiſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>Chap. X.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of a very profitable remedye, againſt the harme which commeth by ſecret ſinnes, and that is, euery day to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine our conſcience: and the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner how this is to he done.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>HAuing now declared, how great an hindera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce it is, to a good confeſsio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, lightly to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine our conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, &amp; the great
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:14230:64"/> harmes which from that negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence doe growe, and that is for a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to fall into thoſe ſins which he knoweth not: requiſite it is likewiſe, to giue ſome inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, how we may ouercome this careleſnes, &amp; deliuer our ſelues from theſe ſo great harmes.</p>
               <p>The firſt is, for a man willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to take paines to enter vvith conſideration into himſelfe, and to ſearch all the corners of his conſcience, and crauing light at Gods handes, that he may know himſelfe, to ſtay there for ſome ſpace, pondering the motions, &amp; deſires of his owne ſoule, and the workes which from that doe ſpring: For to applie carefully, and with diligence, the hearte troubled with ſuch varietye of tentations, to conſider with qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et, the inward actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of the ſoule,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:14230:65"/> and the outwarde of the body, is a thing of trauaile &amp; paine, and therefore neceſſary it is, that a man ſhould reſolue him ſelfe to imbrace this labour, and to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercome this difficultie: And to the end that a man may by vſe make this examination well, and get a facility therein, let him not thinke it enough to examine his conſcience once before he goeth to confeſsion, but let him make it daiely: And for that purpoſe at night when he goeth to bed, let him retire himſelfe, into ſome ſecret place, before ſome image: and there let him call his ſoule to account, how it hath beſtowed that day, and let him examine well all that hee hath thought, ſaid, or done: and ſuch ſins as he findeth himſelf to haue fallen into, let him purge with
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:14230:65"/> the teares of pennance, for ſo did holy <hi>Iob,</hi> and this was his mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning when he ſaide: <hi>I conſidered O Lord, with feare all my workes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cap. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>I knowe, that thou wilt not leaue any ſin vnpunniſhed,</hi> as though hee had ſaid: To preuent thy iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and punniſhment, I haue iudged and punniſhed my ſelfe: and that euery day, and euery hower: becauſe the holye man coulde not make this examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all his workes, had hee not vſed it very often. And king <hi>Dauid</hi> ſo employed about the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires of his kingdome, and ſo charged with buſineſſe of great weight, was not for all that care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe herein, but did euery night recollect himſelfe, to make this examination of his conſcience, and to bewaile all the wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe which he had committed
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:14230:66"/> againſt the will of God. This doth he plainly declare, when he ſaith thus: <hi>I haue labored in ſorowe and ſighing for my ſins, and euery night haue I exerciſed my felfe, vntill I haue waſhed my bed, with the abundance of teares, which mine eyes did powre foorth.</hi> And in an other Pſalme<note place="margin">Pſal. 76.</note> hee ſaith: <hi>In the night time haue I exerciſed my ſelfe, meditating with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in my ſoule the mercies receiued of God, and the ſinnes which I haue commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted againſt him, and reprehending &amp; accuſing my ſelfe, I haue with ſorrowe waſhed my ſoule.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This examination is to bee made by deuiding it into fiue members or points. In the firſt, let him giue thankes vnto God, for benefites receaued, as for hauing created him of nothing according to his owne image, and for his glorie, for hauinge
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:14230:66"/> preſerued him, redeemed him, and made him a chriſtian, and for hauing ſuffered and expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted him to doe pennaunce: and in particular, for that hee hath that daye giuen him life, ſtrength, ſuccour, and holye inſpirations to liue vvell, and deliuered him from many ſins and dangers, into which tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough his owne weakneſſe, and ſubtiltie of his enemies, hee might haue fallen.</p>
               <p>In the ſeconde pointe, let him craue grace and lighte of God, to knovve throughly all his ſinnes, which he hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted that daye, and alſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny others, donne in any time of his life paſt, which by for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getfulneſſe or ignorance, hee hath not yet confeſſed, nor amended. Let him acknowledge
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:14230:67"/> that of himfelfe he is moſt igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, and blinde to knowe any good thinge, and that through the infinite mercy of God, and the merits of Chriſt our Lorde he muſt receiue this gift to know himſelfe, and therefore let him craue it with humility, to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand his ſinnes, and to bewaile them as he ought.</p>
               <p>In the third point, let him run ouer all the workes, wordes, and thoughtes of that day, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider well, whether he hath done any wicked worke or omitted to doe any good, vnto which hee was bounde: And ſuch good workes as hee hath done, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he did not corrupt them &amp; make them naught in the doing, as if he did correct or punniſh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny vpon reuenge, if he reiected any poore body, not giuing him
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:14230:67"/> almes as was conuenient: if he ſaid not his prayers without at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention. In his wordes, let him conſider, whether he hath ſworn without neceſsity, back-bited a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, tolde any lies, or vttered a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny idle or impatient wordes. In his thoughtes, let him examine whether he hath had any pride, anger, couetuouſneſſe, griefe, at the good of his neighbour, vaine deſires of worldly praiſe: and in theſe and other ſuch like wicked thoughtes, let him examine him ſelfe, whether he hath caſt them quickly from him, crauing Gods grace to withſtand them, and hath deteſted them as contrary to the will of God.</p>
               <p>In the fourth point. For ſuch ſinnes as he findeth that he hath committed that daye, bee they great or ſmall, let him repent &amp;
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:14230:68"/> be ſorie from his hart, and pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der with himſelfe, how ſinne is an offence done againſt the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie of God, and therefore let him ſay in his ſoule, with a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation thereof. O that I had neuer committed thee for any thinge in the worlde. And let him conſider, that although hee hath many times fallen into the ſame faulte, that hee ought not for all that to bee diſmaied, nor diſordinatelie grieued, but let him humble himſelfe, and with a louing hart, and confidence in the goodneſſe of God, who ſo often as a ſinner doth turne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, is ready to receaue him againe, craue pardon at his ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, and let him offer vnto his diuine maieſty, the merits of his holye paſsion, that through them hee would voutſafe to grant him re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion:
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:14230:68"/> And if the ſinnes, into which he hath fallen that day be of the greateſt ſorte, let him for them conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne him ſelfe to ſome pena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, as to faſt, or to take away ſome part of his meate or drink, or to giue ſome almes, or to ſay three <hi>Creedes,</hi> or three <hi>Salue regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas,</hi> with his armes ſtretched out like a croſſe, in reuerence &amp; ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of the bleſſed Trinity, or the three howers which our Lord &amp; fauiour remained vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the croſſe, or fiue times to kiſſe the earthe, in honor of the fiue woundes of our Sauiour.</p>
               <p>In the fifte and laſt pointe, let him purpoſe in his hearte, the amendmente of thoſe ſins, that is, not to committe them euer anye more for all the worlde, and although he hath fallen a thouſande tymes into
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:14230:69"/> them, yet let him a thouſande times fully purpoſe to doe ſo no more, and when he determineth not to commit them againe, let him by no meanes truſt vpon himſelfe, or relie vpon his owne ſtrength, for the performance of that his intent, but let him truſt vpon the grace of god, which he will beſtowe vpon him for that purpoſe, through the merittes of his ſacred paſsion, as elſe where hath beene declared: And let<note place="margin">Tract. 2. cap. 2.</note> him conclude with one PATER NOSTER to God, praying ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in for pardon for that is paſt, and grace to amend himſelfe, and an AVE MARIA to our bleſſed Lady, that ſhe woulde vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe for this ende, to aſsiſt him with hir prayers and interceſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
               <p>This is the daily examination
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:14230:69"/> of our conſcience: and it impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth ſo much for a man to be dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent herein, and neuer vpon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny occaſion, or buſineſſe to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit it, albeit he ſpend no more therein, then the fourth parte of an hower, that no wordes can ſufficiently commend the ſame. By the helpe of this examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, a man doth ouercome culpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ignorance, and is deliuered from thoſe ſecret ſinnes, which from that doe growe, becauſe he doth what lieth in him, to know the trueth and for the goodneſſe of God to reueale it. By meanes alſo of this examination, a man is deliuered from that weakenes that blindneſſe, that deformity, which the ſinnes committed that day, left in his ſoule, and obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth of God more ſtrengthe, more light, and purity of ſoule,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:14230:70"/> and doth euery day proceede &amp; goe forwarde in the ſeruice of God. By this examination doth he likewiſe fulfill thoſe precepts and admonitions of Chriſt, ſo often and ſo earneſtlie repeated in the Goſpell. <hi>Watche and pray,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 24. &amp; 15. Luc. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>becauſe you knowe not the day nor the hower of your death and iudgement: Be ready, becauſe at that hower which you thinke not of, the ſonne of the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin will come, to call you to his diuiue iudgement.</hi> By this examination alſo, doth a man watch ouer him ſelfe, eſcapeth the daunger and bande of his former ſinnes, deliuereth himſelfe from thoſe to come, and maketh his ſoule ready for death, yea if it ſhoulde come that very night, as it is poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible and indeede may come, &amp; ſo he might haue chanced vpon a ſodaine death, and therby (had
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:14230:70"/> hee not examined himſelfe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) haue periſhed and beene damned for euer: but now ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing before hand examined wel his conſcience, with contrition for his ſinnes, is a ſaued ſoule. To this daily examination holy fathers doe exhort vs, eſpecially <hi>Saint Baſill,</hi> who ſpeaketh thus: <hi>Examine at euening, or in the night</hi>
                  <note place="margin">De ren<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiatione ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culi.</note> 
                  <hi>thy whole daies worke: Enter into con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, and remember thy actions within thy ſoule, to amende them, and make them better, and compare them with thoſe of the former day, to ſee whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thou haſt amended thy ſelfe, and endeuour carefully euery day, to leade a more vertuous life, for by theſe meanes ſhalt thou bee more like and more neere to the bleſſed Angelles<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and more acceptable in the ſight of God.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <pb n="116" facs="tcp:14230:71"/>
               <head>Chap. XI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of an other ſingular meanes, for a man to deliuer himſelfe from ſecret ſins, and that his confeſsions may be more fruitfull, which is, to haue one de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminat ghoſtly father, vnto whom he ought ordinarily to confeſſe his ſinnes.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>AN other meanes which a man hath to vſe for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy of theſe miſchiefes is, to haue one confeſſor, and ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all father, who is a prudent man, and of a good conſcience, vpon whome ordinarily let him relie, and to him often confeſſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, &amp; in ſuch doubts as occur demande his aduice and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell: Let him not without great cauſe change his ghoſtly father,
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:14230:71"/> but keepe one ſure and certaine, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e he hath made choiſe of: &amp; to him let him open his ſoule, &amp; giue an account of his whole life, and not onely of thoſe thinges which be certainely ſinnes, but likwiſe of thoſe wherein he ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in doubt: neither let him onely diſcouer his ſinnes, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo his good workes and pennan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and mortifications which he doth, that hee may inſtructe and direct him to doe that which is moſt for the ſeruice of God. If our ghoſtly father had no other office but to abſolue vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our ſins, inconuenient it were not, to confeſſe one day to one man, and an other day to confeſſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an other, but ſo it is not, for beſides this, hee hath alſo the office of a father, and a mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, and of a phiſition, and by
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:14230:72"/> reaſon hereof, it appertaineth to<note place="margin">Cap. om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis vtriuſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſexus. Gulielmus Pariſſien. de peniten<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tia.</note> him, to teach his ghoſtly childe all ſuch thinges as be neceſſary for the good of his ſoule, and to knowe the rootes and occaſions of his ſinnes, his paſsions, and wicked inclinations, that he may the better cure them, by preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing meete remedies for thoſe diſeaſes: and to know his vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous actions &amp; good inclinations that he may informe him how to make the more profit of them, for his further encreaſe in ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue: and to vnderſtande vvhat penances he doth, to the ende he may teach him the rule of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion, which touching them he hath to obſerue. To him alſo it belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geth to appoint him meanes both to preſerue himſelfe, and to profit in the ſeruice of God and alſo how to continue thoſe good
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:14230:72"/> meanes. Wherefore to the ende that the ghoſtly father may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme al theſe principall parts of his duty, neceſſary it is, that hee haue a very good inſight in his ghoſtly child, and a long know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge &amp; experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the ſtate of his ſoule, that as reaſon ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire he may apply one day one remedy, &amp; an other day an other &amp; to continue it ſo long, as ſhall be conuenie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, &amp; to enquire whe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther he reape any profit by ſuch cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel &amp; meanes as he doth pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe: which thing ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, if the penite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t do not vſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ally repaire to one ordinary gho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtly father. When a ſcholer lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth an art of ſom wiſe &amp; expert maiſter, it importeth much, that hee haue but one man to teach him, for if hee goe one daye to one, and an other to an other,
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:14230:73"/> that which he learneth with one, he forgetteth with an other. And when any ſicke body is for ſome great infirmity vnder the hands of a learned phiſition, requiſite it is, that the ſame man doe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede forwarde in the cure of his diſeaſe: for if one looke to him one day, and an other, haue care of him an other, his recouery is much hindred, and it falleth out ſometimes, that what one doth, an other doth vndoe. In this manner, it fareth in the arte of good life, and in the phiſicke of the ſoule: for it importeth very much, that the ghoſtly father be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a wiſe and diſcreete man, ſhoulde ordinarily bee but one, who may continue on his good counſel, and the cure of his ſoul. This aduiſe giueth <hi>Saint Bonauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> in theſe wordes. <hi>Make choiſe
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:14230:73"/> of one ghoſtly father, who is of diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, learning, &amp; experience, to whom confeſſe thy ſelfe, and open all the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectes and tentations of thy ſoule, that be may preſcribe thee a remedye, and change him not either for ſhame, or for feare to be confounded, nay rather for thy greater confuſion, enforce thy ſelfe to confeſſe to that man, and open vnto him the ſtate of thy ſoule as plainely as thou canſt.</hi> This is the counſell of <hi>Saint Bonauenture:</hi> And that wee ought likewiſe to declare vnto ſuch an ordinary ghoſtly father, our deuotions, penances, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diuine inſpirations, &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts, <hi>S. Dorotheus</hi> and the holye<note place="margin">S. Dorothe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>us ſerm. 20. Caſſianus collat. 1. cap. 10.</note> Abbot <hi>Moiſes,</hi> and other holye men doe aduiſe vs, as a thinge moſt important, to haue our ſoul well directed, &amp; defended from the craft and ſubtiltie of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell. And as I ſay, that ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:14230:74"/> it is good to keepe one gho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtly father, ſo iuſt cauſes may fall out, for which it may be expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to confeſſe ſome time vnto an other, and to chang one man and take an other, to whome v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually he ſhould repaire for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion: And if it be not done v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon lightneſſe or a vaine deſire, but vpon neceſſitie, or for ſome iuſt reſpecte, it is not to be repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded, eſpecially if the cauſe be, for that our old ghoſtly father ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>not be had at all, or at that time: for then ſhall it not onely be wel done to confeſſe vnto an other, but it ſhould be a great fault not to doe it. For if becauſe our v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual ghoſtly father ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be had, one ſhould giue ouer his ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry confeſsio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, &amp; wax ſlack in his good cuſtome, to go ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it were certainly a very bad
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:14230:74"/> ſigne: for by that, did he make it manifeſt, that in his confeſſions, he ſought his own conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; not God: &amp; that he deſired his own temporall comfort, and not the true good of his owne ſoule: for had hee ſoughte the pleaſure of God, and the profit of his ſoule, when his olde confeſſor coulde not be had, he woulde quicklie haue made choiſe of an other, ſeing in that he did pleaſe God, and procure the good of his own ſoule.</p>
               <p>By this meanes of keeping one ordinary ghoſtly father, who is a wiſe man and one that feareth God, he that ſincerely deſireth, and laboureth to ſaue his ſoule, ſhall deliuer him ſelfe from all e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils and inconueniences of cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable ignorance, and from er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in ſuch thinges as pertaine
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:14230:75"/> to his ſaluation. For ſeeing his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſor, is in the place of Chriſt our Lord, and the penitent ſoule commeth vnto him, as thoughe it were to the feete of Chriſt him ſelfe, it pertaineth to the pietye of our mercifull maiſter, and to the fidelity of his promiſes, to teach &amp; illuminate ſuch a ſoule, in all thinges neceſſary for his ſaluation, ſeing he doth ſeeke it, by thoſe meanes which himſelfe hath ordayned in his church, and eſpecially by this of ſuch humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, &amp; ſo acceptable in his ſight: which thing for the great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and ſecurity of all, our Lord hath voutſafed to confirme with wonderfull examples. <hi>Moiſes</hi> was<note place="margin">Exod. 18.</note> in a great errour when he alone woulde heare all cauſes exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned before himſelfe, being more then he was able to doe, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:14230:75"/> whereof many cauſes were not diſpatched: God to deliuer him from this ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, brought a certaine Prieſt called <hi>Ietro</hi> from the place of his dwelling, into the deſert where <hi>Moiſes</hi> was, by whoſe meanes he learned a more ready way for the diſpatch of the peoples cauſes. <hi>Dauid</hi> likvviſe was much deceaued, when hee thought that God had voutſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed him of that fauour, as that he ſhould be the man, who ſhould build him a Temple, and that this was his diuine pleaſure: and God did deliuer him from this ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, by meanes of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Nathan:</hi> by which fact, God<note place="margin">2 Reg. 7.</note> ſhewed how much it doth pleaſe him, to teach his faithfull ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants ſuch thinges as bee neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarye, and profitable for theire ſoules, and to deliuer them from
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:14230:76"/> ignorance &amp; deceits, by meanes of his Prieſts and ſeruants, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially by the help of a mans ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary ghoſtly father, &amp; in the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of penance, ſeing though <hi>Moiſes</hi> were his familiar friend &amp; vvho as the ſcripture ſaith did talke with him face to face, that is to ſay, in ſome paſſing highe contemplation: and alſo <hi>Dauid</hi> thoughe his greate ſeruante, to whome hee reuealed ſuch deepe miſteries, yet it pleaſed him not to deliuer them from theſe ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norances, but by the meanes of others, to the ende that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thus inſtructed by the will of God, they ſhoulde alſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe humillitye, ſubmittinge them ſelues to men in other thinges, farre inferior to them ſelues.</p>
               <p>Yet neceſſary it is, that a man
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:14230:76"/> ſhould here note one thing, to the ende that God may by the meanes of his ghoſtlye father, teache him the trueth, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recte him in the way of vertue, and that is, that he come to confeſſion, with that ende and intention which he ought to do, to witte with a deſire to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the truth, and that which is moſt expedient for his ſoule, although it be a thing of travaile and that which will put him to much trouble and griefe, &amp; with al let him craue of God, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire and put into the hart of his ghoſtlye father, that which hee hath to ſpeake, becauſe if hee come to his confeſſor with a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire only that he ſhould tell him that which doth pleaſe himſelfe, and to declare the trueth if it bee fittinge to his owne humor,
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:14230:77"/> and if not, to ſay nothing, then for punniſhment of that wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed intention, God vſeth to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the ghoſtly father not cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainely to tell him the trueth, nor that which is neceſſary for him, but rather the contrary: for ſo hath God threatned by his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher <hi>Ezechiell</hi> in theſe wordes: <hi>If</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cap. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>a man who hath his hart from me, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth vnto a Prophet, and by meanes of him would be taught concerning mee, I will permit that the Prophet ſhall bee deceiued and deceaue him: according to the wicked intention of him that aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, ſhall bee the deceite of him that anſwereth.</hi> So did it happen to king <hi>Achah,</hi> and to many more,<note place="margin">3 Reg. 22.</note> as experience hath taught vs, who going to aſke counſell for matters of theire ſoule with a naughtie intention haue beene deceaued. Wherefore very ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarye
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:14230:77"/> it is, that the penitent which deſireth truly to bee illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minated, and directed of God, by meanes of his ghoſtlie father, that he ſhoulde come vnto him with a pure &amp; ſounde intention, that is to ſay, with an effectuall will, that he ſhould tell and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct him in that which is moſt acceptable to God, and moſt neceſſarie and profitable for his owne ſoule, although it be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to his owne liking, &amp; hard and difficult to performe. And comming in this manner, God will teach him by this meanes al trueth, and giue him ſtrength to doe it, and with the helpe of his grace make it eaſie, and ſweete to effect that which ſeemeth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him very ſharpe and difficult. So certaine be holy men of this moſt merciful property of God,
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:14230:78"/> towardes ſuch as come with a good intention, that venerable <hi>Richard</hi> with greate confidence thereof, writeth theſe wordes. <hi>Curious perſons are ſomtimes deceaued</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Richard de Sancto vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctore in cant. c. 39.</note> 
                  <hi>of the Diuel, but the vertuous that with a good intention craue counſell, and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely open vnto their ghoſtly fathers, not onely theire ſinnes, but alſo the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of their ſoules, theſe walke the right way free from deceite, becauſe he cannot erre, that with a ſound intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on asketh counſell, and is gouerned by him, neither can he be beguiled by the enemy that doth diſcouer his tentations.</hi> This which venerable <hi>Richard</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth, may in generall bee hoped for of the goodneſſe of God, but more certaine it is, in thoſe thinges which bee donne throughe obedience, for when they be of them ſelues lawfull, although the ſuperiour that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribeth
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:14230:78"/> them may erre through ignorance, or malice: yet the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent that in thoſe thinges o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyeth, can not erre by obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, for as much as hee doth in that the will of God, concerning which point, and of the neceſsity<note place="margin">Tract. 4. c. 34. &amp; tract. 5. p. 1. cap. 2. tract. 6. p. 2. c. 10. &amp; 11.</note> and profit which commeth by obedience to our ghoſtlye fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, elſe where more hath bene ſpoken.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>Chap. XII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of an other exellent remedy to deliuer our ſelues from the harme of ſecret ſinnes, and to ſupply the defectes of our former confeſsions, and that is, with care and diligence, to make a generall confeſsion.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>Beſids the former meanes now ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of, ther remaineth yet
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:14230:79"/> an other, very excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, by which Gods ſeruant may deliuer him ſelfe from ſuch ſecret ſinnes, as proceede from culpable igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and from other diſorders before handled. This meanes is, to make a generall confeſsion of all the ſinnes of his life paſt: taking for that, the ſpace of a weeke, in which diſcharging him ſelfe from all other buſineſſe, let him enter into himſelfe, &amp; run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ouer the ten commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements, let him call to minde as much as he can, all the ſinnes of his life paſt, and make his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion of them: and by the help and direction of his ghoſtly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther choſen out for that purpoſe, the doing of it will be eaſie and ſweete, in ſuch ſort that in an hower or two, he may diſpatche it, though it be a confeſsion of
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:14230:79"/> many yeeres. When as a man in his former confeſsions hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed ſome mortall ſin through ſhame, vaine feare, or becauſe he would not beſtowe any time about the examination of his conſcience, or if he went to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion without a purpoſe to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine from mortall ſin, in theſe caſes, to make a generall confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, both of all thoſe ſinnes vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered in that former bad confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and of all other ſins com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted afterward, is a thing ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary and commanded by the lawe of God. But when a man hath diſcharged himſelfe well in his former confeſſions, certaine and ſure it is, that bounde hee is not to make a generall confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, nor to confeſſe againe thoſe ſinnes, which before he did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe: but although there be no
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:14230:80"/> bande or precepte, yet verye good and heauenlie counſell it is, and a worke of wonderfull profit, for many reaſons foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the lawe of God and in experience, which briefely now I meane to runne ouer.</p>
               <p>One of the thinges which doth much humble man, is the knowledge of him ſelfe, his owne infirmitie, his owne ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, and eſpeciallye of his ſinnes and vvickedneſſe. And for this cauſe <hi>Saint Augustine</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Tract. 25. in Iohan.</note> calleth humilitie <hi>the knowledge of a mans ſelfe,</hi> becauſe it ſpringeth from that, as from the cauſe and roote thereof. And <hi>Saint Bernarde</hi> ſaith, that <hi>humilitie is a contempt of him ſelfe, as of a verie</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Tractat. de gradibus humilitatis</note> 
                  <hi>vile thing, growing from the true knowledge thereof.</hi> Seing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a man in a generall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion,
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:14230:80"/> calleth to minde all his ſinnes, and beholdeth them all muſtered togither before him, doth conſider and note them more attentiuely, &amp; more clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly doth perceaue all his infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, all his ignorance, and all his malice, by that meanes doth he humble himſelfe, thinke baſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of himſelfe, as hee deſerueth: and diſpiſeth himſelfe as a moſt vile and vvreatched creature. To this may bee alſo added, that hee doth open all his ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, and malice, to an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther man like vnto him ſelfe, and of all that doth accuſe and blame him ſelfe, crauing at his handes, that hee vvould cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recte and punniſhe him, and inioyne him ſuch pennaunce for his ſinnes, as hee iuſtlye deſerueeh: And as all theſe bee
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:14230:81"/> ſuch actions, by which a man doth abaſe, contemne, and han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle himſelf as a miſerable wretch ſo of them humilitie of hart doth encreaſe: and hereof it procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth that Almighty God, whoſe property is to exalt the humble, and to beſtow vpon them grace, light, and comfort, ſeing a man in this manner to bee humbled, giueth him newe and plentifull giftes of grace, wherewith hee doth enriche his ſoule, and giue it new beames of heauenly light, by meanes whereof he doth lay open before him all ſuch grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous ſins, as through ignorance &amp; lacke of conſideration before time he left vnconfeſſed,</p>
               <p>One of the thinges likewiſe, which maketh a man patientlie to endure the miſeries of this life as infirmities of body, pouerty,
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:14230:81"/> iniuries, &amp; perſecutions of men, &amp; the ſcourges of the Diuell, is, to knowe and conſider the pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts which for his grieuous ſinnes he deſerueth: when a man examineth and confeſſeth onely his veniall ſinnes, which hee did ſince his laſt confeſſion, &amp; doth not conſider nor ponder thoſe which in other times he hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, vnwillingly doth he ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer any punniſhment or iniurie, and doth complaine and grieue at litle thinges: but when he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth a generall confeſſion, then doth he enter into the cloſet of his owne conſcience, and doth there behold the bottomleſſe pit of wickedneſſe, and doth looke vpon his heart as an impoſtume from whence ſuch corruption of ſinnes did proceede, and then doth he think vpon the grieuous
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:14230:82"/> paines, which for them hee hath deſerued, and iudgeth hel fire to be to litle for the iuſt puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of ſuch horrible ſins, committed againſt the maieſty of God. And ſo doth hee willinglye offer him ſelfe with patience, to endure all the afflictions &amp; miſeries of this life, and dare not complaine of any harme, or aduerſity that befalleth him, knowing how li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle all is to that which he deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth. Bleſſed <hi>Saint Gregory</hi> the Pope, who was a mirrour of all vertue, being vniuſtly perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by <hi>Mauritius</hi> the Emperour, and very iniuriouſlie entreated, the holy man calling to minde, ſuch ſinnes as hee had commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, in not ſeruing of God, with ſuch puritye and perfection as hee ought, endured all thoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuries with ſuch patience, that
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:14230:82"/> writing to the ſame Emperor, he vttereth theſe wordes: <hi>I beleeue</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ep. ad Mau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritium.</note> 
                  <hi>that thou ſhalt ſo much the better ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſe the wrath of Almighty God, by how much more ſeuerely thou ſhalt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict and punniſh mee, becauſe I haue ſo badly ſerued him.</hi> If the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of ſuch ſmall ſinnes, did cauſe this <hi>Saint,</hi> to thinke that hee deſerued any kinde of pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhmente for them, and was a motiue, ſo vvillingly to haue ſuffered them, how much more will the conſideration of ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and ſo greate ſinnes, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with that heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye lighte, vvhich God beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vpon him, that humbleth him ſelfe in makinge of a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall confeſſion, cauſe him to thinke, that farre more iuſtly he doth deſerue any paines, that God ſhall in this life lay vpon
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:14230:83"/> him, &amp; with patience to endure the ſame.</p>
               <p>Beſides all this, that which doth very much mooue a chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian man to loue God, and to be loued of him, is to conſider well the particular benefits and mercies which of him he hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued: and this falleth out in a generall confeſſion, wherein a man by calling to mind his ſins, and confeſſing them, doth en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into conſideration, and pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, what greate mercies God hath ſhewed him, in deliuering him from ſo great euils, &amp; from ſo many great dangers of euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting damnation, &amp; in ſuffering with ſo great patience, ſuch no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table iniuries as he hath done a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, and pardoning with ſo great clemency ſuch heigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous ſinnes: and that whereas
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:14230:83"/> he hath ſo longe time offended God, ſo boldely, and ſo without all ſhame, yet hath he lik a moſt mercifull father, continually be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed vpon him incomparable benefites: and at that very time, when he did diſpleaſe and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne him, by his wicked life, did the ſame good Lord preſerue him, cheriſh, and maintaine him with his creatures, inſpired into his ſoule holy cogitations, and did offer for him vnto his eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall father, the merits of his ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred paſſion: And whereas hee might moſt iuſtly, infinite times haue throwne him into hell, as he did diuers other ſinners, yet delt he not ſo with him, but ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, and preſerued him from the furie of the Diuelles, and with his potent hand, deliuered him from the bandes of his ſins,
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:14230:84"/> and the daunger of euerlaſtinge damnation. The knowledge of theſe verities, doth a generall confeſſion worke, bringing to a mans memory all the ſinnes of his life paſt, and making him to accuſe himſelfe for committing them, and with this ſpiritual fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, doth hee encreaſe more &amp; more, in the feruent loue of ſo pitifull a Lord and maiſter, who with ſuch incredible longanimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty hath expected and endured him, and with ſo greate loue &amp; ſweetnes, hath cheriſhed, made much of, and drawne him vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him ſelfe, and with ſuch fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther lie pitie hath pardoned him, and therefore doth hee praiſe him, bleſſe him, giue him thanks, and ſing foorth his mercies, ſaying vvith the Prophet <hi>Dauid. If our Lorde had not helped me, my</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 93.</note>
                  <pb n="143" facs="tcp:14230:84"/> 
                  <hi>ſoule had now beene, in hell. Bleſſed be</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 123.</note> 
                  <hi>our Lorde who hath not ſuffered me to periſhe betwixte the teethe of mine enemies the Diuelles; beeinge made their pray: my ſoule throughe his pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etie and grace, hath beene deliuered from the wicked ſnares of them, that woulde haue carried me to euerlasting damnation. Thou haste broken in pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 115.</note> 
                  <hi>O Lorde, the bandes of my ſinnes and paſsions, and therefore will I al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies offer vnto thee, the ſacrifice of praiſe and thankes giuing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this may be added, that of ſuch ſinnes as a man hath in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer time confeſſed, and yet had not then haply all that contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and ſorow which was requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit, being now when hee maketh his generall confeſsion, touched more forcibly with Gods diuine inſpiration, &amp; illuminated with greater light fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heauen, he doth
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:14230:85"/> more bewaile, conceaue greater griefe in his ſoule, and doth ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfie God for them with more ſorrowe and contrition of hart: And to newe griefe for his old ſinnes, he ioyneth alſo a newe purpoſe of the amendment of his life, and ſo the whole man is renewed, and becommeth bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and more zealous in the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of God. Theſe and other ſuch like reaſons do declare, the ſingular commodities, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dounde to the ſoule by making of a generall confeſſion, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience teacheth them to be ſo ſure &amp; certaine, that thoſe which hath made it, doe ſay that they would not for the whole world, haue wanted that ſpirituall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, which by meanes thereof their ſoule hath receaued. But neceſſary it is here to note, that
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:14230:85"/> although the fruites of a general confeſſion wel made, be ſo great and pretious, that yet one may exceede therein: as for exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, when a man hath made a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall confeſſion once or ofte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and it was well done, and that to a prudent and diſcreete ghoſtly father, and yet for al this he woulde once againe, make an other generall confeſſion, not moued vpon any of thoſe good reaſons now ſpoken of, as for to humble himſelfe the more, and to begin with a more reſolute de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>termination to amende his life, but only vpon ſcruples, becauſe hee thinketh that he was not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore well confeſſed, and that by an other generall confeſſion he ſhall quiet his conſcience: in this caſe, when the prudent ghoſtly father knoweth, that it is a ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:14230:86"/> that moueth him to deſire it, conuenient it is, that he ſhoulde not doe it, becauſe the way to ouercome a ſcruple, is not to yeelde vnto it, but to reſiſt it, &amp; to doe contrary to that which it woulde, and the dutie of a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall father in this caſe is, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine what is a ſcruple, and what is a iuſt cauſe, for one to confeſſe that which hath beene confeſſed before, &amp; to ſet down what is expedient for the peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to doe. And the duty of the penitent or ghoſtly childe is, to beleeue and obey his ghoſtly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and that peace and quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of conſcience, which he ſhall neuer obtaine by yeelding vnto the ſcruple, ſhall he finde by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuing and obeying his ghoſtly<note place="margin">Tract. 5. p. 1. cap. 2.</note> father, as before hath beene de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <pb n="147" facs="tcp:14230:86"/>
               <head>Chap. XIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of ſuch defectes, as bee an impediment to many, which doe often communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate, that they receaue not the plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull fruite of the B. Sacrament.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>AMong ſuch perſons as fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent the ſacramentes, as there bee ſome which by often receauing of the Bleſſed Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, doe encreaſe, and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully proceede in all vertue: ſo there be ſome other, which do often communicate, and though they finde not their conſcience guilty of any mortall ſinne, yet doe they not profit, nor goe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in vertue, as reaſon would, nor feele in their ſoules, many of thoſe heauenly effectes, which they haue experience of, that do
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:14230:87"/> communicate with all that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition which is requiſit: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is a thing of great impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, to lay open the cauſes of this ſo great a ſpirituall damage, and the remedies for the ſame. The ordinary cauſes of this litle profit, and ſpirituall harme in ſuch kinde of perſons bee two. The one is, to receaue the B. ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament onely vpon cuſtome, that is, not hauing before hand, any conſideration or ſpirituall feeling of that, which they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tende to doe, but onely mooued of a certaine dry cuſtome, which they haue to communicate, as they haue in other buſines which is, as though they ſhoulde ſay, I communicat becauſe others doe it, and becauſe I haue of longe time vſed it, and I will doe that which I ſee other vertuous per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:14230:87"/> do practiſe: An other cauſe is, aduiſedly to fal into many ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall ſinnes and not to correct or amend them. Such veniall ſins as for want of care and diligence, they fall into that feare God, &amp; be diligent in his ſeruice, worke not this harme, but thoſe onely which be committed deliberat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by them that be lukewarme, and ſlacke in the ſeruice of God, as for example, longe diſtracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of vaine thoughtes, merrie lies, little detractions, and impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, light laughing, ſuperflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous care and curioſitie in appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell, in meate, in recreation, and ſpending of time, ouer much tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, preſumption of themſelues in their own hart, to praiſe them ſelues in wordes, to loue honor, &amp; commendatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of men, and cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſities of the ſenſes. Into theſe
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:14230:88"/> and ſuch other like veniall ſins (whereof wee haue ſpoken be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore)<note place="margin">Tract. 6. p. 2. cap. 1. &amp; ſequent.</note> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a man aduiſedly doth fall, and correcteth not himſelfe by true pennance, and amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of life, they work that harm nowe ſpoken of, and doe greatly hinder the fruite of the bleſſed Sacrament.</p>
               <p>The reaſon hereof is, becauſe<note place="margin">D Thom. 3 p. q. 80. art. 10. &amp; in 4. d. 9. q. 1. ar. 4. q. 2. D Bona. in faſciculario cap. 8.</note> as al holy men do teach, to come vnto the holy communion, and to receaue the great and plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modity, which by meanes thereof God vſeth to beſtow v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon his ſeruants, requiſite it is, to come with much deuotion, &amp; that a man doe for his part what lieth in him to haue it. And to come to the bleſſed Sacrament with deuotion, is to bring a fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent deſire and ready minde to pleaſe God, and to dedicat him<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelfe
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:14230:88"/> from his very hart to his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine ſeruice, and to come with an hunger to be ſpiritually refre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed by this diuine banquet and foode of heauen. And becauſe this deuotion is wrought in the ſoule by meditation of heauenly thinges, and by purity of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, as holy men affirme, &amp; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience<note place="margin">D Thom. 22. q. 82. art. 3.</note> doth teach, hereof it proceedeth that for a man to offer to communicate, not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing prepared him ſelfe before hand by prayer and meditation, and to purge away veniall ſins, which do diſtracte and make the ſoule ſome what colde, he doth not receaue all the fruite of the holy communion. This reaſon ſo ſure and certaine, and ſo wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of conſideration, <hi>Saint Bona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture</hi> doth note in theſe words.<note place="margin">De prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat. ad miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſam. cap. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>When thou mindeſt to communicat, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:14230:89"/> firſt with what charity and fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uor of deuotion thou commeſt, becauſe to communicate as is conuenient, wee ought not onely to auoide mortall ſinnes, but alſo to ſhun veniall, which through negligince, idleneſſe, diſtraction, or an cuill cuſtome be multiplied: for although they doe not kill the ſoule, becauſe they take not away the life of grace, yet doe they make a man more colde, more vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuoute, vnwilling to doe good, &amp; make him ill prepared and diſpoſed, to receaue the holy communion: wherefore hee that mindeth to communicat, let him firſt hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen with Gods grace, and ſtirred vp to deuotion by good meditations and kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dled with the flame of charity, banniſh from himſelfe the duſt and chaffe of ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall ſinnes: and therefore haue care O chriſtian, that thou commeſt not to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municat without conſideration, nor much colde in deuotion, for then thou commeſt not with that diſpoſition, which thou
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:14230:89"/> ſhouldeſt haue.</hi> All theſe bee the wordes of <hi>S. Bonauenture:</hi> in which he doth ſet down, what the cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes be, that hinder ſuch as fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent the B. Sacrament, from receauing that great profit and good, which by meanes thereof they both might &amp; ought. And although it be a common &amp; true opinion, that for ſuch cauſes and ſins as theſe, which be not mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall, that ſuch as communicat do not loſe all the fruit of the B. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, but that they receaue encreaſe of grace, yet certaine alſo it is, that they doe loſe that plentifull and abundant fruit of diuers graces &amp; vertues which are ordinarilye beſtowed vpon ſuch as come better prepared, &amp; other wonderfull effects which vſually it worketh in their ſoules that are more pure and deuout.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <pb n="154" facs="tcp:14230:90"/>
               <head>Chap. XIIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Wherein is declared more at large, howe for the receauing of more abundant fruit of the holy Communion, conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient it is, to purifie the ſoule from ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall ſinnes.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>OVt of the premiſſes, Gods ſeruants that frequent the holy Communion may gather, what meanes they haue to vſe, for the amending of theſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectes and the remouing of theſe impediments: whereof one is, much to enforce themſelues, to avoide not onely mortal ſinnes, but alſo to diminiſh and leſſen what they can thoſe that bee ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall, vſing for that ende morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, whereof before we haue at large entreated, for that is the<note place="margin">Tract. 6.</note>
                  <pb n="155" facs="tcp:14230:90"/> meanes by which the ſoule is cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of the diſeaſe of her paſſions, and is purified from veniall ſins, which out of them doe ſpring. And with this purity, a chriſtian man may ſecurely goe vnto that holy table, as <hi>S. Chryſoſtome</hi> doth exhorte him, ſaying: <hi>Come to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue God with all purity, and giue thy hart with great confidence: by this moſt holy body, which heere I receaue, I doe not account myſelfe any more to be duſt</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Homil. 24. in 1. epiſt. ad Corint.</note> 
                  <hi>and aſhes, no more to be a captiue but free becauſe I hope to obtaine heauen, and thoſe goodes which be there, as immortall and euerlaſting life, a place amongeſt the Angels, and the glorious company of Chriſt.</hi> Thus ſaith <hi>S. Chryſoſtome.</hi> And the glorious Pope <hi>S. Gregory</hi> doth note and ponder this point more in particular, &amp; that moſt excellently: who admoniſhing all faithfull chriſtians, to purifie
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:14230:91"/> themſelues from ſinne, for the receauing of the bleſſed Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſaith, that they ought not onely to cleere themſelues from mortall ſinnes, which doe whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hinder the fruite of this moſt diuine ſacrament, but alſo from veniall, which bee a let to that great ſpirituall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modity which would come by meanes thereof. Theſe be his wordes, worthy of due conſideration. <hi>Thoſe that come</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In expoſit. ſuper 1. reg. li. 1. cap. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>to receaue the conſecrated hoſte, which giueth true health, and doe harboure ſinnes in their ſoule, which they haue committed, doe not reccaue the fruite of health, and therefore albeit they receaue with their mouth, the true ſacrament, yet doe they not receaue with their ſoule, the vertue and fulneſſe thereof, becauſe that is receaued onely of them, that come fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting from ſinnes, and be adorned with vertues. And becauſe the iuſt alſo, and
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:14230:91"/> the elect ſeruants of God, cannot leade this life without falling into ſome ſins, therefore the remedy which they haue, is, that they enforce and ſtirre vp them ſelues, daily to purge their ſoule by pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, from thoſe daily ſins, into which they fall through humane infirmity, for if they haue not this care daily to puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie them ſelues from their ſins, although they be very ſmall, by litle and litle, the ſoule is filled full of ſinnes, which do depriue them of the fruit of the inwarde and ſpirituall fulnes: and therefore to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoide this harme</hi> S. Paule <hi>doth admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh a chriſtian man that hee ſhoulde prooue him ſelfe before he doth commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate, that is to ſay, that hee ſhoulde purge and diſcharge himſelfe from ſin, that being prooued and purified, he may come to the table of our Lord: wherfore ſeeing we ſinne daily, daily alſo let vs bewaile our ſinnes, and doe pennance for them, and the more carefully we doe
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:14230:92"/> purifie our ſelues from theſe daily ſinnes, with the ſorowe of penance, ſo much the more in that ſpirituall banquet, ſhal we receaue the abundant fruite of heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly grace.</hi> All this is out of <hi>S. Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory</hi> in which, diuinely he put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth a difference, betwixte that harme which mortall ſinne doth worke, which is to hinder the whole fruite of the bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, &amp; to make a man wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of condemnation: and the harme which cometh by veniall ſinnes, if they be not waſhed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way by pennance, for they doe much let the wonderfull com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity and effectes of the holy communion. And very ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly doth he admoniſh vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and iuſt men, to purge them ſelues daily from ſuch ſinnes, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peciallye when they meane to communicate, becauſe the more
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:14230:92"/> cleere they be from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſo much the more ſhall they receaue the plentiful fruite of heauenly gifts and graces, and eſpecially ſhall they feele in their ſoule that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine fulneſſe and inward ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe which is beſtowed vpon them that haue the true hunger of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>Chap. XV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How to receaue fruite of the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Sacrament, neceſſary it is, for a man to prepare himſelfe with recol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection, and meditation: and what manner of meditations or conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are good to bee vſed for that purpoſe.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>THE ſecond thinge, which the ſeruants of God haue to do, is to recollect them ſelues
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:14230:93"/> before they communicate, to the ende they may pray and medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate diuine thinges, conforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to thoſe documents which we preſcribed in the treatiſe of prayer: and although a man may out of any matter, which he me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditateth, drawe deuotion meete for the holy communion: yet the beſt and moſt fit conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to furniſh him ſelfe withall for this purpoſe, bee theſe. Let him meditate vpon the inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this moſt holy ſacrament in the laſt ſupper: how our Lord roſe from the table, tooke of his garment, and putting a linnen cloth about him, did vpon his knees waſh his Diſciples feete, and afterward when they were fet, how he tooke bread &amp; wine into his hands, &amp; by his omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent power did conſecrate &amp;
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:14230:93"/> change them into his body and bloud, which were vnited to his ſoule and diuinity, and how whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he had firſt communicated him ſelf, as many holy men do write, hee did ſtreight waies with his owne hands diſtribute his owne body and bloud to his Apoſtles, and withall gaue them authority alſo to conſecrate his body and to giue it to all faithfull people. Heere let a chriſtian man medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate attentiuely, that infinit mag<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nificence of the ſon of God, that liberality neuer before heard of, and that vnſpeakable charity, by which he voutſafed to giue him ſelfe, to be eaten in ſuch a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull ſorte, thereby to binde vs vnto him by a moſt ſtraight band of loue, &amp; by theſe meanes to heale our infirmities, and to make vs after his likeneſſe, holy,
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:14230:94"/> pure, diuine, and heauenlye. From this conſideration, let him labour to procure a greate hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and very feruent deſire to eate this breade of life, and to drawe from it a readye vvill to pleaſe in all thinges the author of life, who with ſo greate loue, doth giue himſelf to vs for meat: Let him likewiſe conſider and ponder, what great purity is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, to come to receaue this diuine foode, ſeing the Apoſtles that were in the ſtate of grace, &amp; cleere from mortall ſinnes, yet our Sauiour preparing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with more purity for the receauing of the holy communion, did waſh their feete, which was as <hi>S. Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Serm. de cena dom.</note> ſaith, to purifie them by a miſtery from their venial ſinnes: For the affections of the ſoule which doe quickly cleaue vnto
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:14230:94"/> earthly thinges, be the feete of our ſoul, &amp; theſe we muſt waſh, and make cleane to enter into heauen, and to come vnto the holy communion: and this mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery as that bleſſed ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſaith, did our Sauiour repreſent by that holy kind of waſhing. Out of this let a man likewiſe enforce him ſelfe, to be ſory for all his ſinnes, both mortall and veniall, and to purpoſe the amendment of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all: and beholding how vile, and vnworthy he hath made himſelf through his ſinnes, and that ſo great purity is required, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue ſo infinite maieſtye, in ſo much that if he ſhould prepare him ſelfe continuallye, for the ſpace of a thouſand yeeres, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue him, by deuoute prayers, holy workes, and with the merits of all Saintes, yet all woulde be
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:14230:95"/> very litle &amp; nothing, to receaue him as he deſerueth: let him en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuour alſo out of this to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue feare and reuerence: for as from loue, deſire groweth and a ready will, ſo from holy feare ſpringeth reuerence, with which he ought to come to the holy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion. An other conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion<note place="margin">Ambroſ. de ſacram. lib. 6. cap. 1.</note> wherewith Gods ſeruant may prepare himſelfe to come vnto the ſacred communio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with deuotion is this: Let him con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the dignity, and high maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty of that Lord, whome he is to receaue: let him thinke, howe in<note place="margin">Concil. Trident. ſeſſ. 13. c. 1.</note> that inſtant, in which the words of conſecration be ſpoken, the ſubſtance of bread, which remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnder the accidentes of the hoaſt, giueth ouer to be breade, by the conuerſion of the ſame, into the body of Chriſt, &amp; ſo the
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:14230:95"/> creature giuing place to the cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator, in that place where before was the ſubſtance of the breade, ſucceedeth the body of Chriſt, which was framed by the holye Ghoſt, in the wombe of the moſt immaculat Virgin: and becauſe the body of Chriſt liueth not without bloud, there alſo is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent the moſt pretious bloude of Chriſt, in the veines of his moſt holy body, and for as much alſo as the body of Chriſt liueth not without the ſoul, there is likwiſe his moſt glorious ſoule, in which are contained the vnſpeakable treaſures of the power and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of God: and for as much as the body and ſoule of Chriſt, are vnited with the perſon of God: Chriſt is God and man, &amp; he that is there contained, is true God, of infinit maieſty &amp; power.
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:14230:96"/> After this let him prepare him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to conſider with attention: Now I am to receaue God: and that hee may the better vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande what a Lord he is, whom he is to receaue, let him by me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation, place himſelfe at the gate of heauen, there let him conſider the glory, and beauty of that ſupreame maieſty, and behoulde, howe by his infinite bounty, he doth enflame vvith wonderfull loue all the citizens of heauen, and with the ſight of his eternall beauty, doth make them all bleſſed, and infinitlie delight them. Let him viewe, with what reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, al the ſaints and Angels, euen to the higheſt Seraphins, doe ſtande in his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, how they doe adore him, howe they doe praiſe him, howe they doe glorifie him, how they
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:14230:96"/> doe loue him: and after he hath ſpent ſome time in the admiratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſo infinite greatnes, &amp; glory, let him turne vnto him ſelfe, and thinke thus in his owne ſoule. This very God, whoſe maieſtie doth terrifie me, am I to receaue into my mouth &amp; body, this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finit good which doth make ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full the city of God, this ſelfe ſame am I to encloſe in mine heart, and this ſupreame creator of all thinges, before whoſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty, the Seraphins and all the glorious company of heauen, be proſtrate with great reuerence, him am I to beholde, &amp; to touch vnder thoſe accidents or out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde formes, and to receaue in to my body, for the foode of my ſoule. And this ſo great a Lord doth come vnto me, ouercome with loue, and drawne by loue,
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:14230:97"/> and he commeth to enamor mee of him ſelfe, and by loue to turne me into himſelfe, hee commeth to beſtow vpon me, the treaſures of his grace and glorye, and to tranſlate me from earth to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. Out of this conſideration will our ſoule gather great loue, and reuerence to come vnto the holy communion: for how can it chooſe, but bee burnt vp in loue, at the conſideration of ſo infinite goodneſſe and bountie, who hath done ſo many thinges for his loue, and who ſo deſireth his loue: how can it be, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a ſinner he ſhoulde not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence, with an holy kinde of feare, that infinite maieſtye be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whome with the eies of his ſoule, he beholdeth all the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſtand trembling for reuerence.</p>
               <pb n="169" facs="tcp:14230:97"/>
               <p>Other conſiderations, more<note place="margin">D Bonau. de prepara. ad miſſam. cap. 6. &amp; in faſciculario cap. 8.</note> proper and more vſuall, vvith which the ſoule hath to prepare it ſelfe, to receaue this moſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine ſacrament, be the miſteries of our Sauiours paſſion: for one of the principall reaſons of the inſtitutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of this ſacrament was, to the ende we ſhoulde alwaies haue preſent, and liuely in our memory, and affection, the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Chriſt, and all that which he did and ſuffered for vs, and this is repreſented vnto vs, in the miſtery of the Maſſe and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, and therefore a verie proper and fit preparation it is before communion, to diſcourſe by meditation, vpon ſome of the principall miſteries of his paſſion, and to entertaine our ſelues for ſome time with atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in ſome one of them. And
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:14230:98"/> from hence ſhall we alſo drawe as afterwardes ſhall be handled, the holy acts of contrition, feare, thankes giuing, loue, and reſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of our ſelues: in which thinges conſiſteth that deuotion which is neceſſary for the recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of the holy communion: &amp; very great reaſon there is, that wee ſhoulde vndertake this ſo ſmall a labor, as attentiuelie to conſider, what our good Lorde ſuffered for our ſake, ſeeing him ſelfe vouchſafed to ſuffer for our loue: and this meditation is ſo effectuall &amp; profitable, that by it, we doe diſpoſe our ſelues, to receaue the wonderful effects of this moſt heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly ſacrament. This admonition doth <hi>S. Cirill</hi> giue vs verye diuinelye in theſe wordes. <hi>I beſeech thee, that togither</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In Ioan. li. 4. cap. 17.</note> 
                  <hi>with thy holy life, thou doſt prepare thy
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:14230:98"/> ſelfe to communicate with godly conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations and beleeue me, that this bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of God</hi> (for ſo hee calleth the holy ſacrament) <hi>will deliuer thee, not onely from death but alſo from all the infirmities of thy ſoul, becauſe by meanes of this ſacrament, Chriſt dwelleth in our ſoules, and by his vertue doth he mitti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate and pacifie our paſsions, and quiet the perturbations of our heart, encreaſe and fortifie pietie and all vertue in vs, and doth deliuer vs from all ſinne.</hi> Thus writeth <hi>S. Cirill.</hi> Wherefore let Gods ſeruant, come to the holy communion, and let him come with a pure intention, and holy purpoſe, that is, to vnite him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe vnto Chriſt by perfect loue as to the ſpouſe of his ſoule, to heale his paſſions, to purge him ſelfe from ſinnes, to ſatiſfie for the paines thereof, to giue than<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes for benefittes receaued, to
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:14230:99"/> finde eaſe and comfort in tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, to ouercome ſome tenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and finally to obtaine ſome particular grace. Let him come with conſideration, with reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, with an hunger and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, ſpringing from loue, &amp; hee ſhall obtaine whatſoeuer he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſireth, becauſe hee is that good ſheepeheard, which ſaith &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeth,<note place="margin">Math. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>Come vnto me all ye that la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor and are burdened, and I will giue you repoſe and comfort.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <head>Chap. XVI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of that outwarde reuerence, humility, and modeſtie, with which we ought to come vnto the holy communion.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>ALthough the principall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion, requiſite for the ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly communion, conſiſteth in the
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:14230:99"/> hart, yet becauſe that which is externall proceedeth from the inward ſoule, &amp; God alſo requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth that, I haue thought good to ſet down ſuch defects, as here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſome time doe fall out, and to preſcribe remedies for the ſame. Some perſons which are carefull to ſerue God, and often goe to confeſſion, comming to the Altar to communicat be in their gallant, and braue apparel, their face drowned in their rufs, &amp; with gloues vpon their hand; and to maintaine their authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, deſirous they are to commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate alone, and to haue a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct place ſeparat from the reſt. All this is contrary to that reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence which is due to this moſte holy ſacrament, and to that hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility with which neceſſary it is, that they ſhoulde come to that
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:14230:100"/> diuine table. Reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce therefore requireth that they come with plaine and ſimple apparell, with a comely face &amp; modeſt handes: And if <hi>Saint Paule</hi> in prayer on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 2.</note> requireth this reuerence and outwarde modeſtie, how much more then conuenient is it that we ſhoulde haue the ſame, when wee come to the holy commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion. Humility alſo requireth, that a man ſhoulde acknowe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge him ſelfe vnvvorthye to approache vnto this holy table, and to thinke of him ſelfe, that any other perſon of thoſe which doe communicat, deſerueth at that time the better place, and alſo to be aſhamed, &amp; confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that they wil ſo much as ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit him to the loweſt roome in that heauenly banquet. If in the feaſte of a mortall man, or to
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:14230:100"/> eate vpon earthly meate, our Sauior requireth that we ſhould<note place="margin">Luc. 14.</note> come with this humilitie: how much more neceſſary is it, that this ſhoulde be obſerued, when wee come to this holy banquet, where he that inuiteth vs is God, and the meate which is receaued is God him ſelfe.</p>
               <p>Some likwiſe whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>muni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cat hold downe their heades too lowe, or do couer it, &amp; ſome do not ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their mouth in ſuch de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent ſort as is neceſſary for the receauing of the ſacred hoſt, and by theſe diſorders they be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time the cauſe that the prieſt do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth light with the B. ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon their cloake, or their lips, or ſome other part of their face &amp; that ſomtimes by this meanes it breaketh &amp; ſome ſmal peece fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth off: wherein they ought to
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:14230:101"/> conſider how great an inconue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience this is, ſeing in the leaſt peece of all, the glorious body of Chriſt is as entire, and vvith as much maieſty, as it is in the whol hoaſt, and as it is in heauen it ſelfe. Wherefore to auoide theſe inconueniences, &amp; to haue that modeſtie which is neceſſary, the duty of him that meaneth to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municat is, to haue his face vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered, ſtraight, and quiet, &amp; to vſe ſilence when the Prieſte commeth vnto him, becauſe it is no time then to pray vocally, &amp; therefore let him meditate vpon ſome good thinge inwardlye in his ſoule, and when hee is to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue, let him open his mouthe moderately, and put forthe his tongue towardes his lippes, and vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that receaue the ſacred hoſt, and when he hath taken it, let
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:14230:101"/> him not breake it, nor preſſe it with his teeth, but ſuffer it a litle to be moiſtened, and ſo to paſſe downe ſweetly, and with reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence: if there be any good ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall worke, conuenient to be well and decently donne: howe much more ought this, being ſo diuine, ſo important, &amp; ſo much to the glory of God? whereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that ſaying of <hi>S. Paul</hi> doth eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially agree. <hi>Doe all thinges with</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>honeſty, comlineſſe and good order.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <head>Chap. XVII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of that quiet and repoſe, with which we ought to come vnto the bleſſed ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament: and what thankes are to be giuen vnto God after the recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing therefore.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>AN other notable defect, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to which many perſons that
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:14230:102"/> frequent the ſacraments do fall, is, that they come to communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate with much haſt &amp; diſquiet, ſo that they are ſcarce entred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the church, or come from the feete of their ghoſtly father, but ſtraight way without any more ſtay, they goe to communicate: And that which is worſe, ſome ſo ſoone as they haue receaued, without giuing any more quiet or repoſe to that heauenly foode and without beſtowinge anye time in giuing of thanks to that diuine gueſt, whome they haue entertained, ſtraight waies goe out of the church, fall a talking with others, or elſe be take them ſelues to ſome other ſuch buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. Al theſe diſorders, do much hinder the fruit of this moſt holy ſacrament: and therefore very neceſſary it is, to preſcribe ſome
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:14230:102"/> remedy for the cure of the ſame: wherefore omitting to ſpeake of ſome particular caſe of neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, in which a man ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not expect, before he doth communicat, nor ſtay after hee hath donne: that which vſuallye herein is to bee obſerued is, that when hee go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to the holy communion, that he doe it with quiet and repoſe of minde, forgetting all earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly buſineſſe and cares, &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting them to the prouidence of God, to beſtowe his vvhole hearte in thinkinge vpon that infinite goodneſſe, which hee is to receaue, crauinge of him that hee vvoulde vouchſafe to adorne his ſoule with that hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie, that puritie and loue vvhich is requiſite. And let him ſtirre vp him ſelfe to doe ſo, vvith this conſideration:
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:14230:103"/> O Lorde, if a potent and riche king were to lie in the houſe of a poore widdowe, neuer woulde he expect that ſhe ſhoulde fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh that rome in which he were to lodge, but he woulde ſende his ſeruantes before hande, to prouide all thinges in good or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. What king is more potent &amp; rich, then thou O Lord, who art king of kinges, and Lord of Lordes? and what creature is more pore or miſerable, then my ſoule? Wherefore ſeeing thou vouchſafeſt to come, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe in it, ſend thy Angelles be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hand, to adorne it, to purify it, to illuminate and perfecte it, in ſuch ſort, as the ſuperior An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelles doe purifie and illuminate the inferior. Sende thy diuine preſents, thy perfecte gifts, thy heauenly treaſures, that my ſoul
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:14230:103"/> with ſuch celeſtial furniture may be adorned, and ſet in that good order, as is conuenient for the lodging of ſo mightie and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly a gueſt. And becauſe O Lord, neceſſary it is, that my ſoule ſhoulde alſo conſent and do what lieth in her power, ſend forth I beſeech thee, ſuch forci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble fauours, and effectual helps, that may make it wholly, ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and cheerefully, to obey thy diuine will. And when he hath craued this of our Sauior Chriſt, let him then turne him ſelfe to the bleſſed Virgin, and to ſuch Saints as his deuotion eſpecially affecteth, &amp; craue of them with humilitye that they woulde ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine for him the effecte of his petition.</p>
               <p>After communion, let him entertaine himſelf in the church
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:14230:104"/> the ſpace of a litle quarter of an hower whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> opportunity ſerueth not to doe more, and that time let him beſtowe in giuinge of thankes to our Lorde, for this moſt high and ſingular benefit, and in crauinge at his handes newe fauours and grace, that he may ſerue him better for the time to come. If one had his neere kinſman or friende, which came out of the Indies, vvith great ſtore of riches, &amp; were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous to lodge in his houſe, and that vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> great curteſy &amp; friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip which he beareth him, and with a minde to beſtovve vpon him part of his wealth, certaine it is, that when he ſawe him en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in at one dore, that he would not goe out at the other: but would keepe him continuall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, and be merry vvith him,
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:14230:104"/> giuing him ſuch entertainment for his welcome, and willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly giue him eare whileſt hee did diſcourſe of his trauailes and aduentures, and when he came to receaue thoſe riche giftes, which hee beſtowed vpon him, hartelie vvoulde he yeelde him thankes, and ſeeing him of a franke and liberall minde, and deſirous to giue yet more, no queſtion but he would demand all that which were neceſſary for himſelfe, and his family. In this maner ought we to behaue our ſelues towardes our Sauiour Chriſt, after we haue communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated: for he commeth vnto vs from the Indies of heauen, full of celeſtiall riches, which be of diuine and infinite value, and hee commeth, mooued of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere loue to lodge in our ſoule,
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:14230:105"/> to enrich it: and beginneth to beſtowe his gifts and treaſures vpon vs, &amp; hath a deſire to giue much more: let vs not then by and by forget him, and ſtraight waies buſie our mindes in other thinges far different: for what were this elſe, but for our Lord to enter in at one dore, and for vs to goe out at an other, which were contrary to all curteſie, &amp; oppoſite to all good manners: but let vs keepe him company, and be glad of his glory, and all that ſeruice which the Saints in heauen, and the iuſt vpon earth doe vnto him. Let vs giue him thanks from the bottome of our heart, for al thoſe benefits which he hath beſtowed vpon vs, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially for this, that he hath vour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafed to come, and remaine in our ſoule, by ſuch a miſtery and
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:14230:105"/> wonderfull meanes. And for this purpoſe let vs conſider who he is that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth, which is God with all his infinite perfection: &amp; to whome he commeth, &amp; that is to a ſinfull man, who often times hath offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded him: &amp; what moueth him to come, which is ſincere loue, and deſire of his good: and wherefore bee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, which is to beſtowe vpon him his merits, and the fruite of his ſacred paſſion, and death, &amp; the moſte pretious giftes of his grace, purchaſed with the inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable trauailes and ſorowes of thirty and three yeeres. After that Gods ſeruant hath wel me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditated vpon this, let him offer vnto him for a thankes giuing al the merits of his moſt holy paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and all the vertues which doe ſhine in that, and relying
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:14230:106"/> vpon theſe merits and ioyning them in companye with thoſe vertues, let him offer vnto him, good purpoſes of the amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his life, and reſolute de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires to make it much better: and let him craue pardon of thoſe ſinnes and faultes into which he hath fallen, in not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municating with all that puritie and deuoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which was requiſit. After al this, let him lay before him all his neceſſities, infirmities, ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norances, falles, and al the reſt of his miſeries, and let him craue for him ſelfe newe gifts, graces, vertues, and particular fauours, and withall let him aske the ſame for all Gouernors ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall and temporall. Let him pray alſo for ſuccor and help for all the neceſſities of the catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke church both generall and
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:14230:106"/> particular: for the encreaſe of true faith, religion, and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, for the conuerſion of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidelles and heritickes, and for the amendment of all ſuch as profeſſe the true faith of Ieſus Chriſt: and the ſelfe ſame thing let him alſo requeſt for all ſuch particular perſons as hee is bounde vnto, or hath any ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall deuotion.</p>
               <p>And here Gods ſeruant hath to vnderſtande that of all the times either of the day or night there is not anie one better to meditate, and praie, and to aske graces at Gods handes then this, in which after he hath communicated hee hath IESVS Chriſt preſent not onely as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerninge the preſence of his diuinitie, accordinge to vvhich hee is in euerie place, but alſo
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:14230:107"/> as touching the preſence of his moſt ſacred humanity, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally continueth ſo long in his bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy, as the ſacramentall formes doe there remaine. Whileſt our ſauiour was in this world in mor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tall fleſh, in all places where hee came, hee beſtowed particular benefits vpon all ſuch as vvith faith did touch him, or comme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d themſelues vnto his diuine ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie. He went into the houſe of <hi>Zacheus,</hi> &amp; of an vſurer made<note place="margin">Luc. 9.</note> him a iuſt man, and the ſonne of <hi>Abraham.</hi> Hee entred into the houſe of <hi>Matthew</hi> the publican, &amp;<note place="margin">Math. 9.</note> made him holy and an Apoſtle: Trauailing vpon the way, a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man<note place="margin">Math. 9.</note> that had an iſſue of bloude, did touch him, and forthvvith was ſhe cured. Being by the ſea<note place="margin">Mar. 4.</note> of Galile, all that had any infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities<note place="margin">Math. 21.</note> did touch him, and were
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:14230:107"/> made ſounde. Being in the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, the blind and the lame came vnto him, and he reſtored ſight to the firſt, and legges to the laſt. Being in the field vpon a moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, there came vnto him thoſe which were poſſeſſed of vvicked ſpirits, and they were deliuered: there repaired vnto him all that had any infirmities, ſtriuing to touch him, and vertue came fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him, &amp; he cured all. That which he did then viſiblie, being in the world, the ſelfe ſame thing doth he nowe inuiſiblie &amp; ſpiritually being preſent in the ſacrament, ſo that ſuch ſoules, as doe enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine him with a liuely faith, and deuotion, or hauing him in their bodye, come vnto him, and with feruent prayers and deſires touch him, thoſe doth hee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer from all their euils &amp; doth
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:14230:108"/> beſtowe vpon them wonderfull benefits, and giue vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> moſt pretious gifts, comforts, &amp; very ſpeciall fauours.</p>
               <p>Hereof and from the experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of this truth, doth it come that many hauing communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, are ſo willing and deſirous to recollecte them ſelues, and to think vpon our Lord, whome they haue receaued, to giue him thankes for this benefite, and to craue newe graces at his handes, to loue him more, and better to ſerue him, that for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getting all worldlie thinges, and as it were alienated from them ſelues, and rapt in God, they woulde not ſpende their time in any other thing then in this kind of exerciſe. All other buſineſſe for that time, doe grieue and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicte them, and this alone doth
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:14230:108"/> delight and giue them comfort. And therfore when either there owne or the neceſſities of others, or ſuch things as they are bound to do, by reaſon of there eſtate or calling, do permit them, they do cotinue long time with great pleaſure and content in this kind of thankes giuing. And for as much as holy deſires, and effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall purpoſes, be tried by the doing of good workes: to this thankes giuing it appertaineth vvhen abilitie doth ſerue, that a man after hee hath receaued the bleſſed ſacrament and with his hearte yeelded thankes as hath nowe beene ſaide, ſhoulde ſhewe him ſelfe alſo indeede thankfull for ſo greate a bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite, and doe that day as hee can, and is able, ſome worke of charitye, and mercie, for
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:14230:109"/> the commodity of his neighbors: as to giue ſomwhat in almes, to viſit ſome body that is ſicke, to comfort ſome that is in miſery, to teach ſome that is ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, or to doe ſome other ſpirituall or cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall worke of mercy. For great reaſon there is, that vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that day in which the king of glorie hath giuen him ſo great a pledg of his loue, and hath ſhewed him ſuch vnſpekable mercy, that he ſhold make his loue likwiſe manifeſt in the works of charity towards his neighbour, vſing mercy &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion towardes him, for this is the proofe that God requireth of vs for a teſtimony of our loue accordinge to that of <hi>Saint Iohn. This precept wee haue receaued from</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iohn. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>God, that he which loueth God, ſhould for his ſake loue his neighbour and bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="chapter">
               <pb n="195" facs="tcp:14230:109"/>
               <head>Chap. XVIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How to abſtaine from the ſacrament of the Aultar without iuſt cauſe, is an impediment to spirituall profit, and how that neither for negligence, or lacke of ſenſible deuotion, a man ſhoulde giue ouer the holie commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>AMongeſt ſuch perſons as haue begone to ſerue god, and for that ende doe help them ſelues, with the holy and lauda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble cuſtome of often repairing to the B. Sacrament: many there bee, which abſtaine from their ordinary cuſtome of communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating, which they did vſe once or twiſe a week, or euery fifteene daies, according to the counſell of their ghoſtly father: Such as
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:14230:110"/> doe ſo, by order from him, who for iuſt reſpectes doth thinke it ſo conuenient, certainelye they doe very well, to obey and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe that which he preſcribeth, and nothinge ſhall they loſe thereby, becauſe that which ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth one waye to bee denied them, if with humilitie they be obedient, GOD will recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence it an other, beſto we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vpon them newe fauoures and mercies, and giuing them ſuch a diſpoſition, by reaſon whereof, at one communion donne vpon obedience to their ghoſtly father, they ſhal receaue more grace and comfort then at many, taken vpon their owne will, as afterwarde ſhall be han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dled. But ſpeaking of ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, as (not by order from their ghoſtlye father, nor by his will
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:14230:110"/> and direction) do giue ouer that cuſtome of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municating, which they had, and their confeſſor did wel like of, I ſay that thoſe which doe ſo only vpon careleſnes and negligence, as not to giue ouer their other worldlye buſineſſe, or not to take the paine to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare themſelues, or not to binde themſelues to that care &amp; watch fulnes in leading of a good and vertuous life, a that holye cuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome requireth, plaine it is, and appara<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to all ſuch as haue reaſo, that they are worthy of blame, and to be condemned of a fault, ſeeing they doe without any iuſt cauſe giue ouer ſo good a cuſto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e: ſo glorious to God, &amp; ſo impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant &amp; profitable for their owne ſaluation, as before was decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the beginning of this trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe.</p>
               <pb n="198" facs="tcp:14230:111"/>
               <p>Other there bee, which ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine from the B. Sacrament v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon other cauſes more apparant, in which the fault or error, that they commit, &amp; the harme they incurre, is not ſo eaſilie percea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. One of theſe is, becauſe hauing at other times beene vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſited of God, when they did communicat, he preparing them for it, with a ſpirituall hunger &amp; liuely deſire of the communion, and helping them with ſpirituall light to meditate the miſteries of this diuine ſacrament, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue it with feruour of ſpirit, with ſweetneſſe of loue, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion: and giuing them when they did communicate, heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly motions, celeſtiall comforts, wonderfull peace, and tranqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of conſcience, ſwete medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, great alacrity, and vigor
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:14230:111"/> of minde, for all good workes: and ſeeing themſelues nowe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priued of all theſe good thinges, and that they haue no hunger, nor deſire to communicate, but faintneſſe and dulneſſe of ſoule: that they haue no light to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>template this or anye other mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery, but a darkneſſe and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion in their vnderſtanding: that they haue not any feruor or deuotion, to the B. Sacrament, but a drie and colde diſpoſition: and that alſo when they do com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate they feele not in their ſoule any ſpirituall taſte or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, and that after they haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued the Sacrament they find not any ſpirit or alacrity to good workes, but a loathſomneſſe to pray, and a griefe and heauineſſe to all kinde of vertue. When therefore theſe perſons find this
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:14230:112"/> greate mutation in themſelues, they verily thinke that they bee not well prepared to communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate, and that Gods pleaſure is that they ſhoulde not doe it, and for as much as great deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is required to come to the holy communion, which they vvant, therefore they ſuppoſe that they oughte not by anye meanes to doe it, and although their ghoſtly father doth aduiſe them to communicate, yet can they not bee perſwaded to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe his counſell, or that it is conuenient for them ſo to doe.</p>
               <p>Such perſons as theſe ought to conſider vvhat in this caſe they haue to doe, and that is, that this mutation vvhich they feele in them ſelues, is a proofe and triall of God, and that his pleaſure is, that as when he ſent
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:14230:112"/> them the ſweeteneſſe of his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nediction, they were animated to communicate, and to doe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther good workes, by reaſon of thoſe motions and ſenſible ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectes of his diuine preſence, which they found in their ſoule: ſo in like maner, that they ſhold now be moued to goe vnto the holy communion, &amp; to do other good works by the only directio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and perſwaſion of faith, not void of charity, but void of the feeling &amp; experimental motio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therof, &amp; be encouraged to worke and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor in the ſeruice of god, moued onely of an effectuall good will, which is the principal part of cha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rity, without any other ſweete viſitatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forts, which accor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding to Gods pleaſure proceede from charity, and doe make the works thereof eaſie &amp; pleaſant.
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:14230:113"/> And if in this manner they doe communicat, &amp; do good works and perſeuere in all their vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous exerciſes, moued by faith, and vpon a good mind, then do they keepe that fidelitie and loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty which they owe vnto God, ſeruing him not only in the time of proſperity, but alſo in the time of aduerſitie and tribulation: &amp; not only in the time of ſweetnes and comfort, but alſo in the time of griefe and deſolation. And let them knowe, that by ſuch a communion, and ſuch ſeruices done in the time of aduerſity &amp; diſcomforts, they doe content, pleaſe, and glorifie God, &amp; me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit for themſelues grace &amp; glory no leſſe, nay more, then in the time of proſperity and ſpirituall comfort, becauſe perſeuering in this manner, they ouercome, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie,
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:14230:113"/> and mortifie them ſelues the more, for the loue of God. And ſuch perſons are to knowe, that the want of deuotion, which (as before hath beene ſaid) is an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediment<note place="margin">In this trea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiſe cha. 13</note> for the receauing of the ſacred communion, is that which is voluntary &amp; commeth of careleſnes and negligence, &amp; becauſe a man will not doe that which lieth in him to come with deuotion: but when the lacke thereof is not volu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tary, becauſe a man with the helpe of Gods grace, doth vſe all thoſe meanes which for his part are neceſſary, as in purging his conſcience by confeſſion and contrition, from all his ſinnes both great &amp; ſmall, and preparing himſelfe to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate with prayer and medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, then the want of devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on doth not hinder the abunda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:14230:114"/> fruite of the holy communion: for although ſenſible deuotion hee hath not, yet hath hee that which is the beſt and moſt prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall, to witte that which conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth in purity and good wil, and a true deſire to pleaſe God, and to doe his holy will.</p>
               <p>Such perſons ought likewiſe to conſider, that as this mutati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which they feele in their ſoul, is a triall of God, and that if they perſeuere in frequentinge the holy ſacrament, and exerciſe of good works, that they do per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme that fidelitye which they owe vnto God: ſo oughte they alſo to perſwad them ſelues that if for this cauſe they ſhoulde ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine from the holy communio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and become more ſlow in doing of good works, that it is the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the ghoſtly enemy, to
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:14230:114"/> make them loſe the fruite of the bleſſed Sacrament and the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of good vvorkes, and ſo to haue an entrie into their ſoules by his temptations and deceits. And as that braue captaine <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſernes</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iudith. 7.</note> did, who to take the city of Bethulia that was ſo ſtronge and vvell manned, cut in two the conduits, by vvhich the vvater paſſed from the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine into the city: and by this meanes was he ready to haue ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken it, had not God miraculou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſly deliuered them: euen ſo dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the prince of darkneſſe, who ſeing that fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſt who is the fountaine of all graces, our ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour and helpe doth come, to defende vs from his aſſaultes, by meanes of the Sacraments, deſirous hee is to breake and cutte in tvvo theſe heauenlie
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:14230:115"/> conduits and diuine pipes, ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting impedime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts before vs, that we may not frequent the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>Palla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius</hi> reporteth how a certaine ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry<note place="margin">In hiſtoria Lauſaica in vita S. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carij.</note> vertuous woman which did frequente the ſacramentes was by a wicked man tempted, to committe ſinne, which ſhe vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly deteſted: whereupon the graceleſſe wreatch delt with a coniurer, who by the arte of the Diuell laboured to induce the woman to yeeld her conſent, but ſtill ſhe reſiſted valiantly, &amp; ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer woulde be perſwaded to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent vnto anye ſuch damnable ſuggeſtion. The Diuell ſeeing that he could not hurt her ſoule, laboured to change her outward forme and ſhape, to the eyes of men: and ſo he transformed her, that ſuch as beheld her, toke her not for a woman, but verelye
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:14230:115"/> thoughte her to bee a mare. Whereupon in the company of her husbande, ſhe went for help vnto <hi>S. Macharius,</hi> who caſting holy water vpon her, delivered her from that illuſion: and hee told her, that the reaſon why the Diuel had ſuch power ouer her, was, becauſe ſhe was negligent in repairing to the ſacraments as hauing not beene at the holye communion of fiue weekes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and the holy man gaue her counſell neuer after to be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les therein, ſpeaking thus to her in great zeale. <hi>Neuer</hi> (quoth he) <hi>abſtaine from the communion of the moſt pure ſacraments of Chriſt, becauſe for this negligence this euill hath befallen you, for it is fiue weekes ſince you were at them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is that which the Diuell pretendeth, when hee perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:14230:116"/> a man to abſtaine from the holy communion, to depriue his ſoule of the gard and defence of the ſacraments: that findinge it weake and careleſſe, hee may by his tentations and deceits ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come it: and therefore Gods ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant ought to reſiſt the tentatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and not for this cauſe to refraine from the holy communion. The veritye of this doctrine our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chriſt taught bleſſed <hi>Saint</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In lib. ab ipſa ſcript.</note> 
                  <hi>Katherine</hi> of Bononia who hauing for ſome yeeres endured moſt pi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tifull tentations of drines of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, of being forſaken, of diſtruſt &amp; tentations againſt the faith of this moſt holy ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, yet ſhe reſiſted valia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly, &amp; perſeuering with great conſtancy in frequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, &amp; in all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther exerciſes of praiers, &amp; good works, our Sauiour Chriſt vout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafed
<pb n="209" facs="tcp:14230:116"/> at length againe to viſit his ſeruant, &amp; amongſt other things he tolde her, how that when any perſon did communicate, with a good co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, although it were without feelinge of deuotion, yet did he for al that receaue the grace of the ſacrament, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he were tempted in faith or troubled with any other te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, yet if he gaue no co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent, he did not for al that leaue of, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue the plentifull fruite of the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: And that ſuch a man, did not only gaine more by figh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ting againſt ſuch tentations, but alſo by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municating did merit much more then if he ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue the ſacrament with much ſweetnes, and ſenſible deuotion, which is to be vnderſtood when the want thereof procedeth not fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the fault &amp; neglige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:14230:117"/> perſon him ſelfe, but by the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence of God, who doth by ſuch meanes try and prooue his ſeruant, as nowe hath beene de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="chapter">
               <head>Chap. XIX.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How for ſcruples and vaine feares, wee ought not to abſtaine from the holy communion.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>OTher perſons there bee, which although they haue not founde any ſuch mutation in their hartes, yet being of a good conſcience, they abſtaine from the B. Sacrament, contrary to the minde and counſell of their ghoſtlye father, mooued vpon ſcruples and vaine feares, &amp; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they think not themſelues worthy to repaire ſo often to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:14230:117"/> the food of Angels, &amp; that it ſhoulde be in them more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence to abſtaine from the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion. And when this temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation falleth to Prieſts, the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantes of God, it is a thinge of greater harme, becauſe it doeth not onely depriue them of the profit of the ſacrament, but alſo the whole church of the fruite of the ſacrifice, ſeing certaine it is as <hi>S. Bonauenture</hi> and other holye<note place="margin">Lib. de pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parat. ad miſſam. ca. 5.</note> men doe teach, that ſo often as a Prieſt may lawfully celebrate, &amp; yet doth not, that he doth vvhat in him is, depriue the moſte holy Trinity of glory, and praiſe, the Angelles of ioy, ſinners of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, the iuſt of grace and ſuccor, the ſoules in purgatory of eaſe &amp; comfort, &amp; the whole church of a ſingular benefit. The reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy againſt this tentation is, for a
<pb n="212" facs="tcp:14230:118"/> man to beleue his ghoſtly father and to relie vpon him, and to do againſt his ſcruples as elſe where hath beene ſaid. And heere we haue to note, that to come wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily &amp; with due reuerence vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this moſt holy and worthy ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramente, may be vnderſtoode two manner of waies: one is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable to the dignity &amp; pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritye of that Lorde whome we receaue, and that vvhich his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite maieſtie deſerueth: and in this ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner none commeth wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thilie, and with due reuerence, no though one ſhould beſtowe time in preparing him ſelfe to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municat ſo long as the world ſhall endure, no nor though hee alone ſhoulde haue all the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritye and holyneſſe of all the iuſt men vpon earthe, and all the Saintes in heauen. An o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="213" facs="tcp:14230:118"/> manner to come worthily, and with due reurence, is in reſpecte of that which God of neceſſitie doth require at our handes, and by bande of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepte: and in this ſorte, all thoſe that come ſo diſpoſed, as in the premiſſes hath bin han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dled, doe come worthely, and vvith due reuerence: becauſe God of his infinite pietie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcending to our infirmitye, vvoulde not binde vs to anye more. And ſeing to iudge whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in this ſence the penitent hath due diſpoſition or no, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth to the ghoſtlye father, who is wiſe &amp; of a good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, a man may ſecurely follow that which he ſhall aduiſe him. And that Gods will is, that a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould ouercome ſuch ſcruples and feares, by the meanes of
<pb n="214" facs="tcp:14230:119"/> good counſell, God hath by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny<note place="margin">Petrus de Aliaco in eius vita. Surius in Maio.</note> teſtimonies declared. <hi>Saint Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Celeſtinus,</hi> who from the ſtate of a pore Monke, was for his great holines of life, choſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be Pope, moued vpon feare that he was a moſte vnworthye ſinner, lacked vertue, and for other ſuch like reaſons, would neither celebrat, nor communicate. Whereupon touching this pointe hee craued counſell of a Monke his ghoſtly father, who did encourage him to ouercome thoſe feares and to ſay Maſſe, which he did: &amp; our Sauiour apearing to him, taught him the ſame leſſon, &amp; ſo he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained ioyfull, and with greate quiet of conſcience. <hi>Caſsius</hi> an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly man and Biſhop of Narnium did daily ſay Maſſe, to the great profit of his ſoul: and to the end he ſhould not for any ſuch feare
<pb n="215" facs="tcp:14230:119"/> giue ouer that good cuſtome, <hi>S. Gregory</hi> reporteth how God ſent vnto him an holy prieſt, to whom he appeared, to deliuer him this meſſage. <hi>Do that thou doeſt, work that</hi>
                  <note place="margin">4 Dialog. cap. 56.</note> 
                  <hi>thou workeſt, let not thy foote ceaſe, let not thy hand ceaſe, and I will giue thee thy reward:</hi> exhorting him by theſe wordes to perſeuere in his good life, and holy cuſtome of ſaying Maſſe. The reaſon why God did thus co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort &amp; animate theſe ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly men by ſpecial reuelatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, was to teach all, that his pleaſure is, that his ſeruants which frequent this diuine ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, ſhould qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et and aſſure the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues touching this matter by obeying the coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſell of wiſe men, for this was the rule which theſe holy men did followe and that which God did alowe of.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="chapter">
               <pb n="216" facs="tcp:14230:120"/>
               <head>Chap. XX.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>With what moderation we ought to fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent the holy communion, that wee doe not therein exceede, nor doe any thinge contrary to due reuerence: and howe wee ought to leaue this to the iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of a diſcreet ghoſtly father.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>AS there be ſome perſons, which with hurte to their ſoules, do without any iuſt cauſe refraine to communicate often, as hath beene now ſaid: ſo there be others which doe exceede in the other extreame deſiring to come oftener, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is conuenie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: Of theſe ſome are moued ſo to do, vpon the commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> conceit &amp; opinion which they haue of the fruite that is receaued in the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly communion: others becauſe
<pb n="217" facs="tcp:14230:120"/> they haue had ſomtimes experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the comfort and ſvveet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of this moſt heauenly ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: Others are moued vpon a kind of lightneſſe, which is for emulation one of an other, and to maintaine theire good opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, &amp; not to be accounted leſſe vertuous then others, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore are they angry and do com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine and bee out of patience whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they are not ſuffered to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate, which is a plaine ſigne that they are not moued of anye good ſpirit, but prouoked of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghtnes: For al theſe kind of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, the doctrine of this chapter ſhall ſerue: and it is a thinge of great importa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, &amp; much to the glory of God, aſſuredly to take the middle way in this holy exer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ciſe, without falling either into the one extreame, or the other.</p>
               <pb n="218" facs="tcp:14230:121"/>
               <p>As touching the firſt, certaine it is, that all ſecular perſons, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well men as women, muſte not herein bee ruled accordinge to their owne opinion, neither muſt they follow their owne content, their owne comfort, nor their owne inclination, but they muſt ſubmit themſelues to the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell and direction of theire gho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtly father: for if in religious peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, the rule of their order and obedience to their ſuperiors doe in this thing preſcribe them that meaſure and moderation, which they ought to keepe: reaſon it is, that ſuch as bee not in religion, that their ghoſtlye father vvho knoweth the ſtate of their ſoule, ſhoulde appoint them that rule which they oughte to obſerue: And the confeſſor or ſpirituall father, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for this purpoſe they
<pb n="219" facs="tcp:14230:121"/> ſhould make choiſe of, ought to be wiſe, of experience, and one that feareth God, &amp; that ſhould not herein reſpecte the comfort of the penitent, or to get credit with him, or any ſuch like thing, but only that which is moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient for the glory and ſeruice of God, and the good of mens ſoules. And the penitent ought not herein to labor either by im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity, or intreatie, or anie other ſuch meanes to drawe his ghoſtly father to that which plea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeth himſelfe, for that were not to obey him, but contrariewiſe for the ghoſtly father to obey the will of his penitent, and ſo his iudgement and opinion ſhoulde in this caſe be erromous: but the penitent ought to leaue his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor free, to determine that which in our Lorde hee ſhall
<pb n="220" facs="tcp:14230:122"/> thinke moſt expedient, and let him ſhew plainly that it ſhal wel content him whatſoeuer he doth therein determine &amp; ſet downe. And let him alſo take heed that he goe not for this ende vp and downe ſeeking ſuch a ghoſtly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as doth beſt fit his humor, for then in punniſhment of ſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ordinate an affection, God will permit him to be deceaued, as it happeneth to ſom perſons which conſult about this point (as alſo in others) many ghoſtly fathers,<note place="margin">Note.</note> going from one to an other with a deſire to finde out him, that woulde tell them that which the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues would haue, and whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they light vpon ſuch a one, hee is the only man that doth pleaſe them, and him they prefer before all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: and alas, pitifully are they deceaued, for doing thus, they
<pb n="221" facs="tcp:14230:122"/> doe not conforme themſelues to the will of God, but to their own pleaſure and liking. Therefore that which Gods ſeruant hath to doe, not to be deceaued here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, is not to haue any reſpecte to his own pleaſure and opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but to deſire only, that the wil of god and that which is moſt for his ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nor may be done: and ſo let him co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſult with his ordinary ghoſtlie father, &amp; if he think not him ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient, let him goe to an other, not him that is moſt for his owne humor, but him in whom by the report of wiſe and iudiciall men, thoſe vertues are to bee founde which for this matter is requiſit. And let him craue of God that he vvoulde put into his hearte, that counſell, vvhich may di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recte him better in his holye ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, and that vvhich maye
<pb n="222" facs="tcp:14230:123"/> more redounde to the glorye of the ſame God, and the profit of his own ſoul. And hauing done thus, let him very quietlie fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe that counſell which he ſhal giue him, and be obedient, truſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in God, that when other di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection ſhall be more conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, that he will inſpire it into the heart of his ghoſtlye father, that hee maye giue order accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly. The holy virgin <hi>S. Lut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde</hi> beeing a religious woman, did vſe to communicate euerye weeke, &amp; this leaue which they gaue her, is agreeable to the minde of <hi>S. Auguſtine:</hi> very well<note place="margin">Thomas Cantipra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſis in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ius vita. Surius in Iumo.</note> content ſhee was. The Abbeſſe vvhich had charge ouer her, thinking that this was to much, gaue order that ſhe ſhould not communicate ſo often, wherein ſhe ſhewed her ſelfe very obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent,
<pb n="223" facs="tcp:14230:123"/> and God who had care of his ſeruant, did reueale vnto the Abbeſſe, that his pleaſure was, that his ſeruant ſhoulde keepe her old holy cuſtome, and ſo her former leaue take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> away, was by her ſuperior reſtored againe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="chapter">
               <head>Chap. XXI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of ſuch rules as holy men preſcribe, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the often receauing of the B. Sacrament.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>PReſuppoſing that the iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment how often in a weeke or month, Gods ſeruant hath to communicate that deſireth his owne ſpirituall profit, ought to be left to the diſcretion of his ghoſtly father: conuenient it is to ſet downe thoſe rules vvhich holy men herein preſcribe, that
<pb n="224" facs="tcp:14230:124"/> the confeſſor may know what he hath to do: for he hath to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand that it importeth much to be aſſured herein, &amp; not to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede at random but to followe that light which God hath left in his church.</p>
               <p>Certaine it is, that in the vſe of the holy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion, Gods wil is, that there ſhould be an order &amp; moderatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, how often one ſhold co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municat, and that it ſhold not be as men the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues liſt &amp; deſire. And this his wil hath he declared in that he hath by his church co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded vnder paine of mortall ſin, that no prieſt or prelat tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ugh<note place="margin">Alex. Papa cap ſufficit de conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crat. diſt. 1. Halenſis p. 4 q. 52. mem 3.</note> neuer ſo holy, ſhold vſually celebrate or communicate more then once a day. And the cauſe why the church hath ſo declared is as Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> ſaith, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers affirme, for the great reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence
<pb n="225" facs="tcp:14230:124"/> which is due to the B. ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, to which reuerence it ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pertaineth, that a man ſhold not goe to it, ſo often as himſelf plea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeth. If then for celebrating and receauing when one celebrate, being yet the common good of the church, Gods pleaſure is, that an order ſhold be ſet down and hath declared it in that very thing wherein his great glory, &amp; the profit of the whole church conſiſteth, that due reuerence to the B. ſacrament, might be pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſerued, by celebrating ordinarily no more then once a day, rather then he would that greate profit which mighte redounde to the church, if euery prieſt might ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> celebrat in one day: hereof doth it follow, that it is great reaſon &amp; very meet, that in particular co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, in which the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> good
<pb n="226" facs="tcp:14230:125"/> of the who! church is not ſo fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered, as by the ſacrifice of the Maſſe, that there ſhould bee a ſtraighter order and more mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration be vſed to preſerue due reuerence vnto ſo holy a ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>The rule which holy men doe<note place="margin">D Thom. in Paul. 1. Cor. 11. lect. 7.</note> in this matter preſcribe is, that when the ghoſtlye father per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaueth that one hath purity of<note place="margin">Gerſon de cognitione peccative<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nialis. p. 2.</note> heart and true deuotion to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate, and the more that he doth communicate, the more he encreaſeth in purity, and doeth more diminiſh his venial ſinnes, proceede more forwarde in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion and feruour, in patience, and charitie, and in all kinde of vertue: to this man conuenient it is, that he ſhoulde giue leaue to repaire more often to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly communion: but when he ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="227" facs="tcp:14230:125"/> one that frequenteth the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, to lacke true deuotion for that ſacrament, and that hee doth therby litle profit, becauſe he keepeth ſtill his former paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of anger, impatience, and pride, hath ſmall care of his ton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue, and doth eaſilie without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny reſiſtance fal into venial ſins, which do breede a kind of cold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in his ſoule, to him he muſt preſcribe abſtinence and not to come ſo often. This opinion, which is of all holy men <hi>S. Bona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture</hi> doth expreſſe in theſe wordes. <hi>In the primatiue churche,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">4 Sent. d. 12 ar vlt q. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>chriſtians had great purity of ſoule, and were feruent in charity, and ſo they might daily receaue the holy communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: after that this great purity was loſt, and that great feruor of charity waxed more colde, and lukewarme dispoſition entred in: he that now hath that purity
<pb n="228" facs="tcp:14230:126"/> and burning charity of the primatiue church, may likewiſe communicate euery day: but he that liueth coldely let him come but ſeldome, and hee that is in a meane, that is ſuch a one, who though he hath not that great feruor and puritie of the primatiue church, yet is he not luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warme, but doth proceede in vertue and walke forwarde to arriue vnto that great feruor, ſuch a one muſt keep a mean in frequenting of the communion, that he may ioyne loue with reuerence, in ſuch ſorte, that comming often to the bleſſed ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, he may be inflamed with loue, and abſtaining for ſome daies hee may learn to haue it in reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce.</hi> Thus ſaith <hi>S. Bonauenture.</hi> And <hi>S. Thomas</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth<note place="margin">3. par q. 80. ar. 10.</note> the ſame thinge in theſe wordes. <hi>He that findeth himſelfe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with deuotion and reuerence, may communicate daiely: for vpon this reaſon in the primatiue church, the faithfull did communicate euery daie: for then great
<pb n="229" facs="tcp:14230:126"/> deuotion did floriſh amongeſt them, but after that charity waxed more colde, that counſell which is to bee giuen to Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans is, that they communicate euerye Sonday.</hi> This is the opinion of <hi>S. Thomas,</hi> and he doeth confirme it with the authoritie of <hi>Saint</hi>
                  <note place="margin">De eccleſi. dogmat. cap. 33. &amp; cap. quoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die diſt. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Auguſtine</hi> and the doctrine of Gods church.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="chapter">
               <head>Chap. XXII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of that diſcretion, which ghoſtly fathers ought herein to obſerue, according to the doctrine of holy men.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>OVT of this doctrine of holye men, vvee maye gather, vvhat diſcretion gho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtlye fathers haue in theſe our dayes to obſerue in graun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinge or denyinge leaue to
<pb n="230" facs="tcp:14230:127"/> communicate. To ſuch perſons that be indeede trulie reſolued to ſerue God, licenſe may be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to communicate once in a fortnight, or once in eight daies. Some Doctors thinke that leaue<note place="margin">Soto in 4. diſt. 22. q. 1 ar. 10.</note> to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municat euery eight daies, ought not to bee giuen but to ſuch as be of rare vertue, but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the counſell of <hi>S. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustin,</hi> in theſe times where there is much frequenting of the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mentes, it may be granted to all them, which truly haue begon a newe life and doe with care a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoide and flie from great ſins.</p>
               <p>To ſuch as be very deuoute, and of whome they haue expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience that they do notably pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit by frequenting the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts and that they doe daily encreaſe in deuotion and puritie of life, they may grant leaue to commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate
<pb n="231" facs="tcp:14230:127"/> twiſe a weeke: and when any particular neceſſitie doeth occurre, or in perſons of greate perfection, or vpon ſome ſpecial deuotion, and hunger of this bread of life, for a weeke or two to communicate once more ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth not exceſſiue, albeit great reaſon there is, that the ghoſtlye father ſhoulde well conſider &amp; thinke vpon the matter, and not be moued ſo much for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of the penitents, as for that hee thinketh hee hath ſufficient reaſon ſo to doe.</p>
               <p>To ſuch perſons as haue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gonne to frequent the holy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, and doe reape litle pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit thereby, and experience tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth that they doe not ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, nor mortifie them ſelues as reaſon woulde, nor aſpire to more vertue and a better life,
<pb n="232" facs="tcp:14230:128"/> but that through their own fault they liue in a colde kinde of ſort, and want deuotion: conuenient it is to depriue them of ſome co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munions, to the ende they may learne to feare, and by that mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes humble themſelues, &amp; make more account of the B. ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, and to prepare themſelues vvith more deuotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for the receauing thereof: and eſpecially this kind of rigor and proofe is to be vſed towardes thoſe that deſire for their owne pleaſure to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>muni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate, and that as a thinge due to them of iuſtice, and bee grieued &amp; complaine if this leaue be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for this is a very greate preſumption, and plaine token, that ſuch ſoules, are farre from true humilitie, and the knowe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of their own vnworthynes, and of that reuerence vvhich
<pb n="233" facs="tcp:14230:128"/> they oughte to bringe vnto ſo heauenlie a banquet. And let not the ghoſtly father, any thing feare, that denying ſome tymes the ſacred communion to all ſuch perſons as theſe, and for ſuch cauſes as theſe be, that he doth them any harme, in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priuing them of that profitte, vvhich by communicating they mighte receaue, becauſe our Lorde that liketh wel to depriue his church of the infinite ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frages of holye Maſſes, by not giuing licence, ordinarily to ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrate anye more then once a daye, for to preſerue that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence, which is due to this moſt ſacred miſterie as before hath beene ſaide, it ſhall like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe<note place="margin">Cap. 21.</note> pleaſe him verye vvell, that ſuch perſons bee depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of many communions, to
<pb n="234" facs="tcp:14230:129"/> preſerue in them and others that reuerence which is due to this moſt holye ſacrament. And if they doe take this croſſe and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all in good parte, humblinge themſelues, and willingly obey, they take not harme, but profit, becauſe as holy Doctors affirme<note place="margin">D Bonau. 4. d. 12. ar. 4. q. 1. Soto in 4. d 11. q. 2. ar. 8.</note> and experience doth teache the ſame, that ſuch as come to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate with a colde kinde of deuotion, through their ovvne faulte, although they bee in the ſtate of grace, yet ſmall is the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of grace which this moſt diuine ſacrament doth vvorke, whereas it is moſt plentifull and wonderfull which it doth effect in them that come with that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition which is conuenient: &amp; ſo by that feare and humilitye which they conceaue by this pu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment it will come to paſſe
<pb n="235" facs="tcp:14230:129"/> that one communion will be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them more profitable, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny others, vnto which they come with careleſſe preparation: And ſufficient it is, that this is the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and counſell of holy men, that the ghoſtlye father, who is Gods ſeruant, may beleeue it &amp; effectually put it in practiſe: <hi>Saint</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In breuilo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quio p. 6. cap. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>Bonauenture</hi> ſpeaking of this verie matter hath theſe wordes. <hi>Thoſe which intende to communicate, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue themſelues not ſo pure, or doe finde themſelues without deuotion, let them take this counſell, and deſerre their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion vntill they be better prepared.</hi> And the holy man doth ſpeake of thoſe, who though they bee confeſſed and in good ſtate, yet through their neglige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce they finde themſelues ſomwhat cold, and drie, and not ſo pure from veniall ſinnes, and ſo deuout as
<pb n="236" facs="tcp:14230:130"/> were co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: for theſe he ſaith, that it is better &amp; more holſome counſel, to defer a day or ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what longer their communion, vntill they be better prepared.</p>
               <p>And to that which ſome may obiecte againſt this aduiſe, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that although it be good for a man to abſtaine from the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, vpon feare and reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, to ſo holy a miſtery: that yet it is better to come vnto it, vpon loue, and for deſire of ſo infinite good: the holye Doctor doth anſwere in theſe wordes: <hi>Both affections are commended &amp; prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the Scripture, and ſo we ſee that</hi> Zacheus <hi>is commended for that he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued readily &amp; with ioy our Sauiour</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In faſcicul. cap. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>into his houſe: and the Centurion prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, that for humilitie and reuerence and knowing his owne vnworthineſſe, and the maieſtie of our Lorde, hee did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech
<pb n="237" facs="tcp:14230:130"/> him not to enter vnder his roofe, and neceſſary it is for the holy communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to preſerue both theſe affections, and that we doe in ſuch manner reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence this moſte highe ſacramente, in which GOD himſelfe is giuen vs for meate, that in like ſorte we doe deſire it, and with confidence come vnto it: and that we doe in ſuch wiſe deſire it, and haue confidence in him, that we loſe not that feare and reuerence which wee owe vnto him. And althoughe loue of his owne nature be better then feare, yet in ſome caſes and in ſome perſons, the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of feare is more conuenient, &amp; it would be more hurtfull and dangerous to be carried away with deſire, and that affection which ſeemeth to bee of loue.</hi> All this is out of <hi>Saint Bonauenture</hi> And that which in briefe he wold ſay is, that he which is with puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty &amp; requiſit deuotion prepared for the holye communion, that
<pb n="238" facs="tcp:14230:131"/> it is better to receaue it, mooued with loue, then for feare to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine, but he that lacketh that diſpoſition, &amp; through his care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſneſſe is ſomewhat colde and indeuout, better it is, mooued with holy feare to deferre it for a day or more, vntill he be better furniſhed with deuotion: not do<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing this vpon his owne heade or pleaſure, but gouerned by the counſell of his ghoſtlye father. And to that which ſome mighte obiect, that by this meanes the profit which by often communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating might be gained is loſte, the holy man doth alſo anſwere in theſe wordes: <hi>To ſome it is more profitable to deferre ſomewhat the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, to the ende they may come vnto it afterwarde with more reuerence and deuotion: becauſe as I thinke, one recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth more fruite at one communion, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming
<pb n="239" facs="tcp:14230:131"/> well prepared, then by manye to which he commeth without any diligent preparation.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="chapter">
               <head>Chap. XXIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Wherein is declared, whether the holye communion ought daily to be giuen to ſome perſons of our time.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>OVt of this doctrine of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly men before mentioned and ſet down for a ground, we gather howe rare the vertue of that perſon ought to bee, to whome licence ſhould be gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted dailye to receaue the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſacrament, and how much, many ghoſtly fathers are decea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, that herein make no diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultie at all: And beſides the reaſon already alleadged, which is that holye men doe ſay that
<pb n="240" facs="tcp:14230:132"/> the perſons to whome this leaue ſhoulde be giuen, ought to be of that great purity of ſoule, and to haue that wonderfull burninge charity, which flouriſhed in the chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of the primatiue church when the heartes of all was but one, and the ſoule throughe the ſtraight bande of loue one, and and when charitye and mercye made the goodes of eache man common to all: beſides this rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, many other there be, worthy of greate conſideration, which here I will ſet downe. Moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine it is, that who ſoeuer doth communicate euery day, that his ghoſtly father doth giue him an open teſtimonie, that hee is one of very ſingular vertue, for this is a generall receaued opinion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong all people, that it doeth not pertaine to anye, dailye to
<pb n="241" facs="tcp:14230:132"/> communicate but to holy per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons: and thereforre it is a thinge vvell to be conſidered, how great daunger of preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and vaine glorye it is for weake ſoules, and ſubiecte to tentation, althoughe very de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoute and vertuous, that they ſhoulde vnderſtande that their ghoſtly father hath ſuch an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of theire vertue: and that people looke vpon them vvith ſuche eyes, and ſuche a conceite of holye perſons. Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant wee are not, and expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience teacheth, howe paſſinge harde it is, to ouercome well the temptation of honor and vvorldly praiſe when it is offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, as <hi>Sainte Auguſtine</hi> doth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellently note in theſe vvords. <hi>How great forces the loue of honor and</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Epiſt. 64 ad Aurelium</note> 
                  <hi>worldely praiſe hath to ouercome ones
<pb n="242" facs="tcp:14230:133"/> ſoule, and to make it fall, none knowe but hee that hath much foughte againſt that tentation, for although there bee no great difficultie to abſtaine from honour and praiſe when they are denied a man, yet when they are offered, very hard it is not to take vaine pleaſure therein:</hi> Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant alſo we are not, howe by offering themſelues to the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of this tentation in recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing honor and worldly praiſe, many perſons of a good &amp; rare life, and thoſe which with great trauaile had gotten much ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, and great ſtore of ſpirituall riches, in the ſeruice of God, in<note place="margin">Homil. 3 in 1. Iohan. &amp; hom. 17. in cap. 10. ad Roman.</note> ſhort time loſte all, as <hi>Saint Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome</hi> affirmeth: becauſe vvhen vaine glory did tempt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, they were ouercome and pitifully o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertaken with that vice, in ſuch ſorte, that leauing the creator, they put their chiefe felicitye in
<pb n="243" facs="tcp:14230:133"/> the creature. Seing then it is ſo harde to ouercome the tentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of honor and worldly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation when it is offered, &amp; that ſo many perſons famous for vertue, haue vpon theſe rocks ſuffered ſhip-wracke, and beene caſt away in this tempeſt, no ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient reaſon there is that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creete ghoſtly fathers, ſhoulde offer weake and feeble ſoules, though neuer ſo deuoute &amp; ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous, to ſo great a danger: but rather neceſſary it is, that they ſhoulde noriſh them in true hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie, labor to haue them well rooted in that vertue, &amp; to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue them therein: and to effect this, very conuenient it is, that the ghoſtly father ſhoulde by no meanes let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnderſtande that others haue any greate conceite and opinion of them, and that he
<pb n="244" facs="tcp:14230:134"/> ſhould, what hee can conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently, take from them the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of all pride, as ſingular things be, which may make them to be famous in the ſight of the worlde, and any thinge elſe that may bring them honor and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation: and to induce them what he can to conceale all ſhew of holineſſe, according to that which elſe where hath bene ſaid, entreating of the vertue of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility. And certaine it is, that many ghoſtlye fathers becauſe they haue without diſcretion, commended their ſpiritull chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, ſet out their vertues, and giuen them occaſion to make o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtentatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thereof, that they haue beene the cauſe that many ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der plantes haue with the nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therne winde of pride withered: &amp; many that were well growne,
<pb n="245" facs="tcp:14230:134"/> haue by the iuſte iudgement of God, bin pulled vp by the roots, whome for their ingratitude and vanitie he hath permitted to fall. To this may bee added that by granting ſuch leaue, they giue occaſion to others that be yet in firme and not ſo well prepared, that they alſo be ſtirred vp with emulation, and doe deſire and procure the ſame, and that with out the counſell and leaue of their ghoſtly father they venture vpon it, ſuppoſing it to be very well donne, ſeing the like leaue is giuen to others, who are in their opinion but litle their ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periors in vertue. They be the occaſion alſo that when any ſuch perſon turne backewarde, that frequentinge of the holye ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, is much infamed and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credited among worldly men, &amp;
<pb n="246" facs="tcp:14230:135"/> that their tongues doe readilye ſpeak euill both of the penitents that come often vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; alſo of their ghoſtly fathers. And rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon it is, as much as we may with out any preiudice to vertue, that we ſhoulde not giue anye ſuch occaſion to weake people. Out of theſe reaſons we haue to learn, that in theſe times thoſe perſons which may daily come to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly communion, ought to be paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing wel grounded in profounde humility, and ſo tried with iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, contempts, &amp; diuers kindes of tribulation, vntill they come to loue them, and to thirſt after them, and that they be fortified with perfect and ſound vertues like vnto <hi>Saint Clare,</hi> or <hi>Saint Ka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therine</hi> of Sienna, that the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then of theſe tentations doe not make them to fall: and that their
<pb n="247" facs="tcp:14230:135"/> rare and extraordinarye vertue be ſo great, and ſo well knowne, that all emulation of others may be cut of, and ſuch inconuenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces as hath now bene ſpoken of, and others which may be obie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted. For certaine it is, that in the primatiue church, thoſe which did dailye communicate were of great vertue as hath bin ſaid, and that in theſe daies, ſuch ſpeciall perſons to whome this licenſe is to be giuen, requiſit it is, that they ſhould be furniſhed vvith more vertue, then that which was at that time common and vſuall among chriſtians, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that being then the cuſto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e and common vſe, the tentation of emulation, and other occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons before mentioned had no place: For none had anye cauſe to think that he was reputed far
<pb n="248" facs="tcp:14230:136"/> more holy then other, for, hauing that leaue granted which was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to all: nor any coulde take occaſion of enuie or emulation, ſeing themſelues might doe that which they ſawe others do. And if any thinke that it doth hereof follow, that fewe will be founde to whome licence daily may bee now giuen, becauſe they be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry rare that be of ſuch ſingular and eminent vertue, and be free from thoſe occaſions and incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, which before haue bin ſpoken of, I ſay that moſt true it is, &amp; that hereof no harme doth followe, but the more glory of God, and very great profitte to mens ſoules, for as much as here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by that is donne which is moſte conuenient in reſpect of that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence which is due to the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Sacrament, and the occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="249" facs="tcp:14230:136"/> of many ſinnes are cut of, &amp; good people be the more ſtirred vp to haue the holy communion in greater reputation, &amp; to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare them ſelues for the recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing thereof, with more reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, more puritie, and deuoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: ſo that by this meanes, one communion is more profitable vnto them, then manye others woulde be, as before hath beene ſaid. And by doing thus we do alſo faithfully obſerue the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of the goſpell &amp; holy men: for by this kind of obedience we performe that which the lawe of loue doeth require in the vſe of the holy ſacrament, by takinge the benefite of that large leaue, which wee haue graunted in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pairing oft to the holy ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, and yet wee doe not forget that holye feare and due reuerence,
<pb n="250" facs="tcp:14230:137"/> which ought to bee ioyned with loue. And for a coucluſion, let Gods ſeruant perſwade himſelf, that althoughe he oughte to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, and to endeuor often to come vnto the holy communion with due modeſty, yet his prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall care ought to be, that whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hee communicateth that it bee donne well, and with that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which is requiſit: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let him prouide him ſelfe with great humility, acknovve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging himſelfe farre vnworthy to come vnto the holy commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and placing himſelfe, with contempt of himſelfe, in the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry bottome of his owne vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynes, let him come with great purity, extending his contrition and the purpoſe of amendment to all his ſinnes, both greate and ſmall, which he hath both com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted
<pb n="251" facs="tcp:14230:137"/> and may commit: Let him alſo for the purchaſing of this purity, helpe him ſelfe with the ſacrament of confeſſion, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though his conſcience doeth not accuſe him of any other ſins the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> veniall, and thoſe alſo of the leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer ſort: Let him come with great hunger of this diuine banquet, and with a liuely deſire, to vnite himſelfe vnto God with moſte feruent loue by meanes thereof: Let him come offering himſelfe whollie &amp; perfectly to performe his diuine will. O what an hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenlye ſtore-houſe of ſpirituall medicines ſhall he finde, for the curing of all the woundes &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities of his ſoule: O what an holy table full of diuine food, and celeſtiall comforts ſhall hee haue, to ſatiſfie his hunger, to ſtrengthen his weakeneſſe, and
<pb n="252" facs="tcp:14230:138"/> to glad his hearte and make it ioyfull: O what a riche ſhoppe and plentifull, ſhall he finde full of diuine vertues, and iewelles, full of ſpirituall and celeſtiall gifts, to adorne and beautifie his ſoule: O what Indies ſhall he meete with, to enrich it with heauenly wealth, diuine furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and the treaſures of Gods grace. Bleſſed bee our good Lorde, and magnified bee his holy name for euer, who fo bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully &amp; in ſuch plentiful man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, hath opened the bowelles of his infinite and vnſpeakable mercy, that by one diuine and ſacred morſel, which pure ſoules doe with ſo greate comfort, and ſweetnes receaue in this moſte heauenly banquet, he hath vout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafed to beſtowe vpon vs mortal men all thoſe goodes, and ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall
<pb n="253" facs="tcp:14230:138"/> riches, which for the ſpace of three and thirty yeares liuing in the pilgrimage of this life, and vale of miſery: yea ſuffering, and at laſt alſo dying vpon the Croſſe, hee did gaine &amp; purchaſe for vs moſt vnworthy and miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable ſinners.</p>
            </div>
            <pb facs="tcp:14230:139"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14230:140"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14230:141"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
